<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="/Dear-Charlotte/xslt/page.xslt"?>
<page>
	<meta>
		<description>Episode 10: Breakdown. Gan's limiter goes wonky and he turns into an angry caveman. The crew set sail for XK-72, a neutral space station, so they can get his head fixed up nice. On the way they fly through a gravitational vortex, so that we can have freaky wobbly shots of the cast looking scared. They borrow the neurosurgeon from XK-72, but he turns out to be a rotter and phones up some pursuit ships, then delays the operation on Gan. Blake forces him to work, then sends him back to his space station, and legs it. A stray blast from one of the pursuit ships destroys the base, but it's OK, because Gan has a funny brain.</description>
		<path>/series-1/episode-10-breakdown/</path>
		<type>episode</type>
	</meta>
	<content type="main">
		<h1>Episode 10: Breakdown</h1>

		<p>In the last episode Travis hatched an elaborate plan involving moles, death stink-bombs, fake escapes and two different flavours of robot. Blake foiled his plans with the help of Jenna, Vila, Gan and Avon. This week, Avon's loyalty is tested when Blake flies into danger, in order to save Gan.</p>
		<p>We get a proper scratch-build model establishing shot, which is always a treat<note>There's some lovely model work in this episode</note>. Gan's on duty on the bridge and starts gurning something rotten. ACTING:</p>

		<blockquote class="imgur-embed-pub" lang="en" data-id="a/wH56D"><a href="//imgur.com/wH56D"></a></blockquote><script async="" src="//s.imgur.com/min/embed.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
		
		<char>
			<h2>Gurning</h2>
			<p>Fun fact for you. <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=cKRa06hP6vc" title="Sylvester McCoy to Paul McGann regeneration scene">Sylvester McCoy's gurning</a> was so effective they were able to reduce the effects they used to regenerate him into Paul McGann. They must have saved, ohh, pounds. Which they then wasted making the rest of that terrible <jargon type="TV"/> movie.</p>
		</char>

		<p>At the same time, <em>The Liberator</em> is caught in an asteroid field. Jenna runs in, turns off manual control and tells Zen to take evasive action.</p>
		
		<ross>
			<p>This is quite a subtle nod to the second theme in this episode (I'll come to the main theme in a bit), that of how much the crew of <em>The Liberator</em> are reliant on Zen for countless little tasks he performs in the background.</p>
		</ross>
		
		<h2>You've been sacked</h2>
		<p>Gan goes berserk and throws Jenna down some stairs then drags her unconscious body like a caveman. Blake enters and tries to reason with him, but instead, they do some <jargon type="RADA"/> fighting, but it's shot with a handheld camera, which is a bit interesting<note>The director, Vere Lorrimer, makes a few brave choices in this episode.</note>.</p>
		<p>Vila and Avon join in the barney but it's only once Avon gets a good shot in on Gan's balls that he goes down like a sack of potatoes.</p>
		<p>They slap a couple of tranquiliser patches on him and carry him to the medical room. Avon asks Zen for an amazingly detailed status report<note>Perhaps he's just lonely.</note>.</p>
		
		<ross>
			<h2>Blog notification</h2>
			<p>I've approached Charlotte for feedback on the blog and I was granted an audience with her, while she sat on her throne (constructed from a hollowed-out Dalek). <q>More cats</q>, was all she'd say. I pressed her for clarification. <q>MORE CATS</q>, she repeated, sipping tea from the skull of Michael Grade.</p>
			<p>Unfortunately, I'm <em>terrible</em> at anthropomorphism. And by <q>terrible</q>, I mean I'm not very good at it.</p>
			<p>In the unlikely event you want to get rid of the cats, just click on them. This is exactly as effective as getting rid of a <em>real</em> cat.</p>
		</ross>
		
		<h2>Gurner on a gurney</h2>
		<p>While Jenna examines Gan's limiter, Cally notices that Gan is making a fist and relaxing it, over and over again. They strap him to the gurney<note>THIS IS FUNNY BECAUSE GAN SPENDS MOST OF THE EPISODE GURNING!</note>, with these sort of future-restraints, which look like the sort of thing you'd find in a scientist's lab in an old horror film, but because they're from the future, they've got there little lights on them.</p>
		<p>Vila presses a switch which makes Gan do a Nazi salute:</p>

		<blockquote class="imgur-embed-pub" lang="en" data-id="a/JHR14"><a href="//imgur.com/JHR14"></a></blockquote><script async="" src="//s.imgur.com/min/embed.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
		
		<figure class="purhundi">
			<img SRC="/Dear-Charlotte/img/the-purhundi.png" alt=""/>
			<figcaption class="details">I have no concept of cause-and-effect.</figcaption>
		</figure>

		<p>Perhaps it's a left brain / right brain thing.</p>
	
		<h2><jargon type="DIY"/></h2>
		<p>Blake wonders if they can do the brain operation themselves. Avon disagrees. <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=5CNiBFrEnWk" title="The Medibot testcard, from Look Around You">Medibot</a> tells them, in the manner of a sexually jaded Headmaster, that they need to get Gan's bonce cracked open sharpish.</p>
		<p>The crew debate as to which planet they should take Gan to - time is short and most planets within a reasonable distance are hostile. Avon suggests <a href="http://www.xk72.com/" title="The quote under the heading is from Avon">XK-72</a>, a research station he was planning to hide out in, if everything goes south. XK-72 is neutral, so they probably won't turn Blake over to the Federation.</p>

		<h2>Here be dragons</h2>
		<p>Zen didn't include XK-72 in his calculations of where to get Gan's noggin checked out because there's an area of space between <em>The Liberator</em> and the station is marked as having <q cite="http://blakes7.wikia.com/wiki/Breakdown_(dialogue_transcript)">unacceptable risk</q> associated with it. That's literally all Zen knows: they keep quizzing the big brown hemisphere, but all he'll say is that there ain't no data. Blake tries to plot a direct course to XK-72, but Zen refuses, claiming the instruction <q cite="http://blakes7.wikia.com/wiki/Breakdown_(dialogue_transcript)">reduces to an order to self-destruct</q><note>This is a nice nod to <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Three_Laws_of_Robotics">Asimov's three laws of robotics</a>.</note>.</p>

		<p>Blake asks Jenna to take them in manually.</p>
		
		<h2>The system has encountered an unknown error, and will be shut down</h2>
		<p>As <em>The Liberator</em> enters the <q cite="http://blakes7.wikia.com/wiki/Breakdown_(dialogue_transcript)">prohibited zone</q>, Zen shuts down a bunch of his background systems in protest. Avon has second thoughts about their route, but Jenna is like <q>it's cool, it's cool</q>. Blake sends Avon to override Zen's shutdown, probably to get him out of Jenna's hair.</p>
		<p>Vila picks up something weak on the scanners. <em>The Liberator</em>'s speed increases, almost like it's getting pulled toward something.</p>

		<h2>Not a morning person</h2>
		<p>Gan wakes up and tells Cally he's feeling tired and wants to sit up, so she should release his restraints. She releases him and he immediately gives her a good strangling. It's interrupted by some space turbulence and Cally is thrown across the room to the unconscious corner where she immediately busies herself with being unconscious. Gan does some gurning and then runs out of the room<note>Note that only exceptional actors could gurn <em>while</em> running out of the room.</note>.</p>
		<p>Avon manages to bypass Zen's protest by making a bank of lights go green, but it's too late: <em>The Liberator</em> is trapped in a gravitational vortex, which looks a bit like when you dyed your hair violet that summer then pulled the plug out the sink and then you couldn't get the sink to look normal and your mum was furious with you and your eyebrows looked weird.</p>
		
		<char>
			<p>Hairdye: nothing to do with science fiction, but never try to save money by buying your 'two tone double impact' hair dye from the Wilkies cheapo bin. Unless 'my little pony' was the look you were going for.</p>
		</char>

		<p>Cally stumbles onto the bridge and admits that she let Gan go, and he's now loose on the ship. Blake goes to look for him.</p>

		<h2>Percussive maintenance</h2>
		<p>In the computer room, Gan bursts in like a space-viking and starts fighting Avon<note>He's probably wanting to make up for the kick in the balls.</note>. Then he starts punching Zen right up his circuits, because fighting is ace. He catches a bonk on the bonce, right in the limiter, because of space-turbulence, then writhes on the floor for a spell.</p>
		<p>Avon decides he's had enough: if they survive the vortex, he's going to leave Blake's crew and take all of his computer probes with him.</p>
		
		<char>
			<h2>We want your brains</h2>
			<p>For some reason this episode reminds me of the Invisible Enemy. Because of the strange temporal vortex distortion that separated Australia from the <jargon type="UK"/> in the 80s, (at least in terms of <jargon type="TV"/>,) I watched the story for the first time in 1989. It also featured meteorites, an invisible force and something trying to get the Dr's brain. (The fourth Dr's brain has particular attraction for baddies. Solon was also keen. Maybe it's the hair?)</p>
			<p>Tom Baker does appear strapped to a gurney. He does not gurn. Instead he does that angsty faced curling uppy / twisty thing that he does so well when showing mental torment.</p>
			<p>That just shows what a terribly super and much underrated actor he is. FACT.</p>
		</char>
		
		<figure class="purhundi">
			<img SRC="/Dear-Charlotte/img/the-purhundi.png" alt=""/>
			<figcaption class="details">I don't ignore you out of passive-aggression. It's because I find your eye contact intimidating and aggressive.</figcaption>
		</figure>

		<ross>
			<p>This is the point where the episode's theme is introduced: loyalty. Blake's loyalty has led him to risk his life, the lives of his crew and also <em>The Liberator</em>, in order to save Gan's life.</p>
			<p>Blake wants Avon to stay with the crew, but makes no attempt to persuade him, even going out of his way to be rude to him. He only wants Avon in his crew if he can count on his loyalty.</p>
		</ross>
		
		<blockquote class="imgur-embed-pub" lang="en" data-id="a/SxZAt"><a href="//imgur.com/SxZAt">The Liberator goes through a gravity vortex</a></blockquote><script async="" src="//s.imgur.com/min/embed.js" charset="utf-8"></script>

		<p><em>The Liberator</em> is trapped in the gravitational vortex, so Blake decides to go through the middle of it, because what the hell: they're going to die either way. There is a <jargon type="TMS"/>, but they get out of it, because someone (Jenna?) manages to hit the <q cite="http://blakes7.wikia.com/wiki/Breakdown_(dialogue_transcript)">automatics</q> button<note>Presumably Avon's tinkering enabled the automatics again, but they weren't switched on until this point.</note>.</p>
		<p><em>The Liberator</em> arrives as XK-72 and Blake tells them they're an experimental Earth ship. The station agrees to let them come aboard and meet their neurosurgeon. Blake teleports into an office where Farren, the administrator and Professor Kayn, the Neurosurgeon, are talking about <em>The Liberator</em>. You can tell they're both important, because they've got three silver stripes on each shoulder.</p>
		
		<biog>
			<src>/img/characters/farren.png</src>
			<info type="Name">Farren</info>
			<info type="Job">Administrator</info>
			<info type="Dramatic role">Bureaucratic speed bump</info>
			<info type="Ambition">To have his own signature line of stationery</info>
			<info type="Catch phrase"><q cite="http://blakes7.wikia.com/wiki/Breakdown_(dialogue_transcript)">This behaviour will have to be noted down in the station log</q></info>
			<info type="Baker number"><a href="http://oracleofbacon.org/movielinks.php?a=Tom+Baker+(I)&amp;b=Ian+Thompson+(I)">2</a></info>
		</biog>
		
		<char>
			<figure class="img-r">
				<img SRC="/Dear-Charlotte/img/series-1/episode-10-breakdown/zarbi.jpg" alt=""/>
				<figcaption><em>Doctor Who and the Zarbi</em> or <em>When Insects Attack</em></figcaption>
			</figure>
			<p>Ian Thompson, who plays Farren, was in a bunch of Doctor Who episodes including <em>The Death of Time</em>, <em>The Centre</em>, <em>Invasion</em> and <em>Crater of Needles</em>. That was when they didn't bother naming whole stories, just individual episodes. Much like film noir being a sort of post-adopted title for a genre (after thought perhaps?) they only linked together the episodes and named the stories later, possibly for the <jargon type="TV"/> novelisations.</p>
			<p>He's in one called <em>The Web Planet</em> (or <em>Doctor Who and the Zarbi</em> if you're reading the book). These weird moth people are enslaved by something called the Animus, who achieves domination by taking over the planet's other inhabitants: massive ants. It's a chilling tale of slavery and cruelty, only involving big insects and costumes which are reaaaaallly rubbish.</p>
		</char>
		
		<biog>
			<src>/img/characters/kayn.png</src>
			<info type="Name">Professor Kayn</info>
			<info type="Job">Neurosurgeon</info>
			<info type="Metal level"><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=otuVawEShi4" title="That Limmy sketch where it is explained that A-ha are metal">A-ha</a></info>
			<info type="Dramatic role">Antagonist</info>
			<info type="Baker number"><a href="http://oracleofbacon.org/movielinks.php?a=Tom+Baker+(I)&amp;b=Julian+Glover">1</a></info>
		</biog>
		
		<ross>
			<p>Kayn is played by <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Julian_Glover">Julian Glover</a> who might as well be Kevin Bacon, as far as <jargon type="sci-fi"/> and fantasy goes. He's been in <em>The Empire Strikes Back</em>, <em>Indiana Jones</em> and <em>Game of Thrones</em>. Charlotte! Say something about his appearance in <em>Doctor Who</em>:</p>
		</ross>
		
		<char>
			<p>Julian Glover plays one of my very favourite Doctor Who villains of all time in <em><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=nH48k3utGHw" title="Quite a good City of Death fan trailer">City of Death</a></em>. The story, involving some aliens stealing the Mona Lisa, is known for its Paris location, extremely witty script (largely written by Douglas Adams) and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=-EPLY9XG5nU" title=" Eleabor Bron and John Cleese's cameo in 'City of Death'">a cameo by John Cleese and Eleabor Bron</a>. Oh and THAT outfit Romana wears. If you only watch one story, watch this. Glover's character is expressionlessly cruel, suave and beautiful. He even manages to retain his elegance whilst pulling off his false face to reveal...a lettuce man.</p>
		</char>

		<h2>House call</h2>
		<p>Blake and Kayn teleport back to <em>The Liberator</em>. Kayn had originally assumed that <em>The Liberator</em> is Federation, but as he looks around, he begins to doubt this. Blake sends Avon back to XK-72 for Kayn's equipment and assistant, then takes Kayn to visit their pet monkey, Gan.</p>
		<p>Avon calls in to say he won't be coming back to <em>The Liberator</em> with Kayn's assistant, as he's <q cite="http://blakes7.wikia.com/wiki/Breakdown_(dialogue_transcript)">staying for a look around</q> XK-72.</p>
		<p>Blake sends in Jenna to talk to Renor, Kayn's assistant. He wants her to get information about Kayn, using her [WINK] feminine [WINK] wiles. Luckily Renor is a class one lounge lizard:</p>

		<biog>
			<src>/img/characters/renor.png</src>
			<info type="Name">Renor</info>
			<info type="Job">Brain-nurse</info>
			<info type="Dramatic role">Surprisingly sympathetic sex-pest</info>
			<info type="Look-a-like">Sam Rockwell</info>
			<info type="Hobbies">Carpet-bombing, dry-roasting, home-brewing, pickling his own onions</info>
			<info type="Baker number"><a href="https://oracleofbacon.org/movielinks.php?a=Tom+Baker+(I)&amp;b=Christian+Roberts+(I)">2</a></info>
		</biog>
		
		<p>You can tell that Renor is less important, because he's only got <em>one</em> silver stripe on each shoulder.</p>

		<p>On XK-72, Avon is offering Farren teleporter technology. Before he'll negotiate, he asks Farren to guarantee the safety of Blake and his crew.</p>
		
		<figure class="purhundi">
			<img SRC="/Dear-Charlotte/img/the-purhundi.png" alt=""/>
			<figcaption class="details">When I lie on my back, it's to show you that you're dominant. When you touch my belly, it feels like a terrible betrayal of trust.</figcaption>
		</figure>
		<ross>
			<p>Avon wants to negotiate a new life on XK-72, by bargaining away either <em>The Liberator</em> or the technology on board. Farren wants to protect XK-72 and avoid contact with the Federation. The scene is a negotiation between a cynical, manipulative thief and a naive bureaucrat. As the scene progresses, the camera moves slowly in on their faces. This <em>should</em> build tension.</p>
			<p>The performances are fine, but the flat studio lighting does nothing to suggest a real location. As with so much in <em>Blake's 7</em>, perhaps a larger budget and longer time would have resulted in a more powerful scene.</p>
		</ross>
		
		<figure class="img-r">
			<img SRC="/Dear-Charlotte/img/series-1/episode-10-breakdown/blackberry.jpg" alt=""/>
			<figcaption>Kayn uses a Blackberry, in product placement which was approximately thirty years ahead of its time.</figcaption>
		</figure>

		<h2>Doctor's orders</h2>
		<p>On <em>The Liberator</em>, Kayn tells Renor that what they've assumed to be a Federation ship, is that of the fugitive Blake. They argue: Kayn wants to give Blake to the Federation and Renor feels they have a duty of care to Gan. Kayn describes the Federation as <q cite="http://blakes7.wikia.com/wiki/Breakdown_(dialogue_transcript)">progress</q>. Renor counters with <q cite="http://blakes7.wikia.com/wiki/Breakdown_(dialogue_transcript)">progress with what, <em>brain implantation</em>?</q>. Kayn says <q cite="http://blakes7.wikia.com/wiki/Breakdown_(dialogue_transcript)">A dangerous psychopath? Certainly</q>. Kayn uses his Blackberry to contact the nearest Federation base, which dispatches three pursuit ships. Farren is upset because he thought only he had the password to the official XK-72 Twitter account, and now Kayn's gone and used it to @ the Federation.</p>
		
		<ul class="tarial">
			<li>
				<header class="clearfix">
					<i class="tarial-xk-72">&#160;</i>
					<section>
						<h3>XK-72: Independent secret laboritory for weaponry and space medicine</h3
					>
						<p><a href="#farren">@xk-72</a></p>
					</section>
				</header>
				<blockquote><a href="/">@FederationCommand</a>: the fugative Blake is currently docked to XK-72. Please send pursuit ships to apprehend him. #order #progress</blockquote>
			</li>
			<li>
				<header class="clearfix">
					<i class="tarial-federation">&#160;</i>
					<section>
						<h3>The Federation: order through strength</h3>
						<p><a href="/">@FEDERATION</a></p>
					</section>
				</header>
				<blockquote><a href="#farren">@xk-72</a>: I'm afraid no one is available to reply to your message right now. Please hold on. Your message is important to The Federation. All data is valid.</blockquote>
			</li>
			<li>
				<header class="clearfix">
					<i class="tarial-prell">&#160;</i>
					<section>
						<h3>Prell, Encryption specialist by day, lover by night</h3>
						<p><a href="/series-1/episode-6-seek-locate-destroy/#prell">@theRealPrell</a></p>
					</section>
				</header>
				<blockquote>Hey, <a href="#farren">@xk-72</a>: Do you still have that contract with Blackberry? Because they SUUUUUUUUUUUUUUK! #zune4life #micro$oft</blockquote>
			</li>
			<li>
				<header class="clearfix">
					<i class="tarial-sinofar">&#160;</i>
					<section>
						<h3>Sinofar</h3>
						<p><a href="/series-1/episode-8-duel/#sinofar">@sinofartheguardian</a></p>
					</section>
				</header>
				<blockquote><a href="/series-1/episode-6-seek-locate-destroy/#prell">@prell</a> <a href="#farren">@xk-72</a> ha ha - great bants, guys. Have you seen my Etsy shop? <a href="https://www.etsy.com/uk/shop/heartsandguns">#heartsandguns</a> #crafty #handmade</blockquote>
			</li>
			<li>
				<header class="clearfix">
					<i class="tarial-sonheim">&#160;</i>
					<section>
						<h3>Sonheim</h3>
						<p><a href="/series-1/episode-7-mission-to-destiny/#sonheim">@MisterSonheim</a></p>
					</section>
				</header>
				<blockquote><a href="/series-1/episode-8-duel/#sinofar">@sinofar</a> that sounds really interesting do you model your own stuff? I am a keen photographer in my spare time. #yolo</blockquote>
			</li>
			<li>
				<header class="clearfix">
					<i class="tarial-federation">&#160;</i>
					<section>
						<h3>The Federation: order through strength</h3>
						<p><a href="/">@FEDERATION</a></p>
					</section>
				</header>
				<blockquote><a href="#farren">@xk-72</a>: Message received. Pursuit ships inbound. You shall be rewarded, citizen.</blockquote>
			</li>
		</ul>
		
		<ross>
			<p>What if Kayn's right and Gan is a psychopath, only restrained from murder by his <jargon type="EBE"/>?</p>
		</ross>

		<h2>Priority treatment</h2>
		<p>On the bridge, Cally, Jenna and Vila are becoming suspicious of how long Gan's operation is taking. Uncharacteristically, Vila takes a blaster off the wall, and leaves to confront Kayn.</p>
		<p>Farren tells Avon that the pursuit ships are on their way, then offers Avon a place on XK-72. Avon agrees, but says he needs to return to <em>The Liberator</em> to <q cite="http://blakes7.wikia.com/wiki/Breakdown_(dialogue_transcript)">collect a few things</q><note>It's his probes. It's <em>always</em> his probes.</note>.</p>
		<p>Vila confronts Kayn with a blaster and tells him to start the operation. Avon arrives and tells Vila that the pursuit ships are on their way. Kayn starts the operation, but says that any movement of <em>The Liberator</em> could endanger Gan. Blake gives him twenty minutes to complete the operation, and if he hasn't completed it by then, Blake will <em>destroy his beautiful hands</em>.</p>
		
		<h2>Voided warranty</h2>
		<p>There is a non-trippy montage sequence, involving Gan doing a Nazi salute, <jargon type="ECG"/> monitors and some light soldering. Kayn completes the operation, is teleported back to XK-72 then <em>The Liberator</em> pulls away as fast as its three prong-things can carry it<note>If it was <em>Star Trek</em>, they'd be called <q cite="http://memory-alpha.wikia.com/wiki/Nacelle">nacelles</q>.</note>. Or perhaps its green bell-end makes it move. I'm not sure.</p>
		
		<h2>Your call has been terminated</h2>
		<p>Kayn argues with Farren, who's irritated that Kayn has violated the station's neutrality. Kayn wants to fire weapons on Blake and Farren wants to stop him. They start to scuffle and Kayn beats him (perhaps to death) with a phone receiver.</p>
		<p><em>The Liberator</em> encounters the pursuit ships and there's some plasma bold action. One of the pursuit ship's bolts <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=sCoHT_cHPzY" title="The incidental dialogue sequence from Mass Effect 2, where they describe the etiquette for shooting things in space">goes wide</a> and heads toward XK-72. As the fire crew desperately call out to Farren for instructions, Kayn stares at his beautiful hands, over Farren's corpse. The bolt destroys XK-72, like a bloody firework<note>Well, they do do weapons research. Perhaps they've got a bunch of explosives on board. Or, I dunno, fireworks?</note>:</p>
		
		<blockquote class="imgur-embed-pub" lang="en" data-id="a/oG7SI"><a href="//imgur.com/oG7SI"></a></blockquote><script async="" src="//s.imgur.com/min/embed.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
		
		<ross>
			<p>If you watch the above explosion long enough, you can see the smoke rising and the sparks falling, despite it taking place in zero gravity. I used to find this annoying as a child. Why couldn't they shoot the model from above or below, so that this effect was disguised?<note>Probably because it would ruin the camera with smoke or debris, I suppose.</note>.</p>
		</ross>
		
		<figure class="purhundi">
			<img SRC="/Dear-Charlotte/img/the-purhundi.png" alt=""/>
			<figcaption class="details">If only you could feel the exquisite joy which comes from taking another creature's life.</figcaption>
		</figure>

		<p>Avon says the line <q cite="http://blakes7.wikia.com/wiki/Breakdown_(dialogue_transcript)">say goodbye to one <em>bolt</em> hole</q>, which sounds like <a href="https://youtu.be/wpvQoXFtWqw?t=20s" title="Compilation of Bond one liners">a line from James Bond</a>, but isn't supposed to be.</p>
		
		<ross>
			<p>This would have been a nice <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=EnViskuZrJk" title="The end of the Star Trek episode 'City on the Edge of Forever'">City on the Edge of Forever</a> style ending, but unfortunately, we've not had the payoff of Gan waking up and being normal again.</p>
		</ross>
		
		<p>Gan wakes up and there's a very <em>Star Trek</em>-style laughy-jokey ending.</p>
		
		<char>
			<p>The 'laughing uncontrollably at something not very funny' ending is one they often used in the Doctor Who as well. I always HATED it. I mean; now when I tell people just how good <em>Seeds of Doom</em> is and force them to watch all six episodes, I have to fast forward the ending in order to maintain my air of authority. Or sort of distract their attention by spilling my tea or something. The indignity.</p>
		</char>

		<ross>
			<p>It <em>could</em> be that the final shot of the episode was taken at the end of a very long day, and everyone was a bit tired. Or perhaps Gan <em>is</em> a psychopath, and it has a sinister undertone:</p>
		</ross>

		<blockquote class="screenplay">
			<header>
				<p><b>B</b><b>B</b><b>C</b> <b>tv</b></p>
				<h2>Blake's 7</h2>
				<h3>&quot;Breakdown&quot;</h3>
			</header>

			<p><abbr title="Interior">Int</abbr>. bridge. Jenna is mopping Gan's brow. Vila stands on his other side.</p>
			<dl>
				<dt>Blake</dt>
				<dd><ins>(to Gan)</ins> How d'you feel?</dd>
				<dt>Gan</dt>
				<dd>I feel like someone's been poking around inside my head - with their foot!</dd>
				<dt>Vila</dt>
				<dd><ins>(to Gan)</ins> We had to kick your brain a couple of times to get it started!</dd>
				<dt>Gan</dt>
				<dd><ins>(to Vila)</ins> Only twice? <ins>(He smiles, unconvincingly. To Blake)</ins> They didn't remove the limiter?</dd>
				<dt>Cally</dt>
				<dd>It was not possible.</dd>
				<dt>Vila</dt>
				<dd>They've modified it, though: your ears glow in the dark now. <ins>(Gan laughs, but it looks like he's dying inside)</ins></dd>
				<dt>Blake</dt>
				<dd><ins>(Walking round behind Gan, and resting a hand on his shoulder)</ins> Let me know when you're ready for work.</dd>
				<dt>Gan</dt>
				<dd><ins>(Flatly)</ins>Thanks.</dd>
				<dt>Blake</dt>
				<dd>Oh by the way - welcome back <ins>(They all start laughing, as if Blake has said something terribly funny. Gan's pain is clearly visible in his eyes)</ins></dd>
			</dl>

			<footer class="clearfix">
				<p>Commercial and in confidence</p>
				<p>Page 50 of 52</p>
			</footer>
		</blockquote>

		<h2>Watch <em>Breakdown</em> on YouTube</h2>
		<youtube id="JYuRAbIz22Q"/>
	</content>
</page>