<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="/Dear-Charlotte/xslt/page.xslt"?>
<page>
	<meta>
		<description>Series 1 of Blake's 7.</description>
		<path>/Dear-Charlotte/series-1/</path>
	</meta>
	<content type="main">
		<h1>Series 1 of <em>Blake's 7</em></h1>
		<p>Terry Nation created <em>Blake's 7</em> and wrote all thirteen  episodes of the first series<note>It's perhaps worth noting here that Nation was under huge pressure and as the writing process collided with the shooting, relatively early drafts of scripts had to be fleshed out slightly by Chris Boucher and Pennant Roberts.</note>. This huge undertaking suggests that the first series of <em>Blake's 7</em> was primarily Nation's vision for the show. In later series, others would take over his writing role, building further on his work.</p>
		<p>The episodes in series one could be slotted into various arbitrary categories. For example:</p>
		
		<figure class="img-r">
			<img src="/Dear-Charlotte/img/series-1/the-way-back-opening-shot.jpg" alt=""/>
			<figcaption>The opening shot of <em><a href="/Dear-Charlotte/series-1/episode-1-the-way-back/">The Way Back</a></em>.</figcaption>
		</figure>

		<h2>World building</h2>
		<p>It's the responsibility of any first episode in <jargon type="sci-fi"/> to cover <em>some</em> world building, and <em><a href="/Dear-Charlotte/series-1/episode-1-the-way-back/">The Way Back</a></em> is no exception. It establishes the oppression which the ordinary people live under and the ruthless methods which the Federation will employ, in order to maintain order.</p>
		<p>We see what happens to people who are banished from civilisation in <em><a href="/Dear-Charlotte/series-1/episode-3-cygnus-alpha/">Cygnus Alpha</a></em>.</p>
		<p>Some episodes deal with the civilisations which have chosen <em>not</em> to be part of the Federation - for example Destiny in <em><a href="/Dear-Charlotte/series-1/episode-7-mission-to-destiny/">Mission to Destiny</a></em>, XK-72 in <em><a href="/Dear-Charlotte/series-1/episode-10-breakdown/">Breakdown</a></em> or Lindor in <em><a href="/Dear-Charlotte/series-1/episode-11-bounty/">Bounty</a></em>.</p>
		<p>Aside from the city in <em><a href="/Dear-Charlotte/series-1/episode-1-the-way-back/">The Way Back</a></em>, we don't see anything of ordinary life under Federation control, just a series of Federation outposts which Blake is intent on blowing up, such as the one on <a href="/Dear-Charlotte/series-1/episode-4-time-squad/">Saurian Major</a> or <a href="/Dear-Charlotte/series-1/episode-6-seek-locate-destroy/">Centero</a>.</p>

		<figure class="img-r">
			<img src="/Dear-Charlotte/img/series-1/mission-to-destiny.jpg" alt=""/>
			<figcaption>Avon does his Sherlock bit in <em><a href="/Dear-Charlotte/series-1/episode-7-mission-to-destiny/">Mission to Destiny</a></em>.</figcaption>
		</figure>

		<h2>Playing with genre</h2>
		<p>More than any other series, the first is the most playful with genre. We have a brief legal drama in <em><a href="/Dear-Charlotte/series-1/episode-1-the-way-back/">The Way Back</a></em>, a prison drama in <em><a href="/Dear-Charlotte/series-1/episode-2-space-fall/">Space Fall</a></em>, a whodunnit in <em><a href="/Dear-Charlotte/series-1/episode-7-mission-to-destiny/">Mission to Destiny</a></em> and a heist in <em><a href="/Dear-Charlotte/series-1/episode-6-seek-locate-destroy/">Seek-Locate-Destroy</a></em>.</p>
		<p>Nation sometimes falls back on an A-B plot structure<note>The <q>A</q> plot taking place somewhere away from <em>The Liberator</em> - usually a planet - and the <q>B</q> plot taking place on board.</note>, so beloved of <em>Star Trek</em> for a few episodes, for example <em><a href="/Dear-Charlotte/series-1/episode-4-time-squad/">Time Squad</a></em>, <em><a href="/Dear-Charlotte/series-1/episode-11-bounty/">Bounty</a></em> and <em><a href="/Dear-Charlotte/series-1/episode-12-deliverance/">Deliverance</a></em> but this split of action usually takes the form that something forces <em>The Liberator</em> to move out of teleport range, in order to increase the peril of those on the ground<note>This is an inherent problem with the teleporter - it's basically a get-out-of-jail-free card (often literally), so writers need to come up with ways for it to be ineffective, in order for there to be any drama at all.</note>.</p>
		
		<h2>Weirdo of the week</h2>
		<p>An episode structure which Nation must have been familiar with from <em>Doctor Who</em> might be described as <q>weirdo of the week</q>: some eccentric loner or alien who's spent so long apart from civilisation that they make things <em>super</em> awkward for Blake and the gang. <a href="/Dear-Charlotte/series-1/episode-3-cygnus-alpha/#vargas">Brian Blessed</a> certainly fits into this role in <em><a href="/Dear-Charlotte/series-1/episode-3-cygnus-alpha/">Cygnus Alpha</a></em>. Also Sayman in <em><a href="/Dear-Charlotte/series-1/episode-5-the-web/">The Web</a></em>, <a href="/Dear-Charlotte/series-1/episode-8-duel/#sinofar">Sinofar</a> and <a href="/Dear-Charlotte/series-1/episode-8-duel/#giroc">Giroc</a> from <em><a href="/Dear-Charlotte/series-1/episode-8-duel/">Duel</a></em>, <a href="/Dear-Charlotte/series-1/episode-11-bounty/#sarkoff">Sarkoff</a> from <em><a href="/Dear-Charlotte/series-1/episode-11-bounty/">Bounty</a></em> and <a href="/Dear-Charlotte/series-1/episode-13-orac/#ensor-senior">Ensor Senior</a> from <em><a href="/Dear-Charlotte/series-1/episode-13-orac/">Orac</a></em>.</p>
		<p>These types of episodes also tend to be ones where a <jargon type="TMS"/> might occur at any moment. Space magic is my personal least favourite part of <em>Blake's 7</em>.</p>
		
		<figure class="img-r">
			<img src="/Dear-Charlotte/img/series-1/cally-saurian-major.jpg" alt=""/>
			<figcaption>Cally on Saurian Major during <em><a href="/Dear-Charlotte/series-1/episode-4-time-squad/">Time Squad</a></em>.</figcaption>
		</figure>

		<h2>Character building</h2>
		<p>Some episodes are specifically designed for building or introducing new characters. We first meet Servalan and Travis in <em><a href="/Dear-Charlotte/series-1/episode-6-seek-locate-destroy/">Seek-Locate-Destroy</a></em> (the episode title is the orders which Servalan gives to Travis, regarding Blake). Cally is found during <em><a href="/Dear-Charlotte/series-1/episode-4-time-squad/">Time Squad</a></em> and is a sort of space terrorist from the planet Auron. Others from her planet are discovered in the next episode, <em><a href="/Dear-Charlotte/series-1/episode-5-the-web/">The Web</a></em>, but any chance for character development or back story is lost when Blake leaves her on the ship.</p>
		<p><em><a href="/Dear-Charlotte/series-1/episode-10-breakdown/">Breakdown</a></em> is <em>supposed</em> to be about Gan, but gurning during its opening scene is hardly the tour de force of thespianism. Most of Gan's back story seems to relate to his <q>limiter</q> - a chip in his brain which means he can't kill people, only wrestle with them.</p>
		<p>We get some Blake / Travis back story during <em><a href="/Dear-Charlotte/series-1/episode-6-seek-locate-destroy/">Seek-Locate-Destroy</a></em> and a tiny bit more Travis lore in <em><a href="/Dear-Charlotte/series-1/episode-12-deliverance/">Deliverance</a></em>. During <em><a href="/Dear-Charlotte/series-1/episode-11-bounty/">Bounty</a></em>, we discover that Jenna used to hang out with space pirates.</p>
	</content>
</page>