<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="/Dear-Charlotte/xslt/page.xslt"?>
<page>
	<meta>
		<description>An introduction to Doctor Who, part 4: RADA acting</description>
		<path>/Dear-Charlotte/charlotte-responds/rada-acting/</path>
	</meta>
	<content type="main">
		<h1><jargon type="RADA"/> acting</h1>

		<p>Pretty much all Doctor Who actors up until the 80s were theatrically trained. Liz Sladen’s autobiography charts her history as a jobbing actor, describing points where she was so poor she had to write a section in her script a point where she could eat a banana so she didn’t faint<note>There’s a sweet reference to this in <em>Hand of Fear</em>.</note>. Combined with the quality of sets and props, plus the 70s effects and pacing, it can feel like watching amateur dramatics. 95% of Doctor Who actors seem to take the thing incredibly seriously, at least until Douglas Adams took over and the humour turned up to 11. But in the dark, gothic Hinchcliffe years, it was serious business. There are some shocking performances (Vira in <em>Ark in Space</em>), but also some real treasures. Tony Beckley as the evil millionaire who loves plants more than people and tries to turn the Doctor into compost. Philip Madoc as Frankenstein, sorry, Solon. Freddy Jaeger in <em>Planet of Evil</em> (one of two stories in this era where the Doctor advocates suicide). Plus my favourite ever Doctor Who actor, <a href="http://tardismusings.blogspot.co.uk/2012/10/michael-sheard.html">Mr Bronson from Grange Hill</a>. There’s pathos, irony, humour and lots of abstract gazing and gurning. There’s a ten second clip in Shada where Tom Baker performs every expression in ‘my first guide to TV performance’.</p>
		<p>Oh and if Blake’s 7 had Brian Blessed, Doctor Who had STEPHEN THORNE!!!!!</p>

		<figure>
			<img src="/Dear-Charlotte/img/charlotte-responds/stephen-thorne-roles.jpg" alt=""/>
			<figcaption>The many faces of Stephen Thorne. From left to right, Eldrad, Azal and Omega.</figcaption>
		</figure>

	</content>
</page>