<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="/Dear-Charlotte/xslt/page.xslt"?>
<page>
	<meta>
		<description>Episode 5: The Web. Cally sabotages The Liberator so it goes to a planet wrapped in an inescapable web. She's been mind controlled by Saymon, one of 'the lost', a group of Cally's people exiled from their planet. They need new power cells, but when Blake realises they intend to use them to eliminate a race of sentient life-forms called the Decimas, he refuses to hand over the cells. The Decimas attack and The Liberator escapes.</description>
		<path>/Dear-Charlotte/series-1/episode-5-the-web/</path>
		<type>episode</type>
	</meta>
	<content type="main">
		<h1>Episode 5: The Web</h1>
		<p>In the last episode, Blake picked up <a href="/Dear-Charlotte/about-blakes-7/cally/">Cally</a> from Saurian Major, where she was a freelance terrorist<note>Once Blake blew up the only Federation building on the planet, she'd run out of things to terrorise</note>. There was also a bunch of stuff with men in leather bikinis, but that's not important right now. Cally suffers from telepathy. That's the salient fact.</p>
		
		<figure class="img-r">
			<img src="/Dear-Charlotte/img/series-1/episode-5-the-web/saymon.jpg" alt=""/>
			<figcaption>I have no words</figcaption>
		</figure>
		
		<h2>Tripping balls</h2>
		<p>This episode is rife with a 1970s <jargon type="sci-fi"/> staple - the trippy montage sequence (<jargon type="TMS"/>), made up of slow dissolves. I blame 2001, a wonderful film, but one which influenced a generation of film makers to imitate its surface style only. Let's reduce the opening scene to bullets, to save time:</p>
		<ul>
			<li>A cobweb and ball-littered landscape tracking shot leads to a temporary structure of some kind</li>
			<li>Interior of structure: some kind of laboratory</li>
			<li>A couple of silver-suited berks, lounging on garden furniture</li>
			<li>That twat on the right there<note>I'd pixelate the groin region, but it looks like the video compression has done most of my work for me.</note>. <a href="https://youtu.be/Oi60CCM9jZU?t=14s" title="Reeves and Mortimer's impression of Otis Redding and Marvin Gaye">Does that look remind you of anything</a>?</li>
		</ul>
		<p>Over the top of this, the phrase <q>they must come to us</q> is repeated through a flanger. Or perhaps a phaser. Not sure. One of those guitar effects pedals which <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/BBC_Radiophonic_Workshop">The BBC Radiophonic Workshop</a> probably invented one afternoon in 1964.</p>
		
		<h2>Night terrors</h2>
		<p><em>The Liberator</em>'s speed is increasing without Jenna doing owt to the space-throttle. Then we see Cally skulking about and  doing something well dodge in what looks like the space-basement (spacement?) in the middle of the night<note>Always difficult to tell in space</note>. Jenna hails Blake, we learn the disturbing fact that Blake likes to sleep topless under a bomber jacket, unpopped to the navel. Good lord, man, think of the <em>children</em>.</p>

		<figure>
			<img src="/Dear-Charlotte/img/series-1/episode-5-the-web/nightwear.jpg" alt=""/>
			<figcaption>Pictured: appropriate night-wear</figcaption>
		</figure>

		<p>Vila meets Cally in a corridor and asks her what she thinks of his new outfit. She bashes him on the bonce. Then she asks Avon about the forward projectors and is generally a bit weird. He's suspicious, but has been summoned by Blake, and goes to meet him, furrowed brow at the ready.</p>
		
		<ross>
			<p>The scene between Cally and Avon is nice, but you wouldn't know it from the script:</p>
		</ross>

		<blockquote class="screenplay">
			<header>
				<p><b>B</b><b>B</b><b>C</b> <b>tv</b></p>
				<h2>Blake's 7</h2>
				<h3>&quot;The Web&quot;</h3>
			</header>

			<p>Cut to:</p>
			<p><abbr title="Interior">Int</abbr>. teleporter room</p>
			<dl>
				<dt>Avon</dt>
				<dd><ins>(to Blake)</ins> Alright</dd>
				<dt>Blake</dt>
				<dd><ins>(from the communicator)</ins> If it was alright, I wouldn't need you here.</dd>
			</dl>
			<p class="desc">Cally enters in the background. Avon starts, when he realises she's there.</p>
			<dl>
				<dt>Avon</dt>
				<dd><ins>(to Cally)</ins> Our leader seems a bit peaked.</dd>
			</dl>
			<p class="desc">He examines the tool he's holding, perhaps embarrassed at his jump.</p>
			<dl>
				<dt>Cally</dt>
				<dd>What are you doing?</dd>
				<dt>Avon</dt>
				<dd>A little private research.</dd>
			</dl>
			<p class="desc">She approaches.</p>
			<dl>
				<dt>Cally</dt>
				<dd>Why?</dd>
			</dl>
			<footer class="clearfix">
				<p>Commercial and in confidence</p>
				<p>Page 5 of 50</p>
			</footer>
		</blockquote>

		<blockquote class="screenplay">
			<header>
				<p><b>B</b><b>B</b><b>C</b> <b>tv</b></p>
				<h2>Blake's 7</h2>
				<h3>&quot;The Web&quot;</h3>
			</header>
			<dl>
				<dt>Avon</dt>
				<dd>All knowledge is valuable.</dd>
				<dt>Cally</dt>
				<dd><ins>(putting her hand to her temple)</ins> Which are the forward detector links?</dd>
				<dt>Avon</dt>
				<dd><ins>(confused)</ins> What?
				<ins>(pause)</ins> Oh. Em...
				<ins>(indicating on unit in front of him)</ins> Those two there. Why do you want to know that?</dd>
				<dt>Cally</dt>
				<dd><ins>(brightly)</ins> I'm interested in your work.</dd>
			</dl>
			<p class="desc">There is a pause. Avon regards Cally.</p>
			<dl>
				<dt>Avon</dt>
				<dd>Yes. Well, I suppose I better go and see what it is that Blake wants.</dd>
			</dl>
			<p class="desc">He leaves. Cally reaches for one of his tools.</p>

			<footer class="clearfix">
				<p>Commercial and in confidence</p>
				<p>Page 6 of 50</p>
			</footer>
		</blockquote>
		
		<ross>
			<p>That gap - the one indicated by <q>There is a pause. Avon regards Cally</q> - is lovely. Paul Darrow (Avon) expresses his character's mild confusion and suspicion but also it seems like he's looking for a sexual subtext, not necessarily out of interest in Cally, but because such information - or knowledge, as he might put it - might be valuable. It feels like the first piece of acting in the series which treats the audience like adults.</p>
			<p>Science fiction is a genre where exposition is almost a defining feature. It's a fiction of world building first and characters second. Authors rarely attempt character exposition, thank goodness. Character should not be explained in the same way as a piece of technology is. A good actor can use the space between the lines - as Darrow does in this scene - to add something which isn't necessarily in the original script.</p>
		</ross>
		
		<p>Avon and Blake confront Cally, who pulls a blaster on them. While they distract her, Gan creeps up and disarms her. Jenna realises she's under some kind of telepathic control.</p>
		<p>We see that fish tank freak again. He's the puppet master, which is ironic. I think he's genuinely made out of pipe cleaners. Cally is cured of telepathic possession via a hearty slap from Jenna. The 1970s were big on <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=i0GW0Vnr9Yc" title="That scene from Airplane, where the panicking woman gets slapped a lot">slap-based medical treatments</a>. It was a simpler time.</p>
		<p>Cally's suspicious device turns out to be a bomb. Blake tries to disarm it, and sets it off. Avon saves him, much to his surprise.</p>
		
		<ross>
			<h2>Best of frenemys</h2>
			<p>This episode suggests twice that there's some affection between Blake and Avon, despite Avon vehemently denying it. Immediately after being saved by Avon, Blake asks him why he did it. Avon claims it was an <q>automatic reaction: I'm as surprised as you are</q>. And later on, when Avon is in a threatening position, Blake describes him as <q>my friend</q>. You'd imagine this would produce a thriving slash community eagerly documenting their imaginary encounters, but I can't confirm this: I'm far too frightened to search for it. <em>This is an exercise left up to the reader</em>.</p>
		</ross>

		<p>Then this happens:</p>
		
		<blockquote class="imgur-embed-pub" lang="en" data-id="LPksXxk"><a href="/Dear-Charlotte//imgur.com/LPksXxk">Saymon gets his two thralls, Novara and Geela, to make his laboratory fit for visitors.</a></blockquote><script async="" src="//s.imgur.com/min/embed.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
		
		<p>Say what you will about montage sequences and slow dissolves: they sure can fill out a running time.</p>
		<p>Because of all of Cally's mischief, the crew has no idea where they are, but are close to a planet. Also, they're trapped in some kind of web.</p>
		<p>Cally's better again, apparently. But then Jenna gets taken over, and speaks in a freaky voice<note>There's not any suggestion that Jenna is telepathic too. Perhaps this sort of mind control requires a womb?</note>. It tells them that they're trapped. The voice offers to help free them, but in exchange for some unspecified help which requires them to go down to the planet.</p>
		
		<h2>Hatches solve all plot holes</h2>
		<p>Cally suggests that the being which took over Jenna could be one of <q>the lost</q>, a group of people from her planet who were cast out. She doesn't elaborate on <em>why</em> they were cast out, but then Cally also seems to be, so perhaps they're cool?</p>
		<p>Blake has a go at escaping the web and we finally get to see <em>The Liberator</em> fire the neutron blasters. But the web closes up again, so they are doomed to follow the A-plot after all.</p>
		<p>On the planet, there's a bunch of aliens cavorting about near the temporary structure. They look a bit like the <a href="http://tardis.wikia.com/wiki/Zygon">Zygons</a>, but without the creepy suckers and perhaps 70% more lettucy. Lettuce-like. Whatever. They try and break into the structure with rocks and hammers. The tiny fish tank man looks like he's shitting himself<note>WAIT - I'VE SEEN FISH POOP. WHAT IF THAT ISN'T AN UMBILICAL CORD OR HIS PENIS?</note>.</p>
		
		<char>
			<figure class="img-r">
				<img src="/Dear-Charlotte/img/charlotte-responds/creature-from-the-pit.jpg" alt=""/>
				<figcaption>A reminder: Doctor Who was a <em>children's</em> show.</figcaption>
			</figure>

			<p>As Terence Dicks once said: the colour for aliens is green. From Krynoids to Zygons, Swampies to Rutans, if it’s not a robot it looks like something from the organic section of Morrison’s veg counter. Again, all the actors are required to maintain a straight face whilst greeting these creatures. <em>Horror of Fang Rock</em> is frankly ruined by the Doctor having to sit and have a chat to a green foamy sponge creature on the stairs. In <em>Creature from the Pit</em> he has to communicate via Erato's, err, let’s call that slightly dodgy appendage a claw shall we?</p>
			<p>Mainly the moral message is: sometimes things that look a bit odd might be nice.</p>
			<p>Other times of course they try to take over your planet.</p>
		</char>

		<p>Blake teleports down on his own. Cally's miffed, because she wanted to go too. Tough luck, Cally: you should have thought of that before you left your doors of perception unlatched.</p>
		<p>One of the lettuce men lobs a spear at Blake, and catches the back of his hand. Blake pegs it for the structure. One of the lettuce men follows him and asks for help in a high-pitched voice which clearly means he's supposed to be the good guy. He says <q>Help us. Help us please</q>, and then this happens:</p>
		
		<blockquote class="imgur-embed-pub" lang="en" data-id="qUVh8bJ"><a href="/Dear-Charlotte//imgur.com/qUVh8bJ">A Decima gets the lightning rod for not looking sufficiently like David Bowie.</a></blockquote><script async="" src="//s.imgur.com/min/embed.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
		
		<p>That look Blake gives the Thin White Duke while he's killing the iceberg lettuce child gets me every time.</p>
		<p>The two silver people introduce themselves to Blake:</p>

		<biog>
			<src>/img/characters/novara.png</src>
			<info type="Name">Novara</info>
			<info type="Job">Lab assistant / Thin white duke</info>
			<info type="Dramatic role">Counterpoint to primitive lettuce people</info>
			<info type="Dislikes">Conjunctions</info>
			<info type="Holiday essential"><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=T24DdUPt5d0" title="Studio Line advert from the 1980s">Studio Line</a></info>
		</biog>

		<biog>
			<src>/img/characters/geela.png</src>
			<info type="Name">Geela</info>
			<info type="Job">Lab assistant / Aquarist</info>
			<info type="Dramatic role">Demonstrating creepy liver-based medicine</info>
			<info type="Dislikes">People making assumptions about her sexuality</info>
			<info type="Eyebrow game">Strong</info>
		</biog>

		<p>Geela applies a dressing Blake's hand. It looks exactly like liver, and pulses and squeaks while it's fixing him up. He seems perfectly fine with this. Moments later, it's a dry husk, and his hand is healed. We learn that the lettuce people are called Decimas.</p>
		
		<h2>The cement garden</h2>
		<p>Novara and Geela claim to be brother and sister. They're doing some sort of medical research. One of their earlier experiments was the web which has trapped <em>The Liberator</em>, which is a self-replicating fungus which <q>got out of control</q>. They also invented a fungicide which can remove it. They'll use the fungicide to remove the web around <em>The Liberator</em> if Blake gets them two new power cells.</p>
		<p>Suddenly the Decimas attack again but it's a diversion, so they can collect their fallen colleague:</p>
		
		<blockquote class="imgur-embed-pub" lang="en" data-id="IKpnKsL"><a href="/Dear-Charlotte//imgur.com/IKpnKsL">Those poor, sad lettuce people.</a></blockquote><script async="" src="//s.imgur.com/min/embed.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
		
		<p>You'd have to have a heart of stone, not to laugh like a drain at that scene. <em>Look at the lettucy sadness in his eyes</em>. I think I might have watched too much <em>Mighty Boosh</em>.</p>
		
		<p>Blake calls <em>The Liberator</em>, and asks Avon to bring him two flutonic power cells.</p>
		<p><em>The Liberator</em>'s repair systems have finally fixed all of Cally's nocturnal mischief so Jenna runs a scan and spots a small fleet of Federation pursuit craft at <q>extreme range</q> which are closing in. The ships can't see <em>The Liberator</em> yet, though.</p>
		
		<h2>Wipe the slate clean</h2>
		<p>Novara and Geela explain that the original aims of the project were immortality for the creators. There was also a sort of side project to create a butler race, presumably to wipe the immortal creature's bottoms, because they'd be too busy to get involved in mundane tasks like that. The Decimas were intended to be the butlers, but a mutant gene spread through their race and they're now considered too aggressive. Novara and Geela want to wipe them out (no pun intended).</p>
		<p>Blake argues for the Decimas right to life. Then - <em>plot twist!</em> - it turns out that Novara and Geela were <em>also</em> genetically constructed and are meat puppets for the tiny freaky man in the tank, who is called Sayman<note>And I thought he was their <a href="https://theawl.com/the-shocking-true-tale-of-the-mad-genius-who-invented-sea-monkeys-9105de87d446">Sea Monkey</a>.</note>. Saymon is a <q>corporate identity</q>, which means that all six original team members exist within his disgusting, pipe-cleaner body. He needs the power cells partially to continue his life support systems, and partially to generate lethal levels of radiation, in order to kill the Decimas.</p>

		<h2>Power play</h2>
		<p>By this time, Avon's beamed down with the power cells and is in danger from the Decimas. Blake, Novara and Geela rush out to meet him<note>This is the point where Blake says to Saymon of Avon: <q>I don't give a damn about your power cells: there's a <em>friend</em> of mine out there!</q></note>.</p>
		<p>Blake, Novara and Geela split up, to search for Avon. Blake finds him, and explains the moral dilemma to Avon, with predictable consequences. Blake stashes the power cells, so he can negotiate. Novara and Geela arrive and ask for the power cells. Blake rolls over almost immediately <note>Avon gets a shock on his hand from Geela at <q>minimum power</q></note>.</p>
		<p>They return to the base, without locking the door, for some reason, and the Decimas attack. The battle looks and sounds preposterous. They start wrecking the place and Blake turns on the fungicide beam and turns off the radiation. The web starts dissolving. Novara and Geela get stomped to death by the Decimas, and just their skulls and floppy uniforms are left. It's like they were deflated, or something.</p>
		
		<h2>Tanks for the memory</h2>
		<p>Blake and Avon beam up, and the Decimas reach Saymon's tank. It doesn't look good for him.</p>
		
		<ross>
			<h2>Anthropocentrism</h2>
			<p><em>The Web</em> isn't a <em>great</em> episode of <em>Blake's 7</em>, to be honest. If you manage to ignore the surface, there's a tiny idea there which needed to be said - <em>Star Trek</em> in particular is especially bad at anthropocentric narratives, which assume that the more humanoid a race is, the morally better they are. This doesn't necessarily come from a dark place - the reasons are more likely to be ones of narrative convention and ease of storytelling. While even <jargon type="sci-fi"/> on <jargon type="TV"/> has covered some quite difficult subjects in the past, it's also primarily made as escapism. Viewers don't expect their deep prejudices to be challenged by it.</p>
			<p>Unfortunately, the message of <q>sometimes the little ugly guys are good, and the tall pretty ones are bad</q> is hopelessly undermined by the presence of Saymon, who is disgusting and hilarious in equal measure. The morally questionable nature of Novara and Geela is telegraphed clearly, by their robotic speech and Aryan appearance<note>Or even worse, the <a href="http://tvtropes.org/pmwiki/pmwiki.php/Main/EvilAlbino">evil albino</a> trope</note>.</p>
			<p>The only point where the episode comes close to puncturing our smug sense of self-satisfaction is the exchange between Avon and Blake toward the end:</p>
		</ross>

		<blockquote class="screenplay">
			<header>
				<p><b>B</b><b>B</b><b>C</b> <b>tv</b></p>
				<h2>Blake's 7</h2>
				<h3>&quot;The Web&quot;</h3>
			</header>

			<p>Cut to:</p>
			<p><abbr title="Exterior">Ext</abbr>. woodland</p>
			<p class="desc">Blake is searching for Avon. The camera movement implies that someone is creeping up behind him. Cut to Avon, walking completely normally, seemingly without a care in the world. Blake jumps slightly.</p>
			<dl>
				<dt>Avon</dt>
				<dd>I've been looking for you. What's been going on?</dd>
				<dt>Blake</dt>
				<dd>Let's get under cover first.</dd>
			</dl>
			<p class="desc">They walk a few feet, then crouch down among some ferns.</p>
			<dl>
				<dt>Blake</dt>
				<dd><ins>(quietly)</ins> Have you got the cells?</dd>
				<dt>Avon</dt>
				<dd><ins>(indicating the box he's carrying)</ins> What do you think these are, field rations?</dd>
				<dt>Blake</dt>
				<dd>Listen: there's a problem. If we let them have those, they'll use them to wipe out an entire race of creatures - <em>people</em> - here.</dd>
				<dt>Avon</dt>
				<dd>If it concerns you, don't give them the cells.</dd>
				<dt>Blake</dt>
				<dd>No, there's more: they've got a carrier beam which projects a fungicide which will clear the way through the web for us. And doesn't work, without this power.</dd>
				<dt>Avon</dt>
				<dd>Ah well. If it's between the creatures and us, there's no argument. Even <em>your</em> irrational conscience should be able to cope with that. <ins>(Blake gives him a look)</ins> What do you want to do?</dd>
				<dt>Blake</dt>
				<dd>Hold off long enough to make a deal.</dd>
			</dl>
			<footer class="clearfix">
				<p>Commercial and in confidence</p>
				<p>Page 42 of 50</p>
			</footer>
		</blockquote>
		
		<h2>Watch <em>The Web</em> on YouTube</h2>
		<youtube id="fHfd2QY3okE"/>
	</content>
</page>