<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="/Dear-Charlotte/xslt/page.xslt"?>
<page>
	<meta>
		<description>David Bowie tribute, by Charlotte</description>
		<path>/Dear-Charlotte/charlotte-responds/loving-the-alien/</path>
	</meta>
	<content type="main">
		<h1>Loving the Alien</h1>

		<p><q>I'd rather stay here, with all the madmen</q></p>
		<p>Following Bowie’s death, many spoke of how he gave them permission to be alien. Teenagers, loners, those who struggled to ‘fit in’ had lost a role model. Bowie recorded over 100 albums<note>27 studio albums, 9 live albums, 49 compilation albums, 6 extended plays, 121 singles and 3 soundtracks.</note>.</p>
		<p>His message with his final <em>Dark Star</em> album was as fresh as it was with <em>Space Odyssey</em> nearly 50 years previously. In a world that finds comfort in handy labels for all those it struggles with, a figure who flaunts the rules, who refuses to be boxed, can be a hero.</p>
		<p><!--Many people have written tributes that are far more eloquent and original than mine. -->These are just a few reasons why, for me Bowie was and still is awesome. Also why I think he might say to the Doctor: <q>we are not so different you and I.</q> Probably whilst wearing ten metre wide concrete trousers, paired with a beautifully tailored velour poncho and kitten heels.</p>

		<figure>
			<img src="/Dear-Charlotte/img/charlotte-responds/loving-the-alien/bowie-trousers.jpg" alt=""/>
			<figcaption>Image from Masayoshi Sukita / David Bowie Archive</figcaption>
		</figure>

		<h2>1- Creating and living a legend</h2>
		<p><q>He … became the special man.</q></p>
		<p>I love that the legend that is Bowie is actually made up of so many deliberately created characters. I recall from a documentary that he made sure Angie was filmed at the front of the stage, screaming like a fan girl. Tell the world you are sexy and talented and they will believe you. (He was, obvs.) He was accompanied by bodyguards in the street. Again; tell the world you are valuable, they will believe you. Play the media at their own game. I’m particularly interested in those 70s and 80s characters he designed. Everything played a role; costume, make-up, hair, music style. He lived them on and off stage. That’s dedication.</p>

		<figure class="bakerfact">
			<a href="#clothes-maketh-the-man" class="toggle-link">
				<i class="sticker">Tom Baker fact!</i>
				<img src="/Dear-Charlotte/img/charlotte-responds/loving-the-alien/peeping-top.png" alt=""/>
			</a>
			<figcaption class="js-hidden" id="clothes-maketh-the-man">In Tom Baker’s autobiography he admits he didn’t really know who he was until he played the Doctor. In later years he apparently took to wearing the outfit full-time. But then, with that outfit, you would wouldn’t you?</figcaption>
		</figure>

		<h2>2- Leaving on a high</h2>
		<p><q>Your circuit’s dead, there’s something wrong.</q></p>
		<p>Like his early creation, Major Tom, Bowie was never afraid to surprise his audience by cutting the cord; to destroy one of his creations at the height of popularity. There’s a lovely story about him being on stage as Ziggy announcing to the audience this will be the last performance and his band turning to one another going: <q>What?</q>. Leave them wanting more. Something that quite a lot of TV series could learn from. <small>(<em>Coughs</em> House.)</small></p>

		<figure class="bakerfact">
			<a href="#always-leave-em-wanting-more" class="toggle-link">
				<i class="sticker">Tom Baker fact!</i>
				<img src="/Dear-Charlotte/img/charlotte-responds/loving-the-alien/peeping-top.png" alt=""/>
			</a>
			<figcaption class="js-hidden" id="always-leave-em-wanting-more">Sadly this wasn’t the case with Baker. Arguably the most successful Doctor, he was elbowed out by the 80s and JNT who of course I don’t bear any grudge against at all. Baker chose to leave. Did he fall or was he pushed? Well, he wasn't actually pushed. More sort of 'tipped' off the Pharos Project by the Master. <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=l3w-BHsXt4I" title="The climax of 'Logopolis'">Haven't you seen Logopolis?</a></figcaption>
		</figure>

		<h2>3-Regeneration</h2>
		<p><q>Ch … ch … changes.</q></p>
		<p>I almost didn’t put the above quote as it’s such an obvious one, but Bowie was all about change. No sooner were people used to one personality than it evolved into another: David Jones, David Bowie, Ziggy Stardust, Aladdin Sane, the Thin White Duke. The music changed as well, sometimes shockingly. A couple of times I’ve bought an album listened to it and wondered whether I actually liked it. Some songs feature ear-bleeding guitar work and a voice so raw, often shouting. He pushed me to enjoy what might initially be disturbing. Of course I eventually loved those songs.</p>

		<figure>
			<img src="/Dear-Charlotte/img/charlotte-responds/loving-the-alien/david-bowie-doctor-who.jpg" alt=""/>
			<figcaption>It's tricky to establish the origin of this image - <a href="http://tineye.com/">TinEye</a> suggests that <a href="https://plus.google.com/+JonathanSeyghal">Jonathan Seyghal</a> created it, but there's an almost illegible username in the bottom left hand corner</figcaption>
		</figure>

		<p>Visiting the V&amp;A exhibition I was struck by what a polymath he was. He took inspiration not just from music, but books, films and art. He was nomadic, spending time in America and Berlin. Many artists change in order to keep fresh. I get the impression of a man who was excited by everything and wanted to capture it all; to live every second of life to the full.</p>

		<figure class="bakerfact">
			<a href="#regeneration" class="toggle-link">
				<i class="sticker">Tom Baker fact!</i>
				<img src="/Dear-Charlotte/img/charlotte-responds/loving-the-alien/peeping-top.png" alt=""/>
			</a>
			<figcaption class="js-hidden" id="regeneration">Regeneration is an obvious link with the Doctor. Regeneration was a stroke of genius, allowing the show to continue when William Hartnell no longer could. The longevity of the programme is entirely due to the main role being able to evolve into a completely different character. Elements of the Dr, as with elements of Bowie, are core. The rest is up for grabs.</figcaption>
		</figure>

		<h2>4- Standing alone</h2>
		<p><q>Sometimes you get so lonely. Sometimes you get nowhere.</q></p>
		<p>Growing up in a village I have a soft spot for eccentricity. Country life has its fair share of odd-bods. Perhaps because you are expected to follow a set pattern (job, partner, marriage, house, kids etc.) breaking the norm was breaking free. It was also alienating.</p>

		<figure class="img-r">
			<img src="/Dear-Charlotte/img/charlotte-responds/loving-the-alien/ashes-to-ashes.jpg" alt=""/>
			<figcaption>Still from the <em>Ashes to Ashes</em> music video</figcaption>
		</figure>

		<p>Bowie’s aliens were less rural. He is urban to the core (except when he’s in space). I love the bleakness of some of his themes, videos, lyrics and characters. For the <em>Ashes to Ashes</em> video, I imagine him saying: <q>right, I want to be on a lonely beach. Make the colours all trippy so it’s unsettling. Oh and I’m dressed as a clown. With a snow plough. And a confused old lady</q>. As an actor he has played prisoners-of-war, stranded aliens, the Elephant Man, even Herod. But always in the solitariness, there is some comfort, or reassurance. It’s hard to pinpoint, but then pretty much everything about Bowie is.</p>

		<p>As a kid I borrowed my music taste from my circle of trust: jazz from my parents; <em>The Cure</em> from my brother; Kylie because small girls can be terribly catty in the playground if you don't know the words to <q>I should be so lucky</q>. Bowie's was the first music I listened to and thought: whatever that is, that's mine. Everyone else hated it, which made me love it more. So the equation began: weird + unpopular can = brilliant.</p>
		<p>As an aside: the Doctor Who audio drama <em>The Foe from the Future</em> there is a character called <q>Charlotte from the village</q>. She spends the episode being the fourth Doctor's side kick and loves David Bowie. It's the nearest I've come to appearing in a Doctor Who story.)</p>

		<figure class="bakerfact">
			<a href="#loner" class="toggle-link">
				<i class="sticker">Tom Baker fact!</i>
				<img src="/Dear-Charlotte/img/charlotte-responds/loving-the-alien/peeping-top.png" alt=""/>
			</a>
			<figcaption class="js-hidden" id="loner">Of course the Doctor is a loner. He’s nomadic and has a series of companions who can never live out his life with him because he’s ageless. No sooner has he got the situation sorted, saved the world, than he leaves again. Baker, too, comes across as a loner in his autobiography. He grows up as a Catholic schoolboy, tries being a monk, an army nurse and working on a building site before he finally gets cast as the Doctor. His portrayal apparently excited <jargon type="BBC"/> staff as he was the first to show the Dr for the alien he really is.</figcaption>
		</figure>

		<h2>5- Breaking the rules, taking risks</h2>
		<p><q>People stared at the make-up on his face...</q></p>

		<figure class="img-r">
			<img src="/Dear-Charlotte/img/charlotte-responds/loving-the-alien/the-man-who-sold-the-world.jpg" alt=""/>
			<figcaption>Cover of <em>The Man Who Sold the World</em></figcaption>
		</figure>

		<p>Again, a lot of people have written about this far more eloquently than me. In the V&amp;A exhibition book <em>David Bowie is</em> it talks about <em>Space Oddity</em> coming at the end of the sexual revolution with its <q cite="https://shop.vam.ac.uk/shop/index/view/David-Bowie-Is-Deluxe-Hardback/119209">haunting isolation of asexual purity and passivity</q>. (Nice.) Even after the 60s, a simple act like appearing in a dress on the album cover of <em>The Man Who</em>, or putting his arm around Mick Ronson while on <em>Top of the Pops</em> threw the world into turmoil. Bowie doesn’t even try to hide the stage make-up, but pushes it to the fore. In <em>Life on Mars</em>, the colour is saturated to reduce him to red hair, white face, blue eye shadow.</p>
		<p>Again from the V&amp;A book, it recalls the 1972 <em>Melody Maker</em> when Bowie declared himself gay. This was a big thing as no one had ever publicly outed a British pop musician. Philip Hoare notes all the gay role models before Bowie had been <q cite="https://shop.vam.ac.uk/shop/index/view/David-Bowie-Is-Deluxe-Hardback/119209">patronising</q> Again they <q cite="https://shop.vam.ac.uk/shop/index/view/David-Bowie-Is-Deluxe-Hardback/119209">boxed</q>. Bowie was saying: you can do anything.</p>

		<figure class="img-r">
			<img src="/Dear-Charlotte/img/charlotte-responds/loving-the-alien/labyrinth.jpg" alt=""/>
			<figcaption>David Bowie, from the film <em>Labyrinth</em></figcaption>
		</figure>

		<p>For me, it wasn't just about Bowie’s deliberate confusion of sexuality. (Let’s face it, sexuality is confusing enough for many. Let’s not discuss that outfit in <em>Labyrinth</em>, which really shouldn’t be attractive, but is.) For me it was about challenging established roles. His outfits could be with by men or women - provided you're brave enough! He wasn't repeating the tedious (still continuing) ‘men do this, women are like this.’</p>

		<figure class="bakerfact">
			<a href="#sexuality" class="toggle-link">
				<i class="sticker">Tom Baker fact!</i>
				<img src="/Dear-Charlotte/img/charlotte-responds/loving-the-alien/peeping-top.png" alt=""/>
			</a>
			<figcaption class="js-hidden" id="sexuality">Asexuality in Doctor Who is a difficult one. Up until Paul McGann, <a href="/Dear-Charlotte/charlotte-responds/women-in-the-fourth-doctor-era/" title="Women in the fourth Doctor era">as I’ve discussed elsewhere</a>, there was no Doctor-snog. The Doctor was a man, but an alien. He was hundreds of years old and travelled through space and time, largely on his own. I liked the asexuality of the character. It made him far more interesting. The story was about the concepts and the characters, not the all too human relations that push their way into other sci-fi/adventure stories. Thus for me, New Who is tricky. Ok, it has got a lot more girls watching it. But then I have to push them out of the way to get David Tennant’s autograph and I feel bad elbowing 9 year olds.</figcaption>
		</figure>

		<h2>6- Defeating your enemies with humour</h2>
		<p><q>Pablo Picasso never got called an asshole.</q></p>
		<p>I love the fact that everything Bowie did was with a wink to camera. Theatre at its best. I have a strong memory of seeing footage of him about to go onstage, with the crazy make-up and world’s widest trousers. He turns to the camera and says something like <q>eh, up</q>. Who can’t love a man like that? At times he was definitely going: yup, this is silly, but you’re going to love it. What better way to beat your critics?</p>

		<figure class="bakerfact">
			<a href="#use-of-humour" class="toggle-link">
				<i class="sticker">Tom Baker fact!</i>
				<img src="/Dear-Charlotte/img/charlotte-responds/loving-the-alien/peeping-top.png" alt=""/>
			</a>
			<figcaption class="js-hidden" id="use-of-humour">Of course this is one of the best things about the Doctor. Violence is a last resort. If you can defeat your enemies with intellect, humour and a pan-galactic neutron de-fuser made from paper clips and string, that’s just so much more satisfying than shooting them in the face.</figcaption>
		</figure>

		<h2>7- That Wardrobe</h2>
		<p><q>Put on your red shoes and dance the blues.</q></p>

		<figure class="img-r">
			<img src="/Dear-Charlotte/img/charlotte-responds/loving-the-alien/cobweb.jpg" alt=""/>
			<figcaption>Cobweb costume with fake hands by Natasha Korniloff (1973)</figcaption>
		</figure>

		<p>It’s impossible to talk about Bowie without mentioning this. I just loved the V&amp;A. Who else can pull off a leather Woodland Creatures leotard? Other outfits revealed his beautiful humour, like a suit which wouldn’t seem out of place in the office <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=NKw2oe4fI3o" title="David Bowie wearing said outfit, during a performance of 'Moonage Daydream' and 'Under Pressure' in 1996">except for the man-sized turquoise lady shoes designed to match the tie</a>. My favourite was the ridiculous cobweb outfit. At first there were three conveniently placed ‘hands’. This was considered indecent, so the hand covering the … er, Bowies … was removed. It became quickly apparent it had been covering rather more than it revealed. A half pair of leggings were swiftly added to the ensemble. Think of the children, David.</p>

		<figure class="bakerfact">
			<a href="#costume-changes" class="toggle-link">
				<i class="sticker">Tom Baker fact!</i>
				<img src="/Dear-Charlotte/img/charlotte-responds/loving-the-alien/peeping-top.png" alt=""/>
			</a>
			<figcaption class="js-hidden" id="costume-changes">Not quite the kitten-heels, but I love the Doctor’s wardrobe. Later regenerations ended up with a bit of a ‘uniform’ but the fourth Doctor’s outfit evolved from early red jacket and brogues, to the later dashing adventurer style frock coat with long boots. He even ditched the scarf ensemble in a couple of stories, dressing up as Sherlock Holmes in one story and in a floppy pirate shirt in another. I’m just going to finish here …</figcaption>
		</figure>

		<h2>8- His last bow</h2>
		<p><q>This is all I ever meant, that's the message that I sent.</q></p>
		<p>I can’t give everything away is a farewell song from a man who knew he was dying. It’s difficult to listen to, but very typical of Bowie to have hidden the truth for so long, only to reveal it so heart-breakingly. Still pushing boundaries. Still musically brilliant. Out on a high. The message that he sent, as always: hey kids it's alright to be different. To be disliked. For everyone who doesn’t understand you, there's a person who adores you saying- thank you.</p>
	</content>
</page>
