<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="/xslt/page.xslt"?>
<page>
	<meta>
		<description>Episode 5: Pressure Point</description>
		<path>/series-2/episode-5-pressure-point/</path>
		<type>episode</type>
	</meta>
	<content type="main">
		<h1>Episode 5: Pressure Point</h1>
		<p>Last week<note>I'm aware there's been a bit of a gap between these episode reviews. Sorry.</note>, Blake stumbled upon a secret planet the Federation was hiding from everyone, because it held reserves vital to their control of the galaxy. Blake restored power to the enslaved people then watched some pursuit ships blow themselves up on the force wall, like furious Bluebottles.</p>
		<p>This time, Blake goes after the Federation's server farms, in the hopes of wiping the value off Sainsbury's Nector cards world-wide. Then comes up against all kinds of defences which try and blow him the heck up.</p>

		<ross>
			<p>It's a Terry Nation episode! The first he wrote for series 2, or <q>Series B</q>, as the cool kids say it.</p>
		</ross>

		<p>A couple of olive-drab chaps, Arle and Berg<note>You can tell them apart because they like to appear on screen in alphabetical order</note>, are in the long grass of the <q>forbidden zone</q><note>The grubby signs in the first shot identifies it as the "security zone" but whatever</note>. One is slightly more nervous than the other. They report in to someone called <q>Kasabi</q>, then move into the zone, watched by a standard issue Federation camera.</p>
		<p>Servalan and Travis have set up a snazzy white base, inside a nearby thatched cottage, because they enjoy contrasting styles in architecture. Travis has lain in wait for these men for eighteen days (a popular tactic of his) but Servalan is sceptical that they are Kasabi's men. Travis is certain that somehow Blake will turf up too.</p>

		<ross>
			<p>As far as I can work out, we never find out how Travis knows that Blake is here. Unless Travis has finally worked out how Blake's mind works.</p>
		</ross>

		<p>Arle and Berg come across the enterance to a bunker. Berg is keen to leave but Arle think the place looks undefended.</p>

		<ross>
			<p>The exteriors of the bunker were shot in <jargon type="RAF"/> Abingdon - now known as <jargon type="RAF"/> Harwell. These days, <jargon type="RAF"/> Harwell is <a href="https://goo.gl/maps/LoY2TrwLzDD2" title="RAF Harwell and the European Space Agency on Google maps">right next to the European Space Agency</a> and <a href="http://www.diamond.ac.uk/">Diamond Light Source</a>, a science facility which looks a lot like Servalan's space station, which is a delightful coincidence.</p>
		</ross>

		<p>The bunker houses <q>control</q>, some kind of computer. Arle and Berg<note>There's something of <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=0NQphQZXhFM" title="Amish Sex Pistols">Kevin Eldon</a> about Berg.</note> approach the bunker but something freezes them in place and then they EXPLODE!</p>

		<blockquote class="imgur-embed-pub" lang="en" data-id="a/73nYy"><a href="//imgur.com/73nYy"></a></blockquote><script async="" src="//s.imgur.com/min/embed.js" charset="utf-8"></script>

		<ross>
			<p>The way in which the bunker's defences are unknown and unconventional (there's nothing as crass as a fence, for example) reminds me of Tarkovsky's <em>Stalker</em>, a beautiful and glacially slow film.</p>
		</ross>

		<p>Onboard <em>The Liberator</em>, there's been another costume change. The cast are all done up like this:</p>

		<figure>
			<img src="/img/cast-photo.jpg" alt=""/>
			<figcaption>I especially like Vila's outfit, which subtly suggests he's the jester.</figcaption>
		</figure>

		<p>Blake's pulled one of his hilarious pranks on the crew - he told them they were going to just skirt past the solar system to do some long-range reconnecaunse, when in fact, he intends to return to Earth. Everyone's a bit freaked out by this, apart from Cally, who's always up for a bit of a scrap.</p>
		<p>Blake plans to hit <q>Control</q>, a computer complex which has all of the accumulated data the Federation has been monitoring about its citizens for the past two hundered years.</p>

		<ross>
			<p>Timeline of the shift from <q>big iron</q> to micro-computers?</p>
		</ross>

		<p>The location of Control is well known - Blake regards it as a <q>challenge</q>. Blake has been collating information on Control with Orac. He finishes his speech and Avon slow-claps him:</p>

		<blockquote class="imgur-embed-pub" lang="en" data-id="a/o5o29"><a href="//imgur.com/o5o29">https://www.dear-charlotte.com/series-2/episode-5-pressure-point/</a></blockquote><script async="" src="//s.imgur.com/min/embed.js" charset="utf-8"></script>

		<p>Blake won't ask any of his crew to accompany him, because the operation is too dangerous. Instead, he's contacted Kasabi, a resistance leader on Earth and supervisor to the two mannequins we watched getting exploded at the start of the episode.</p>

		<figure class="img-r">
			<img src="/img/series-2/episode-5-pressure-point/cctv-owl.jpg" alt=""/>
			<figcaption>Like a robotic, cyclops owl: The Federation <jargon type="CCTV"/> camera</figcaption>
		</figure>
		<p>Meanwhile, on Earth, <a href="http://www.imdb.com/name/nm2228384/">Veron</a> (a resistance fighter) asks <a href="http://www.imdb.com/name/nm1519700/">Kasabi</a> (her mother) about Arle and Berg. Kasabi is not optimistic. Kasabi and her troop of olive drab revolutionaries have arranged to meet Blake at the outskirts of the forbidden zone. They move off. A Federation <jargon type="CCTV"/> camera watchens them from a nearby tree, like a cheeky owl.</p>
		<p>Servalan spots Kasabi on the video feed, from within her thatched base. She's pleased. We get some Kasabi background.</p>

		<biog>
			<src>/img/characters/kasabi.png</src>
			<info type="Name">Kasabi</info>
			<info type="Job">Freelance terrorist</info>
			<info type="Previous job">Senior Political Officer in Space Command</info>
			<info type="Narrative role">Servalan backstory dispencer / Earth's last hope</info>
		</biog>

		<ross>
			<p>It's confusing that Servalan uses the title <q>Senior Political Officer</q>, to describe Kasabi's old job. It suggests that I might have been wrong, in my take on <a href="/series-2/episode-4-horizon/#trundles-comment-7">what Kommissar means</a> or Servalan likes to much about with job titles.</p>
		</ross>

		<p>It turns out that Kasabi was tutoring officer cadets in a manner which was somehow treasonious. Servalan was amongst those cadets, and informed on Kasabi. Kasabi managed to escape, before she could feel the might of Federation justice. Servalan's not going to let her escape again, which means Travis should be kept as far away from this plan as possible<note>Travis couldn't organise a pissup in a brewary, without somehow allowing Blake to escape</note>.</p>
		<p>Back on <em>The Liberator</em>, Blake is preparing to teleport down to the outskirts of The Forbidden Zone alone. The rest of the crew (apart from Avon) have had a little meeting and are prepared to come with him, on the condition that <del>no-one will die</del> if the mission looks impossible, they'll pull out. Blake agrees <del>that no-one will die</del>.</p>
		<p>Blake sidels onto the banquette with Avon, to try and persuade him to come. Avon's already decided to come, but naturally, it's all part of his larger plan to get his hands on <em>The Liberator</em>. His prediction is that if he can successfully destroy Control, Blake will have to run the resulting revolution from Earth, leaving Avon to swan about in <em>The Liberator</em>. Zen announces that they've arrived at Earth.</p>
		<p>Outside the Forbidden Zone, Servalan is somehow overlooked by Kasabi and her troops, despite Servalan wearing the signature look of <a href="https://www.google.com/search?tbm=isch&amp;q=mel+%26+kim">Mel &amp; Kim</a>, but in white, and standing on a hillside. Servalan has to call her tutor by name, before she looks up. Kasabi orders her troop to run, so Servalan orders her <a href="http://www.imdb.com/name/nm0084200/">Mutoids</a> (<a href="www.imdb.com/name/nm1311362/">all two</a> <a href="http://www.imdb.com/name/nm1528322/">of them</a>) to fire upon the heavily armed group of resistance fighters. All of the fighters, apart from Kasabi and Veron are killed. They are taken prisoner<note>Dunno about you, but at this point, my confidence in Kasabi is sliding somewhat</note>.</p>
		<p>Kasabi is being interrugated in the techno cottage. Servalan wants her to give up the rendevous with Blake, in order to spare her life.</p>
		<p>Kasabi tells Travis that her original report on Servalan listed her as unsuitable for command, but Servalan's connections allowed her to move up through the ranks.</p>
		<p>Amazingly, Kasabi isn't even tied to the chair. She makes a break for the door, but two sturdy Mutoids stop her.</p>
		<p>Blake and crew are waiting for Kasabi's signal in the teleport lounge. It's an hour late. Blake agrees to wait another hour, then move away.</p>
		<p>Travis interrigates Kasabi, but gets nowhere. They've pumped her full of truth drugs already so Servalan tells him to double the dose. Kasabi loses conciousness so Servalan goes through Kasabi's posessions. There's a homing beacon, but Travis explains that if they trigger it the wrong way, or in the wrong location, they could scare Blake off. Travis asks Kasabi again about the beacon, now the drugs have had a chance to swim about in her system. She gives up the code and beacon location.</p>
		<p>Servalan gives Kasabi another dose, in order to gloat at Kasabi, but then something unexpected happens: Kasabi apologies to Servalan for failing to help her.</p>

		<ross>
			<p>This is a lovely idea, suggesting that truth is like an onion. As Servalan dosed Kasabi with the drug, she penetraited a lay of the skin. The first is her resistanct to the questions. The second is the arrangement of the rendevouz with Blake. But the third is her personal regret of failing to steer Servalan towards more positive life choices. I'd like to think there's a further layer, exposing Kasabi's own vanity over her social standing.</p>
			<p>Jane Sherwin, as Kasabi, gives a lovely performance here. There's nothing camp or overstated about it.</p>
		</ross>

		<p>The message from the homing beacon reaches Blake and he teleports a mile away, to give him time to approach it safely. Clearly some sort of plan has happened off-screen, as everyone knows what they have to do. Blake arrives, checks it's safe and once he's confirmed it, Gan teleports down on his position.</p>
		<p>Blake and Gan wander through the shell of a church. Blake explains that the Federation had all churches destroyed at the start of the <q>new calander</q><note>This kind of exposition is probably best done with a character who has little or no knowledge of earth - Cally, for instance.</note>. The rendevouz is in the basement of the church. They meet Veron, who immediately collapses at the sight of them, repeating <q>no ... no</q>. I think it's Blake's hair which has set her off.</p>

		<biog>
			<src>/img/characters/veron.png</src>
			<info type="Name">Veron</info>
			<info type="Job">Trainee terrorist</info>
			<info type="Hobbies">Horse riding, tennis, dingy racing</info>
			<info type="Narrative role">Quadruple agent</info>
		</biog>

		<p>Gan treats her with the medical ink blotter he used on Jenna, during <a href="/series-1/episode-4-time-squad/"><em>Time Squad</em></a>. Despite Kasabi being absent from the rendevouz point and the only member of her squad being unconcious, Blake stil calls <em>The Liberator</em> and tells them <q>everything is all right</q>. <note>Perhaps his time in space has radically redefined this phrase</note></p>
		<p>Avon picks up on this, his cynicism super-sense twitching visibly.</p>
		<p>Veron regains conciousness. Gan reassures her and offers her some drugs. She refuses them. <q>Please</q> he implores. She acquiesces, as he's so polite about it<note>This is terrible lifestyle advice, people</note>. She tells them about the ambush and the death of Kasabi, but claims to have hidden from the Federation, then given the signal herself.</p>
		<p>Blake wants to go ahead with his plan anyway, reasoning that Kasabi and her team were probably not going to be much use anyway. Gan is sceptical. Blake goes ahead with the plan: Vila and Avon are to teleport into the forbidden zone, carry out a survey of it's defences, then teleport to Blake's position. This is to take no more than five minues.</p>
		<p>Vila and Avon teleport down, and are immediately spotted by another one of the Federation's robot owls. They are in the same location where Arle and Berg bought it at the start of the episode. Turns out that Arle and Berg trod on a <q>high intensity radiation grid</q>. Avon tries snipping it, but it repairs itself in eight seconds<note>Avon is being generous. According to YouTube, it's six seconds.</note>. He checkes the distance to the bunker, wondering if he can peg it there, before getting fried.</p>
		<p>Cally and Jenna teleport Avon and Vila away just before the high intensity radiation grid blows up.</p>

		<blockquote class="imgur-embed-pub" lang="en" data-id="a/NhSo4"><a href="//imgur.com/NhSo4"></a></blockquote><script async="" src="//s.imgur.com/min/embed.js" charset="utf-8"></script>

		<p>They rematerialise in the crypt of the church<note>This is the first point-to-point teleport in the show</note>. Veron is a bit startled so Gan explains who these weirdos are to her. Blake asks them for a report on the defences. Vila doesn't believe it can be done. Avon thinks it can. Gan tells them that Veron is the only surviver from Kasabi's gang. Avon realises Blake was withholding the true danger of the mission from them.</p>
		<p>Vila produces a map he seems to have scrawlled on a disk of acitate and they begin to plan the assault. While they're doing that, Veron creeps up behind them with a gun, in a not-at-all-suspicious way. She asks to go outside and Gan tells her to be careful. Blake's plan is to get over the nest of high intensity radiation grid by teleporting right up to the front door, then get Vila to work his magic.</p>
		<p>Then some cheeky bugger dressed in olive green lobs a grenade down the stairs. Blake shouts a warning, and they all lie on the floor for a bit. The same person then gathers up their teleport bracelets from their sleeping bodies, but we never see their face. I wonder who it could be?</p>
		<p>In the techno cottage, Servalan is questioning Travis's plan: he has somehow manipulated Veron into doing his bidding and everything is running according to his plan because it's his <q>turn</q> now.</p>
		<p>Blake wakes up and announces that the grenade contained <q>sono gas</q><note>We last heard of sono gas - or vapour, as it was called then - during <em><a href="/series-1/episode-7-mission-to-destiny/">Mission to Destiny</a></em></note>. Blake immediately realises it was Veron who lobbed the grenade, but poor, simple Gan can't believe it. Veron's barred them into the cellar, so Gan starts grunting at it. Blake tries to call in to <em>The Liberator</em>, but realises that everyone's tleeport bracelets have been filched.</p>
		<p>Veron delivers the teleport bracelets to Travis. She says <q>the only lies were that I escaped the ambush and that my mother was dead</q>. Travis looks awkwardly at Servalan. Travis breaks the bad news about Kasabi's death to Veron in the only way he knows how: verbally and swiftly followed by a karate-chop to the side of her head. Veron goes down like a sack of potatoes. Servalan ordered Travis to bring Blake to her and he struts off. Servalan says <q>Kasabi's child</q> to herself, because apparently she didn't know that's who Veron is.</p>
		<p>Gan does some more grunting and the priceless antique door is broken through.</p>
		<p>Onboard <em>The Liberator</em>, Cally's getting bored of playing telephone operator, because Blake and the Earth Crew aren't answering their braceletts. Jenna asks for the last contact bearing.</p>
		<p>Travis and the Mutons<note>Sounds like a rockabilly band from the early eighties</note> arrive at the crypt, to find it empty. Travis works out all by himself that Blake is heading for the forbidden zone, because he pulled on his big-boy trousers that morning.</p>
		<p>Avon's plan is to make a channel through the radiation grid with his blaster, then watch with faint amusement, as Blake tries to reach the bunker within the eight (well, six) seconds. Blake makes it, and the rest follow in his footsteps, after further volleys from Avon. Vila starts working on the door.</p>
		<p>Travis works out they're inside <q>Control</q>, but Servalan doesn't have the autority to turn off the radiation grid. She contacts the high council.</p>
		<p>Blake and the gang work their way through Control, walking through a series of identicle corridors with slightly different lighting. They come to a corridor where the floor is electric, but there's a series of monkey bars daftly fitted in the ceiling, so that only phisically fit terrorists can progress<note>This sequence looks as if it's designed to be replicated in playparks the length and breadth of the <jargon type="UK"/></note>. Vila goes next.</p>
		<p>Servalan gets the grid deactivated, then someone enters the techno-cottage. <q>Who are you?</q>, she asks, but we don't see who it is.</p>
		<p>Blake and crew have cleared the monkey bar puzzles and come to the final door<note>You can tell it's the final door because there's a huge Federation logo embossed into it</note>. Vila is momentarily unsure if he can open it or not, so Blake gives him a speech about how important it is. Vila shrugs, puts a credit card in the slot and nothing happens. He takes another credit card, then appears to inject it with something, to spur it along. It works, with some minor grunting from Gan.</p>
		<p>Blake's uncharicteristicly delighted, as he enters a huge, empty room. Then horrified, as he realises it's all been a trick. Travis enters, sarcasitcally laughing. He explains that thirty years previously, Control was moved to a secret location even he doesn't know, and the old server farm left as bait to the Federation's enemies.</p>

		<blockquote class="screenplay">
			<header>
				<p><b>B</b><b>B</b><b>C</b> <b>tv</b></p>
				<h2>Blake's 7</h2>
				<h3>&quot;Pressure Point&quot;</h3>
			</header>

			<p>Cut to:</p>
			<p><abbr title="Interior">Int</abbr>. Control</p>
			<dl>
				<dt>Avon</dt>
				<dd><ins>(to Blake)</ins> There's nothing. Here.</dd>
			</dl>
			<p class="desc">Travis's mirthless laughter softly echos in from outside the room.</p>
			<dl>
				<dt>Avon</dt>
				<dd>Nothin!</dd>
				<dt>Blake</dt>
				<dd>Travis?</dd>
			</dl>
			<p class="desc">Travis enters.</p>
			<dl>
				<dt>Travis</dt>
				<dd>You believed it, Blake. Like all the other fools before you. <q>Destroy <em>Control</em> and you destroy the Federation</q> - no. </dd>
				<dt>Blake</dt>
				<dd><ins>(Grasping at the front of Avon's tunic)</ins> It <em>was</em> here. Everybody knows it was here.</dd>
				<dt>Travis</dt>
				<dd>Of course! We've never concealed it. On the contarary, we've broadcast the fact - we used it as a challenge to our enemies. We invited them to attack Control.</dd>
				<dt>Blake</dt>
				<dd>It was <em>never</em> here?</dd>
				<dt>Travis</dt>
				<dd>It was moved. Thirty years ago.</dd>
				<dt>Blake</dt>
				<dd><ins>(Hissing)</ins> To <em>where</em>?</dd>
				<dt>Travis</dt>
				<dd>Even I don't know that. But it's safe and secure. And will remain so, while those who seek to destroy us believe it's here. You see, it's the great illusion, Blake: You give substance and credibility to an empty room and the real thing becomes ... undetectable. Virtually ... invisible.</dd>
			</dl>

			<footer class="clearfix">
				<p>Commercial and in confidence</p>
				<p>Page 42 of 48</p>
			</footer>
		</blockquote>

		<p>He orders the Mutoids to take their weapons.</p>
		<p>Servalan enters, wearing a dress held together with a silver lizard. She orders Travis to release his prisoners. She does this because Jenna and Veron have her at gun point. Blake gets his guns back, and takes the Mutoid weapons too, as a sort of consolation prize. Blake and his crew leave and Travis orderes the unarmed Mutoids to give chase<note>Presumably they're to subdue Blake and crew using their creepy blood needles</note>. Servalan slaps Travis across the face because he wasn't fast enough lowering his weapons, when she ordered him to.</p>
		<p>They all chase after Blake and Travis lobs a <q>strontium grenade</q>, even though Servalan tells him it's too powerful for such a confined space. The grenade brings the roof down, just as Servalan predicted. The rubble kills Gan. Yes, killed. Gan is dead. Which is the exact phrase Blake uses, to break it to the rest of the crew.</p>
		<p>Veron is staying on Earth: she feels she has a debt to pay, for her mother's death. The others teleport back to <em>The Liberator</em>.</p>
		<p>The last moments of the episode echo those of the origianl <em>Star Trek</em> episode <em><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=EnViskuZrJk" title="'Let's get the hell out of here'">The City on the Edge of Forever</a></em> - Blake just wants to leave the solar system. Blake glances across at the empty station, where Gan used to sit.</p>

		<h2>Watch <em>Pressure Point</em> on YouTube</h2>
		<youtube id="ruI-HONU6lM"/>

	</content>
</page>
