<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="/Dear-Charlotte/xslt/page.xslt"?>
<page>
	<meta>
		<description></description>
		<path>/writing/domestic-servants/</path>
	</meta>
	<content type="main">
		<h1>ServiceHome Ltd. meeting minutes</h1>
		<h2>Research &amp; Development focus meeting, 24/06/66</h2>
		<ul>
			<li>Present: Trixie, Admiral Sass, Brandston, Max.</li>
			<li>Absent: Muffin.</li>
		</ul>
		<h3>Proceedings:</h3>
		<ul>
			<li>Meeting called to order at 11:00am by Chair, Trixie</li>
			<li>Brandston suggested that in light of the legislation changes allowing artificial life, the company shifts <jargon type="R&amp;D"/> from robotics to biology.</li>
			<li>A brief ethical discussion followed, which was interrupted when sunlight shining through the window made an interesting pattern on the wall.</li>
			<li>Admiral Sass complained of feeling sleepy, so moved to vote.</li>
			<li>Unanimous result in favour of policy change, followed by nap.</li>
		</ul>

		<hr/>

		<h2>Product line discussion, 14/03/71</h2>
		<ul>
			<li>Present: Trixie, Admiral Sass, Brandston, Max.</li>
			<li>Absent: Muffin.</li>
		</ul>
		<h3>Proceedings:</h3>
		<ul>
			<li>Meeting called to order at 11:30am by Chair, Trixie</li>
			<li>Max demonstrated functional biological servant prototype.</li>
			<li>Most agreed the prototype was non-threattening, but that the smell was terrible.</li>
			<li>Admiral Sass suggested that to encourage adoption, the product should be &#8220;cute&#8221; - perhaps modeled on a kitten.</li>
			<li>Meeting adjorned when Brandston felt a pressing need to lick his balls.</li>
		</ul>

		<hr/>

		<h2>Latest prototype, 10/01/72</h2>
		<ul>
			<li>Present: Trixie, Admiral Sass, Brandston, Max.</li>
			<li>Absent: Muffin.</li>
		</ul>
		<h3>Proceedings:</h3>
		<ul>
			<li>Meeting called to order at 11:00am by Chair, Trixie</li>
			<li>The latest prototype was seen as excellent, but limited, due to small size and power.</li>
			<li>Product smell greatly improved.</li>
			<li>Trixie suggested new, much larger product line, for use in the construction industry.</li>
			<li>Life-span of all products agreed to be set at five year, guarenteeing future sales and protection against any emergant issues with wet-ware.</li>
			<li>Brandston suggested to adjurn the meeting to go hunting.</li>
		</ul>

		<hr/>

		<h2>New product line, 27/05/72</h2>
		<ul>
			<li>Present: Trixie, Admiral Sass, Brandston, Max.</li>
			<li>Absent: Muffin.</li>
		</ul>
		<h3>Proceedings:</h3>
		<ul>
			<li>Meeting called to order at 10:30am by Chair, Trixie</li>
			<li>Admiral Sass described the latest breakthough of the <jargon type="R&amp;D"/> department - a gland which allows lucid dreaming.</li>
			<li>The gland would also allow the individual to share the same virtual space as anyone else who has a similar device installed.</li>
			<li>Meeting adjurned so the board could have the gland surgically added.</li>
		</ul>

		<hr/>

		<h2>&#8220;Project Retirement&#8221; - Proposal from Max, 22/08/72</h2>
		<ul>
			<li>Present: Trixie, Admiral Sass, Brandston, Max.</li>
			<li>Absent: Muffin.</li>
		</ul>
		<h3>Proceedings:</h3>
		<ul>
			<li>Meeting called to order at 10:00am by Chair, Trixie</li>
			<li>Max proposed that the aim of ServiceHome should be to become obsolete.</li>
			<li>He suggested that through the use of artificial life forms, all physical needs could be taken care of, leading everyone to lead a life comprised 100% of leasure.</li>
			<li>For this to be achieved, more autonomy should be granted to the servants, as they will take change of all production, constrution, waste management, livestock <jargon type="etc"/>.</li>
			<li>Max also suggested that the domestic servants should be created fertile, so they could undertake their own manufacture process. If neccessary, this would go unchecked.</li>
			<li>Max was keen to stress that this was not an alturistic act, but that in light of the lucid dreaming gland, he really wanted to spent most of his time asleep.</li>
			<li>There was broad agreement that more leasure time would be appreciated.</li>
			<li>Meeting adjurned to allow board time to reflect on Max's proposal.</li>
		</ul>

		<hr/>

		<h2>ServiceHome five year plan, 29/08/72</h2>
		<ul>
			<li>Present: Trixie, Admiral Sass, Brandston, Max.</li>
			<li>Absent: Muffin.</li>
		</ul>
		<h3>Proceedings:</h3>
		<ul>
			<li>Meeting called to order at 9:30am by Chair, Trixie</li>
			<li>Trixie noted that productivity is down as more of the workforce spends as much time as possible asleep.</li>
			<li>Admiral Sass presented the latest breakthrough from <jargon type="R&amp;D"/>: the lucid dreaming gland will be inheritable. All future generations will be born with one.</li>
			<li>Brandston suggested that this gives new urgency to Project Retirement.</li>
			<li>Meeting adjurned for snacks and naps.</li>
		</ul>

		<hr/>

		<h2>Product alignment suggestion, 05/10/72</h2>
		<ul>
			<li>Present: Trixie, Admiral Sass, Brandston, Max.</li>
			<li>Absent: Muffin.</li>
		</ul>
		<h3>Proceedings:</h3>
		<ul>
			<li>Meeting called to order at 11:00am by Chair, Trixie</li>
			<li>Trixie suggested that all product lines should be merged into one, strong enough to undertake construction tasks but sensative enough to be domestic servants too.</li>
			<li>Admiral Sass raised the issue of ethics: how could such autonimous beings be programmed to care for the entire population?</li>
			<li>Meeting degenerated into confused phisosophy.</li>
			<li>Ethics issue parked, then assigned to the ethics sub-committee.</li>
			<li>Meeting adjurned for naps.</li>
		</ul>

	</content>
</page>