<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="/Dear-Charlotte/xslt/page.xslt"?>
<page>
	<meta>
		<description>Episode 3: Cygnus Alpha. Blake, Jenna and Avon get to Cygnus Alpha, which turns out to be the home of a cult. Gan and Vila fall ill and are given an antidote by the monks, but they need to keep taking it for the rest of their lives. Blake beams down and is captured. There's a big duff-up and everyone plus the cult leader ends up on The Liberator. The cult leader gets beamed into space and RUDDY EXPLODES.</description>
		<path>/Dear-Charlotte/series-1/episode-3-cygnus-alpha/</path>
		<type>episode</type>
	</meta>
	<content type="main">
		<h1>Episode 3: Cygnus Alpha</h1>
		<p>So in the last episode, Blake, Vila and Jenna escaped the prison ship <em>London</em>, which was bound for Cygnus Alpha, a prison planet<note>Think of your childhood home, Australia, but with significantly less sun</note>.</p>
		<p>On the <em>London</em>, Leylan prepares to land on Cygnus Alpha. He does a little recap of the previous episode, which happens in black and white, because it's the past.</p>

		<h2>Show me your o-face</h2>
		<p>On the alien ship, Avon finds some guns. Jenna's trying to work out the ship while Blake and Avon sort of stand about. Jenna presses a wrong button, and we see what the actors look like with high powered fans blowing at them:</p>
		<blockquote class="imgur-embed-pub" lang="en" data-id="GiZUXUi"><a href="/Dear-Charlotte//imgur.com/GiZUXUi">Blake, Avon and Jenna test out The Liberator.</a></blockquote><script async="" src="//s.imgur.com/min/embed.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
		<p>It's not pretty.</p>
		<p>Turns out that the ship is faster than anything the Terran Federation have.</p>
		
		<h2>Facebook helps you connect and share with the people in your life</h2>
		<p>Jenna gets sort of psychologically invaded by the computer which involves <a href="/Dear-Charlotte/charlotte-responds/rada-acting/">ALL OF THE FACIAL EXPRESSIONS WHICH <jargon type="RADA"/> TEACHES</a>. Basically, the computer (Zen) is checking out if Jenna's cool or not. She turns out to be cool.</p>
		<p>Zen starts speaking. He sounds almost exactly like <a href="https://youtu.be/-YttqW-Da8o?t=18m37s" title="Jump to the middle of an episode of 'University Challenge', where a name gets read out.">the man who reads out the names on <em>University Challenge</em></a>. He avoids Blake's questions about the previous occupants of the ship, but takes them where they want to go. Which kind of suggests there's no need for Jenna.</p>
		
		<h2>Not Amnesty International</h2>
		<p>There's a small chat about <jargon type="AI"/>, which I find interesting because the position of <jargon type="AI"/> is often a defining characteristic of science fiction universes<note>To take three examples, in <em>Dune</em>, <jargon type="AI"/> is completely outlawed. <jargon type="AI"/> doesn't seem to exist in <em>Firefly</em> because Joss Whedon wanted no robots or aliens in the show. Hang on - I think in <em>Serenity</em> there was a robot sex doll. In the <em>Mass Effect</em> series, the theme of <jargon type="AI"/> having <q>human</q> rights comes up several times.</note>. From their discussion it would seen that true AI is not widespread in The Terran Federation.</p>
		<p>Meanwhile, the <em>London</em> lands on Cygnus Alpha.</p>
		<p>Jenna, Blake and Avon find the teleporter. Which is another thing no-one else in the Terran Federation has. We learn that the ship is called <q>The Liberator</q>, because that was something Jenna was thinking about, while Zen was poking about her frontal lobes. Blake plans to take the teleport system down to Cygnus Alpha.</p>
		<p>The <em>London</em> drops the prisoners off on Cygnus Alpha and leaves. The prisoners find evidence of a weird cult.</p>
		<p>Blake teleports down to the planet COMPLETELY UNARMED:</p>

		<blockquote class="imgur-embed-pub" lang="en" data-id="11cvdO2"><a href="/Dear-Charlotte//imgur.com/11cvdO2">View post on imgur.com</a></blockquote><script async="" src="//s.imgur.com/min/embed.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
		
		<ross>
			<p>I quite like Blake's stumble. I get the impression that this was something the actors thought up, which wasn't in the script. But I could be wrong.</p>
		</ross>

		<h2>Bad habits</h2>
		<p>He spots a bunch of monks who chase him about a gravel pit and are just about to stab him right up, when he gets teleported away.</p>
		
		<ross>
		
			<figure class="img-r">
				<img src="/Dear-Charlotte/img/series-1/episode-3-cygnus-alpha/gravel-pit.jpg" height="120" width="120" alt="Blake, pursued by evil monks, tries to escape up a gravel pit"/>
			</figure>

			<h2>This is the pits</h2>
			
			<p><a href="/Dear-Charlotte/charlotte-responds/use-of-quarries/">Let's talk about gravel pits</a>. There's a tired running joke that gravel pits act as a stand-in for alien planets in <em>Blake's 7</em>. And this scene is the genesis of this idea. Look - there on the right - it's Blake! Scrabbling up some gravel!</p>
			<p>It's true that certain locations <em>do</em> seem to get reused. I wish they'd used more brutalist architecture, though. That stuff was built for sci-fi<note>See: <em>A Clockwork Orange</em> and <em>Attack the Block</em></note>.</p>
		
		</ross>
		
		<p>The prisoners spot this castle:</p>
		<figure>
			<img src="/Dear-Charlotte/img/series-1/episode-3-cygnus-alpha/early-maniac.jpg" alt=""/>
			<figcaption>Vila memorably describes the architectural style as <q>Early maniac</q></figcaption>
		</figure>
		<p>They <a href="/Dear-Charlotte/charlotte-responds/weird-cults/">meet some cultist</a> one of whom is a SEXY LADY<note>She's called <q>Kara</q> and doesn't have a page on the <a href="http://blakes7.wikia.com/">Blake's 7 Wiki</a>. This is sad.</note>. Then she kisses Gan. Because of course she does.</p>

		<biog>
			<src>/img/characters/kara.png</src>
			<info type="Name">Kara</info>
			<info type="Job">Priestess</info>
			<info type="Dramatic role">Weird attempt to reposition Gan as <q>the sexy one</q></info>
			<info type="Favourite textile">Hessian</info>
			<info type="Favourite word"><q>Forsooth</q></info>
		</biog>
		
		<p>Blake goes down to the planet again, this time remembering to PACK HEAT. He enters the castle which looks exactly like a reused set from a different production. The SEXY WOMAN does some praying then ruddy Brian Blessed<note>I'm frankly amazed to learn that Brian Blessed didn't act in a single episode of <em>Doctor Who</em> during Tom Baker's reign. He did do an episode of <em>Space: 1999</em> though.</note> turns up, playing the part of BRIAN BLESSED. Blake skulks behind a pillar and watches them.</p>

		<biog>
			<src>/img/characters/vargas.png</src>
			<info type="Name">VARGAS</info>
			<info type="Job">LEADER OF THE WORSHIPPERS OF CYGNUS</info>
			<info type="Dramatic role">ANTAGONIST</info>
			<info type="Aren't these usually in sentence case?">YES, BUT IT'S BRIAN BLESSED</info>
			<info type="Acting intensity (1&#160;-&#160;10)">Between 11 and &#8734;</info>
		</biog>
		
		<char>
			<figure class="img-r">
				<img src="/Dear-Charlotte/img/series-1/episode-3-cygnus-alpha/nicola-bryant-as-peri.jpg" alt=""/>
				<figcaption>Nicola Bryant as Peri</figcaption>
			</figure>
			<p>Brian Blessed did in fact turn up in the later Colin Baker era (no relation, less hair) as King Ycarnos. The companion at the time was Peri, played by the very beautiful Nicola Bryant. Because the story is set in a Time Lord trial, her character has two alternative endings:</p>
			<ol>
				<li>Her brain is removed and replaced by that of a slug.</li>
				<li>She marries Brian Blessed.</li>
			</ol>
			<p>I leave you to decide which is the worse fate.</p>
		</char>

		<p>They do some fruity cod-religious nonsense, then the SEXY LADY takes a plate of extra-strong mints to the prisoners. No, I'm <em>not</em> joking. It's their medicine.</p>
		<p>Blake talks to the prisoners through the bars and finds out they're all ill from the planet or something. Turns out they need to eat extra strong mints for the rest of their life, or they'll die of <q>The Curse of Cygnus Alpha</q>. Blake wants to see if he can secure a supply of extra-strong mints, but before he can do so, he gets clobbered right up his bonce, then captured.</p>
		<p>More importantly, on <em>The Liberator</em>, Jenna has found the costume department room and picks out a floaty little number with some practical trousers.</p>
		
		<h2>Back story</h2>
		<p>Brian Blessed starts chewing scenery at Blake, who is manacled to a chair. It turns out that Blessed is descended from the first batch of prisoners who created the religion to unite the planet.</p>

		<ross>

			<p>Let's have another break. This time, I've got a little treat for you: a peek behind the curtain, of <a href="https://soundcloud.com/user-708498335/directing-brian-blessed-1">what it was like to direct Brian Blessed</a> in the scene described above. Here, from 1978, is Vere Lorrimer doing exactly that:</p>
			
			<p><iframe width="100%" height="166" scrolling="no" frameborder="no" src="https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/271368789&amp;color=ff5500&amp;auto_play=false&amp;hide_related=false&amp;show_comments=true&amp;show_user=true&amp;show_reposts=false"></iframe></p>
			
			<p>Now, back to the blog.</p>
		
		</ross>
		
		<p>The religion practised on Cygnus Alpha has some similarities with a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cargo_cult">cargo cult</a> - fresh inmates are delivered the Cygnus Alpha on a regular basis, allowing Vargas to grow his flock<note>Fun fact: <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prince_Philip_Movement">Prince Philip is worshipped by the Kastom people in Vanuatu</a>. Fun fact 2: Prince Philip is known for his views on race being ... perhaps a little out of step with current thinking. Alanis Morissette ought to write a song about this.</note>.</p>
		<p>Blessed - sorry, <em>Vargas</em> - wants <em>The Liberator</em> so he can export his subtle mixture of medieval nonsense, Hessian and shouting throughout the galaxy.</p>
		
		<ross>
			<h2>Wrath Vargas</h2>
			<p>You might recognise chunks of this plot from <em>Star Trek II: The Wrath of Khan</em>, which came out four years after this episode was broadcast. Given how much <em>Blake's 7</em> borrowed from <em>Star Trek</em>, I'm going to let it slide.</p>
		</ross>

		<p>Back on <em>The Liberator</em>, Avon, following Jenna's directions, finds a room full of costume jewellery. Apparently it's worth a lot of money. Avon wants to leg it and live like kings but Jenna feels she's got to give Blake a chance to wrap up the main plot, or she won't enjoy her new wealth.</p>
		<p>Blake gets tortured and thrown in with the rest of the prisoners. He gives a rousing, unrealistic speech, and Gan joins his cause. They start planning something, and the camera cuts away, before we can find out what it is.</p>
		
		<h2>Drunken punch-up at a sacrifice</h2>
		<p>Gan is lead by monks to be sacrificed and lies down on the sacrificing table strangely passively BUT WAIT IT'S ALL A TRICK! There's a terrible fight scene. It goes on for far too long. Kara gets a spear which was intended for Gan, when she warns him at the last moment<note>This is confusing because when Gan was about to be stabbed in the chest by Vargas, she showed no emotion whatsoever.</note>.</p>
		
		<char>
			<p>It's a bit of a running theme that <a href="/Dear-Charlotte/series-1/episode-12-deliverance/#charlotte-comment-5">people who fall for the Dr's companion, Sarah Jane, normally end up copping it badly</a>. I like the idea that Nation was trying to do the same with Gan. Turn him into a sort of 'gurn-fatale' if you will.</p>
		</char>
		
		<p>Blake saves Vila, who almost immediately returns the favour by stabbing up a monk who's going for Blake.</p>
		<p>The crew all have teleport bracelets on but Avon isn't beaming them up because he wants to fly off and live like a prince, even though Blake has asked for teleport. Vargas corners Blake with a blaster then Jenna finally teleports all of them (Vargas included) up to <em>The Liberator</em>. It turns out the pills are just placebos.</p>
		<p>Vargas holds the crew up with his a blaster and even worse, gives another shouty speech. As he's gesticulating wildly, he steps onto the teleporter platform. By this time, <em>The Liberator</em> is moving away from Cygnus Alpha, so when Blake hits the teleporter panel, this happens:</p>
		<blockquote class="imgur-embed-pub" lang="en" data-id="MgwGH8a"><a href="/Dear-Charlotte//imgur.com/MgwGH8a">This is why you should never try and teleport when you&#39;re out of range.</a></blockquote><script async="" src="//s.imgur.com/min/embed.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
		<p><em>The Liberator</em> gets detected by some Federation pursuit ships, so legs it.</p>

		<h2>Watch <em>Cygnus Alpha</em> on YouTube</h2>
		<youtube id="cqglSCyNZDY"/>
	</content>
</page>