<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="/xslt/page.xslt"?>
<page>
	<meta>
		<description>Episode 4: Time Squad. Blake finds a loose space probe full of frozen leather men, and brings it aboard The Liberator. Avon defrosts them and then follows Blake and Vila down to Saurian Major, where they plan to blow up a Federation communications relay. They meet Cally, a resistance fighter, team up and destroy the relay. Meanwhile, Gan and Jenna have various struggles with the leather men, who all end up dead. We learn that Gan has a brain implant which stops him from killing people.</description>
		<path>/series-1/episode-4-time-squad/</path>
		<type>episode</type>
	</meta>
	<content type="main">
		<h1>Episode 4: Time Squad</h1>
		<p>In the last episode, Blake saved Vila and Gan from Cygnus Alpha, a prison planet with a taste for culty religion and a sort of high-camp cover version of <em>The Name of the Rose</em><note><em>The Name of the Rose</em> was published two years after <em>Cygnus Alpha</em>. I'm not saying the events in that novel were inspired by an episode of <em>Blake's 7</em>. But I'm not <em>not</em> saying it either.</note>. They exploded Brian Ruddy Blessed then went on their merry way, pursued by Federation Pursuit ships, appropriately enough.</p>
		
		<ross>
			<h2>Model behaviour</h2>
			<figure class="img-r">
				<img src="/img/series-1/episode-4-time-squad/cardboard-liberator.jpg" width="200" alt=""/>
				<figcaption>The cardboard Liberator</figcaption>
			</figure>
			<p>The episode starts with a 2D animated <em>Liberator</em> in space. The special effects in <em>Blake's 7</em> shift between <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rostrum_camera">rostrum camera work</a> and proper, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gerry_Anderson">Gerry Anderson</a> style models, seemingly at will. I've no problem with the flat style appearing in the opening titles, but for whatever reason, this method sometimes makes it into the body of the episodes too. As a child, this would make me <em>furious</em>. Couldn't they see that <em>The Liberator</em> was the second-most important character (after Vila)? This would be like if they <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=mufix337VbQ" title="That scene in 'Scrubs' where the janitor makes a cutout of JD.">made the main character of a <jargon type="TV"/> series out of cardboard</a>, and expected you not to notice. As an adult, I've learnt to hide this fury.</p>
		</ross>

		<p>Jenna's teaching Blake how to fly <em>The Liberator</em>, while Avon grumbles in the background. They've managed to escape the Federation Pursuit ships which turned up at the end of the previous episode.</p>
		
		<h2>Have you tried turning it off, and then leaving it off forever?</h2>
		<p>Blake plans to take the fight to the Federation, so he plots a course to Saurian Major, a planet which tried to become independent from The Federation, but was crushed. Now it's a sort of telephone exchange for the Galaxy. Blake wants to turn it off.</p>
		<p>On the way there, they encounter a distress call from <q cite="http://blakes7.wikia.com/wiki/Time_Squad_(dialogue_transcript)">a projectile</q>. It's tiny<note>Jenna warns that the signal might be a ruse by <q cite="http://blakes7.wikia.com/wiki/Time_Squad_(dialogue_transcript)">space pirates</q>. I quite like this, because Jenna has worked with space pirates in her shady past, plus she's a pilot. This is exactly the sort of thing she'd know.</note>. Blake and Jenna plan to teleport abroad. Zen goes a bit weird, when he's answering their questions about the projectile<note>He sounds like <a href="https://youtu.be/nIimxRH8vqw?t=2m47s" title="Modified Speak 'n' Spell demo, by circuitbenz">a modified Speak 'n' Spell</a>, which incidentally first came out the year this episode aired.</note>.</p>
		<p>Gan suggests that Zen has a <q cite="http://blakes7.wikia.com/wiki/Time_Squad_(dialogue_transcript)">limiter</q>, which prevents him from helping the crew too much. FORESHADOWING.</p>
		
		<h2>The frozen aisle</h2>
		<p>Blake and Jenna teleport over to the probe standing stock upright, but rematerialise sort of crouched. It's annoying.</p>
		<p>The ship is small and basic and includes three people in cryogenic suspension, one of whom is dead. Jenna and Blake have a butchers at one of them, who has veins all over his face. He looks a bit like a blue cheese.</p>
		
		<ross>
			<h3>Is it just me, or does this dead guy make you horny?</h3>
			<p>So this probe is tiny - it's about the size of a camper van. And they built both an interior and full-sized exterior of it for the episode. So Blake and Jenna are having to clamber about, poking buttons and squeezing past each other. But there's no sexual tension whatsoever. They conduct themselves with all of the sensuality of sewerage workers.</p>
			<p>I like it.</p>
		</ross>
		
		<p>The air's running out and Blake and Jenna can't teleport off because of Zen's suspicious malfunctions. Avon is forced to bring the probe into the cargo hatch of <em>The Liberator</em><note>The docking scene is a lot like one of those buzz wire games which were common in the late 1970s (seriously, you could hardly move without tripping over one of the blasted things). This idea of taking something mundane and transplanting it into this <jargon type="sci-fi"/> universe will crop up again later.</note>.</p>
		<p>Avon pokes about in the ship, then starts the defrosting process of the surviving crew. Because what's the worst that could happen?</p>
		
		<h2>Communications blackout</h2>
		<p><em>The Liberator</em> arrives at Saurian Major. Blake assembles his party: Vila for his lock pick skills and Avon for his hacking skills<note>Presumably he ensures they are levelled up and have their best possible gear first.</note>. They find some fleshy plants. Blake plans to make friends with the local rebels before assaulting the communications centre.</p>
		<p>On <em>The Liberator</em>, Gan confesses to Jenna that he murdered a guard because the guard killed <q cite="http://blakes7.wikia.com/wiki/Time_Squad_(dialogue_transcript)">my woman</q>.</p>
		<p>Jenna goes down to the hold to check on the folk from the probe. She notices one of them is missing and there's an incredibly long scene where she tries to find him in the suspiciously dark cargo hold<note>The music for this scene is a slightly distorted organ. They're playing the horror movie card.</note>. She repeats the phrase <q cite="http://blakes7.wikia.com/wiki/Time_Squad_(dialogue_transcript)">we're not going to harm you</q>. Then this happens:</p>
		
		<blockquote class="imgur-embed-pub" lang="en" data-id="RfgnAAb"><a href="//imgur.com/RfgnAAb">Jenna meets a defrosted ancient spaceman.</a></blockquote><script async="" src="//s.imgur.com/min/embed.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
				
		<p>To be fair to Jenna, the bloke did lob a bright purple wrench at her, so he was asking to get his arm bit. Gan performs FUTURE MEDICINE on Jenna's arm, then goes to check on the defrosted bloke.</p>
		
		<char>
			<p>I do love a bit of trippy space medicine. In the fourth Doctor's era, (ignoring the shiny nonsense that is the Bi-Al Foundation), methods include spray-based (<em>Ribos Operation</em>), glittery bandage-based (<em>Robots of Death</em>), tickertape analysis-based (<em>Face of Evil</em>) and what looks like a massive gob stopper and flower injection device (<em>Ark in Space</em>). Possibly the props department were enjoying a few pills of their own.</p>
			<p>I've often wondered to what extent Time Lords get injured, bearing in mind they can regenerate. This may yet form another specialist essay.</p>
			<p>In other news: I learnt today the naked mole rat is able to maintain near-perfect muscle structure into old age. Nothing to do with this blog, but isn't that interesting? You're welcome.</p>
		</char>
		
		<h2>The path to telepathy</h2>
		<p>Blake finally meets a member of the resistance, who immediately rolls him down the side of a gravel pit<note>Yes, yes. I <em>know</em>.</note>. She speaks to him using THE POWER OF HER MIND, because she's a telepath<note>Cally suggests that telepaths can hear each other's thoughts all of the time, but can't hear thoughts of non-telepaths. They can <em>send</em> thoughts to non-telepaths, though. This definition of telepathy is mostly ignored from then on.</note>. Blake turns the tables on her, then tells her his plans. She doesn't believe him then it gets worse: Vila calls her <q cite="http://blakes7.wikia.com/wiki/Time_Squad_(dialogue_transcript)">pretty lady</q>. Turns out her name is Cally and is the only surviving freedom fighter left on the planet, after the Federation <q cite="http://blakes7.wikia.com/wiki/Time_Squad_(dialogue_transcript)">released poison from the sky</q>. They agree to team up.</p>
		<p>Gan's gone missing on <em>The Liberator</em>, so Jenna goes looking for him. She notices that someone is recharging the probe, but decides not to mess with the huge cable, snaking across the floor. Jenna enters the probe and notices that all of the cryogenic chambers are empty. She somehow misses that Gan is there too, semi-conscious. One of the men attacks her. He's dressed like a <a href="http://gameofthrones.wikia.com/wiki/Dothraki">Dothraki</a>. She gives him a good zapping and Gan crawls out of the probe.</p>

		<figure class="img-r">
			<img src="/img/series-1/episode-4-time-squad/ebe.jpg" alt=""/>
			<figcaption>Gan's <jargon type="EBE"/></figcaption>
		</figure>

		<p>It turns out that Gan has a <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=spF6A2QK31s" title="'Go easy on your EBEs', from 'Look Around You'">brain implant</a> which means it's impossible for him to kill anybody any more. And that the frozen folk kill anyone who isn't like them.</p>
		<p>Cally, Blake, Avon and Vila arrive at the communications centre. It's a nice use of an industrial location. They scamper along a bunch of catwalks.</p>
		<p>Vila gets them past a big locked door<note>Presumably levelling up in the process</note>, then the guards arrive and we move to a studio set, rather than the nice industrial location.</p>
		
		<h2>Firefox has stopped responding</h2>
		<p>Jenna gets attacked by another leather man and does <a href="/charlotte-responds/stage-fighting/">some basic <jargon type="RADA"/> tumbling</a>. He gets her gun but it doesn't work because it's not plugged into the power brick. Gan bursts in, and tries to shoot him, but his <jargon type="EBE"/> makes him do this:</p>
		
		<blockquote class="imgur-embed-pub" lang="en" data-id="JN8bXkq"><a href="//imgur.com/JN8bXkq">Remember people, go easy on your EBEs.https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=spF6A2QK31s</a></blockquote><script async="" src="//s.imgur.com/min/embed.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
		
		<p>Luckily Jenna is allowed to kill all the Dothraki she wants, so she blows him away.</p>
		<p><em>The Liberator</em> keeps getting brownouts, which Jenna realises is to do with the power drain from the cable she noticed attached to the probe earlier. She goes to disconnect it, while Gan struggles to the flight deck, because his <jargon type="EBE"/> is giving him jip.</p>
		
		<ross>
			<h2>Brownouts</h2>
			<p>Let's put this episode in a bit of context: it was broadcast on the 23rd of January, 1978, one year before <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Winter_of_Discontent">the Winter of Discontent</a>.</p>
			<p>Industrial action in the late 1970s and early 1980s caused fluctuating power supply to be much more frequent than we would expect today. I remember from my early childhood candles being kept in the house not as mood lighting, but in case the electricity went off.</p>
			<p>The previous year had seen <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New_York_City_blackout_of_1977">the blackout of New York</a>. In a similar way to how <em>Doctor Who</em> often took something mundane from the real world, and use it to cause nightmares in children, Terry Nation may have been inspired by real-world events to add this fluctuating power.</p>
		</ross>
		
		<h2>Windows updates have been successfully installed</h2>
		<p>Zen has finally finished reverse-engineering the computer from the probe. It turns out that the Dothraki were just the muscle. The cargo they were protecting is the <q cite="http://blakes7.wikia.com/wiki/Time_Squad_(dialogue_transcript)">brood units and genetic banks</q> found in the boot of the probe. Also, there's one more <q cite="http://blakes7.wikia.com/wiki/Time_Squad_(dialogue_transcript)">guardian</q> to worry about. Gan moves the corpse of the guardian Jenna just killed, calls her name, then faints like a great big Jessie.</p>
		<p>Avon finishes his sabotage and Blake asks for teleport. Gan manages to pull them up, despite feeling a bit weak and weepy. The guards burst into the room, and a tiny explosion sends them tumbling to the floor like ninepins.</p>
		<p>The final, backup guardian creeps up behind Jenna while she's trying to unplug their <jargon type="USB"/> charging cable, but Blake warns her just in time, so we see this indignity:<note>Charlotte was struck by how similar this shot is to The Doctor's electrocution scene in <em>Genesis of the Daleks</em>. Whereas I think the guy below looks like <a href="https://www.google.com/search?tbm=isch&amp;q=andy+serkis">Andy Serkis</a>.</note></p>
		
		<blockquote class="imgur-embed-pub" lang="en" data-id="CoIqcLO"><a href="//imgur.com/CoIqcLO">The backup guardian creeps out of the boot, and tries to stab Jenna up. He fails.</a></blockquote><script async="" src="//s.imgur.com/min/embed.js" charset="utf-8"></script>


		<p>This man trained for five years for this moment.</p>
		
		<h2>The tiny explosion which could</h2>
		<p>The crew watch the planet, or the communications base, or something, exploding on the view screen<note>It's not really clear what we're seeing. It just looks like tiny explosions and puffs of smoke</note>.</p>
		<p>Blake asks if Cally wants a lift home, but it turns out she's not allowed to, because she failed, somehow.</p>
		<p>Avon says that the probe can manufacture guardians out of the cells in the boot. Not quite sure how he knows this. Perhaps he's reading Zen's logs. Zen knew the probe was bad news, but chose to inform the crew by pretending to go a bit wonky for a bit. Zen's a <em>twat</em>, is my point. When <em>my</em> computer doesn't want me to do something, it throws dialogue boxes at me until my spirit's broken. <em>Speaking in a slightly weird voice doesn't cut it, Zen</em>.</p>
		<p>We also finally learn why the show's called <em>Blake's <strong>7</strong></em>: they now have six humanoid crew members<note>Cally's an alien from the plant Auron. At least I <em>think</em> she's an alien.</note> and also Zen.</p>
		<p>Blake sets a course for Centero and Avon looks disgusted.</p>
		
		<ross>
			<h2>Genre-shifting</h2>
			<p>It's still really hard to predict where individual episodes of <em>Blake's 7</em> are likey to go. The show still resolutely refuses to adhere to any kind of repeating structure. However, this episode does loosely follow the formula which <em>Star Trek</em> quickly established: twin plot lines, one on the ship, the other on a planet. A good deed gone wrong. You know the sort of thing.</p>
			<p>The difference is that <em>Star Trek</em> was rarely about using violence (and terrorist violence at that) to solve problems.</p>
			
			<h2>From telepathy to antipathy</h2>
			<p>This episode is book ended with two similar scenes: Blake makes a decision about where they're going and what they'll do when they get there, Avon disagrees and tries to open it up to debate, and they end up doing Blake's thing anyway.</p>
			<p>Avon is a bit like <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=edflm7Hh3hs" title="Worf getting shut down on Star Trek the Next Generation">Worf</a> in this regard - his values are often opposed to those around him, and his input is ignored for this reason. Avon hides his altruism and idealism well, but it does exist. And I get the sense that the script wants him to join the rest of the crew as they go about happily murdering Federation guards.</p>
		</ross>

		<h2>Watch <em>Time Squad</em> on YouTube</h2>
		<youtube id="oQTt5y_phVU"/>
	</content>
</page>