<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="/Dear-Charlotte/xslt/page.xslt"?>
<page>
	<meta>
		<description>Episode 9: Project Avalon. Travis captures Avalon, a resistance leader who is trying to liberate an ice planet. He knows Blake will try and free Avalon, so he sets up a trap involving a tiny pink ball of death. Blake, Vila, Cally and Chevner (another member of the resistance) break Avalon out of jail with apparent ease, but Blake realises that it's a trap. Avalon turns out to be a robot so Avon reprograms her and Blake uses her to extract the real Avalon.</description>
		<path>/Dear-Charlotte/series-1/episode-9-project-avalon/</path>
		<type>episode</type>
	</meta>
	<content type="main">
		<h1>Episode 9: Project Avalon</h1>

		<figure class="img-r">
			<img src="/Dear-Charlotte/img/series-1/episode-9-project-avalon/travis-in-a-cave.jpg" alt=""/>
			<figcaption>Hey Travis. <em>Travis</em>. Travis. TRAVIS. Travis: What do you call a big prick in a cave? A stalactite. A ha ha ha ha ha ha ha oh God, I'm so lonely.</figcaption>
		</figure>

		<p>In the last episode, Travis and Blake were forced to have a ruddy big duff-up in a foggy wood, while their gal-pals ably assisted. Blake bested Travis, who threw a strop, and arranged to have his gal-pal murdered. Which was a shame, because <a href="/Dear-Charlotte/series-1/episode-8-duel/#the-mutoid-previously-known-as-keyeira">she is the most metal character in <em>Blake's 7</em></a>. Blake implied that Travis was, like, <em>totally</em> obsessed with him? And he didn't even <em>think</em> about Travis? In this episode, Travis hatches a new plan, which he calls PROJECT AVALON. Travis, you so silly!</p>
		<h2>I am a Mole and I Live in a Hole</h2>
		<p>Travis and his <jargon type="YTS"/> Mutoid are on UNNAMED SNOW PLANET. They creep about a cave for a spell, before meeting Terloc, who is their mole<note>I've literally just got this joke. He's a mole who lives in a cave.</note> inside the resistance movement there. Terloc tells Travis that Avalon, the leader of the local resistance, wants Blake to take her somewhere.</p>
		<p><em>The Liberator</em> has arrived at the ice planet.</p>
		
		<ross>
			<h2>Blog notification</h2>
			<p>The planet doesn't seem to have a name, which is a shame. To make it easier to follow, I'll refer to the ice planet henceforth as <q>Sparkletown</q>.</p>
		</ross>
		
		<p><em>The Liberator</em> has arrived at <em>Sparkletown</em>. Jenna needs to teleport down with Blake because she's met Avalon before and knows her a bit. Avon starts giving some background information:</p>

		<blockquote class="screenplay">
			<header>
				<p><b>B</b><b>B</b><b>C</b> <b>tv</b></p>
				<h2>Blake's 7</h2>
				<h3>&quot;Project Avalon&quot;</h3>
			</header>
			
			<dl>
				<dt>Avon</dt>
				<dd>And don't imagine they'll maintain the same orbit. I've summarised the relevant data.</dd>
				<dt>Blake</dt>
				<dd>And?</dd>
				<dt>Avon</dt>
				<dd>We've come at the worst time, of course. The northern hemisphere is just entering its winter cycle. They call it <q cite="http://blakes7.wikia.com/wiki/Project_Avalon_(dialogue_transcript)">the long cold</q>. Something of an understatement: it lasts the equivalent of eight and a half earth years.</dd>
				<dt>Blake</dt>
				<dd>Does it support any intelligent life?</dd>
				<dt>Avon</dt>
				<dd>Does The Liberator? <ins>He looks at Jenna</ins></dd>
			</dl>
			
			<footer class="clearfix">
				<p>Commercial and in confidence</p>
				<p>Page 4 of 53</p>
			</footer>
		</blockquote>
		
		<p>Jenna does this:</p>
		
		<blockquote class="imgur-embed-pub" lang="en" data-id="CVEeNGt"><a href="/Dear-Charlotte//imgur.com/CVEeNGt">Directed at Avon, naturally.</a></blockquote><script async="" src="//s.imgur.com/min/embed.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
		
		<ross>
			<h2>Eye roll if you want to, this lady's not for rolling</h2>
			<p>The robust community in <a href="http://imgur.com/gallery/CVEeNGt">Imgur</a> assure me that whatever Jenna is doing above, it's certainly <em>not</em> an eye roll. Eye rolls are MASSIVE.</p>
			<p>Sally Knyvette is a <em>classically trained actor</em>. She's aware that television acting is a completely different discipline to that which is practised on the stage. <em>This</em>, fine folk of Imgur, is what ACTING looks like.</p>
		</ross>
		
		<p>Avon's back story is that the population of <em>Sparkletown</em> were enslaved by the Federation in order to work in the mines, so Avalon turned up in order to emancipate them.</p>
		
		<h2>When Mutoids attack</h2>
		<p>A large group of Mutoids locates Avalon's terrorist cell and surrounds them. They call for Avalon to come forward, and one guy tries to <em>Spartacus</em> himself, but the others don't join in, so he ends up looking a right prat. Luckily, he's spared further embarrassment when Avalon herself steps forward and the Mutoids slaughter everyone else, including Terloc, their man on the inside.</p>
		
		<ross>

			<figure class="img-r">
				<img src="/Dear-Charlotte/img/series-1/episode-9-project-avalon/yts-mutoid.jpg" alt=""/>
				<figcaption>Travis' <jargon type="YTS"/> Mutoid</figcaption>
			</figure>
		
			<h2>Child labour</h2>
			<p>I suspect Travis' new Mutoid is on work experience from school. What is she, fourteen years old?</p>
			<p>She's played by Glynis Barber, who we'll be seeing again at some point in the future, in a very different role. Glynis Barber is so famous that when I typed <q>glynis</q> into my search box, <em>the <q>barber</q> was auto-completed</em>. Now it's quite possible that I've got myself into one of those Internet echo chambers you hear about, where every search result loops back to <em>Blake's 7</em>. Or perhaps it's the fact that <em>Glynis Barber was one half of <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=CFfFuwd5L5c" title="Dempsey and Makepeace title sequence">Dempsey and Makepeace</a>!</em></p>
			<p>Come on, you <em>must</em> remember it. It was like a British version of <em>Moonlighting</em>. It was <em>massive</em> in the Eastern Block.</p>
		</ross>

		<p>Blake and Jenna teleport down and find the bodies and Chevner, one of the rebels who's only a <em>bit</em> dead. He tells them that Avalon has been taken away.</p>

		<h2>Scenes of a sexual nature</h2>
		<p>Inside the Federation base on <em>Sparkletown</em>, Avalon has been put into what appears to be <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=J04gTJvynjg" title="Barbarella gets uh ... played like an instrument.">the Excessive Machine</a> and dressed as Leeloo from <em>The Fifth Element</em><note>I'd have taken a screen grab, but this is not that sort of blog.</note>. Travis tells Avalon that he plans to use her to take <em>The Liberator</em>.</p>

		<biog>
			<src>/Dear-Charlotte/img/characters/avalon.png</src>
			<info type="Name">Avalon</info>
			<info type="Job">Leader of various resistance cells</info>
			<info type="Dramatic role">McGuffin</info>
			<info type="Skills">Bandage wearing, stiff-upper-lip-haver</info>
			<info type="Hobbies">Tennis, writing letters, horse riding, jigsaws</info>
			<info type="Perfect day off">Just wandering about in my fuchsia jim-jams, happy as a clam</info>
		</biog>
		
		<ross>
			<a href="/Dear-Charlotte/img/series-1/episode-9-project-avalon/levett-hope-poster.svg" class="img-r" title="Download the poster in SVG format"><img src="/Dear-Charlotte/img/series-1/episode-9-project-avalon/levett-hope-poster.png" alt=""/></a>
			<h2>Casting call</h2>
			<p>Avalon's supposed to be this great inspirational figure, who's set up rebellion cells on multiple worlds, but you wouldn't know it from Julia Vidler's performance. I'm concerned that the casting criteria was <q>will look good with her erogenous zones covered with thin strips of bandage, while getting a strobe light to the face</q><note>I've since learnt that Julia Vidler was in the original running for the character of Jenna.</note>.</p>
			<p>A much better choice (in my opinion) would have been Kate Coleridge, who played <a href="/Dear-Charlotte/series-1/episode-7-mission-to-destiny/#levett">Levett</a> in <em>Mission to Destiny</em>: she barely gets two lines, but makes it quite clear that she takes no nonsense from anyone.</p>
			<p>Are we still doing Obama <q cite="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Barack_Obama_%22Hope%22_poster">Hope</q> poster jokes? It <em>was</em> almost ten years ago now. Well, I've spent the morning wrestling with <a href="https://inkscape.org/">Inkscape</a> so <a href="/Dear-Charlotte/img/series-1/episode-9-project-avalon/levett-hope-poster.svg" title="Download the poster in SVG format">this poster</a> is going in, HUMOUR BE DAMNED.</p>
		</ross>

		<p>Blake patches up Chevner with the magic science blotting pad which Gan used on Jenna in <a href="/Dear-Charlotte/series-1/episode-4-time-squad/">Time Squad</a>. Then Vila teleports down to help them get into the centre<note>They never really explain what the centre <em>is</em>. Is it the headquarters of the mining operation? Is it a detention centre? After a while, they'd said the word <q cite="http://blakes7.wikia.com/wiki/Project_Avalon_(dialogue_transcript)">centre</q> so often, it'd lost all meaning for me.</note>, so they can rescue Avalon.</p>
		
		<h2>Death is <em>so boring</em></h2>
		<p>Servalan arrives, dressed like Cruella Deville and gives Travis grief for not catching Blake fast enough. She's brought with her a McGuffin in the form of a ball made out of pink <jargon type="TV"/> static. They test the McGuffin out by strapping the world's most indifferent man to a chair in a sealed room. They then convey the McGuffin inside on a slightly simplified version of <a href="https://youtu.be/KVdqwD_bcPs?t=1m11s">Pee Wee Herman's breakfast machine</a>, where it is broken like an egg. While the man looks bored, he's briefly given <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/comedy/lookaroundyou/programmes/health/gallery2.shtml">Cobbles</a>, then turned into a skelington, all without uttering a sound.</p>
		
		<ross>
			<p>The unnamed man's death is watched by Servalan, the <jargon type="YTS"/> Mutoid and Travis. Travis is the one one who expresses any emotion - a sort of excited astonishment. The other two watch the spectacle with all the emotion of a by-election.</p>
		</ross>
		
		<h2>Enter the hero</h2>
		<p>Then <q><a href="/Dear-Charlotte/series-1/episode-6-seek-locate-destroy/">Trundles</a></q> turns up! I love that guy. He's patrolling the tunnels around the mining complex where Vila is picking the lock.</p>

		<biog>
			<src>/Dear-Charlotte/img/characters/trundles.png</src>
			<info type="Name">Trundles</info>
			<info type="Job">Security robot</info>
			<info type="Dramatic role">Missed merchandising opportunity</info>
			<info type="Most embarrassing moment">That time he put in a <jargon type="USB"/> cable the wrong way up in front of that really shiny robot from accounts</info>
			<info type="Metal level">Ramstein</info>
		</biog>

		<h2>Please turn all phones to silent mode</h2>
		<p>Back on <em>The Liberator</em>, some Mark IV Federation Interceptors approach. Cally calls Blake, using the communicator, rather than THE POWER OF HER MIND, and in doing so, nearly alerts Trundles to their location. Blake doesn't answer (because he's hiding from Trundles) so Avon legs it away from <em>Sparkletown</em>, leaving Blake out of teleport range.</p>
		<p>Travis stops to examine a side arm of a guard. <q cite="http://blakes7.wikia.com/wiki/Project_Avalon_(dialogue_transcript)">Enjoying your new weapon from the armoury, I see</q>, he says. This is a PLOT POINT.</p>
		
		<h2><jargon type="RP"/> is good <jargon type="PR"/></h2>
		<p>Blake makes it through the door and into the detainment centre, then attracts a guard by pretending to be slightly posher and authoritative. When the guard approaches, they all pop out and point their guns up his face. So basically the same schtick Vila pulled in <a href="/Dear-Charlotte/series-1/episode-6-seek-locate-destroy/">Seek-Locate-Destroy</a>, but more in-character for Blake. Their new pet guard leads them to Avalon's cell.</p>
		<p><em>The Liberator</em> is out of range of the Interceptors, so turns about to return to <em>Sparkletown</em>.</p>
		
		<h2>Walking carpet</h2>
		<p>Blake does the old pretend-to-be-a-prisoner bit from <em>Star Wars</em><note>See also: <em>Blood Diamond</em>, weirdly</note>. They walk up to a group of other guards and there is some strangle-based fighting. One guard buggers off and raises the alarm.</p>
		<p>Blake finds Avalon's cell, while the others set up defencive positions. Vila picks the lock, while the guards attack. They do a fighting retreat to the tunnels. Avalon gets a bit shot, but it's the <q cite="http://www.urbandictionary.com/define.php?term=walk%20it%20off">walk it off</q> kind of shot.</p>
		
		<ross>
			<h2>Revenge of the Servalan</h2>
			<p>As the 2002 documentary <a href="https://youtu.be/LQn-iXhepyI?t=38m56s">Making <em>Blake's 7</em></a> suggests, the battle in the tight corridors of the centre was heavily influenced by the release of <em>Star Wars</em> in the <jargon type="UK"/>.</p>
			<p>Disposable guards pop round corners and are bloodlessly shot down, their faces covered and their deaths quick. It's made abundantly clear that Blake and his gang are murdering their way through quite a lot of them.</p>
		</ross>
		
		<h2>Urinary tract inferno</h2>
		<p>They reach the ice caves and as Trundles approaches, Blake asks for teleport. Trundles pops out his belly-pipe and wees fire all over them, just as they teleport away:</p>
		
		<blockquote class="imgur-embed-pub" lang="en" data-id="ihT0qoL"><a href="/Dear-Charlotte//imgur.com/ihT0qoL">Producing a stream of fiery wee-wee.</a></blockquote><script async="" src="//s.imgur.com/min/embed.js" charset="utf-8"></script>

		<p>Avalon seems fine, but asks for her tunic, because it's <q cite="http://blakes7.wikia.com/wiki/Project_Avalon_(dialogue_transcript)">very important</q>.</p>

		<h2>Shooting blanks</h2>
		<p>Blake is troubled by how easy it was to escape. Both he and Avalon were shot and both are fine. In examining a captured weapon, he discovers it was made to stun and not kill. Blake suspects the Federation wanted him to escape and that Travis' <em>real</em> goal is not the death of Blake, but to capture <em>The Liberator</em>. In order to do this, he needed to place someone or something on board. Avon assumes it's Chevner who has been planted. They go to the room where Avalon was being treated and discover Cally unconscious and Chevner and Avalon missing. Blake starts searching the ship.</p>
		
		<ross>
			<h2>If a stormtrooper falls in a forest and no one is around to hear it, does it make a sound?</h2>
			<p>The ease with which Imperial Stormtroopers are dispatched in the <em>Star Wars</em> films has inspired debate on the Internet since before the web existed. There's at least one page on <a href="http://tvtropes.org/pmwiki/pmwiki.php/Main/ImperialStormtrooperMarksmanshipAcademy">TV Tropes</a> which suggests a similar reason to such a non-fatal (at least for the protagonists) gunfight.</p>
			<p>But here Terry Nation underlines Travis' ruthless methodology: not only was he prepared to kill all of Blake's crew in order to deliver <em>The Liberator</em> to The Federation, he was willing to kill countless of his own guards in pursuit of that aim.</p>
			<p>Note that this is never stated by any character, nor is it underscored with music. As often with <em>Blake's 7</em>, the darkness is simply present in the world and taken for granted by everyone.</p>
		</ross>

		<p>Avalon wanders onto the bridge, where Gan is busy drinking a glass of water in the manner of an actor. She tells him Chevner attacked Cally, dragged her away, then sort of wandered off. Then she mentions her tunic again. She sure loves that tunic.</p>
		<p>Jenna is comforting Cally, when Chevner wanders in, all bloodied up, collapses and dies.</p>
		
		<h2>The pink egg of death</h2>
		<p>Gan brings Avalon into the teleport room, to find her tunic. He hands her it, and she removes a cylinder from a pocket, opens it, and takes out that pink ball of <jargon type="TV"/> static McGuffin. She's just about to stamp it open, when Gan figures out something's up, and tries to stop her. There's a frantic fight scene, where whenever Avalon exerts effort, there's a sort of whining noise, like when your remote control car you got from <a href="http://www.tandyonline.co.uk/">Tandy</a> is running out of batteries. Blake joins in, and Avalon is finally subdued.</p>
		<p>Zen explains what's inside the pink ball, while Avon pokes about in Avalon's ear. It turns out she's a robot<note>I think the nice pink circuits are because she's a <em>lady</em> robot.</note>, look:</p>
		
		<blockquote class="imgur-embed-pub" lang="en" data-id="GH66qLB"><a href="/Dear-Charlotte//imgur.com/GH66qLB">View post on imgur.com</a></blockquote><script async="" src="//s.imgur.com/min/embed.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
		
		<ross>

			<figure class="img-r">
				<img src="/Dear-Charlotte/img/series-1/episode-9-project-avalon/sarah-android.jpg" alt=""/>
				<figcaption>One more crack about Doctor Who and I'll wipe that smile off your face.</figcaption>
			</figure>
			
			<h2>#NoMakeup</h2>
			<p>Charlotte pointed me towards the Doctor Who episode <em>The Android Invasion</em>, originally broadcast over two years earlier. When the special effects department needed to show the inside of a lady-bot, they went to considerably more effort.</p>

		</ross>
		
		<char>
			<p>There was a robot Romana too.</p>
			<p>Also- that picture is from the Android Invasion, also written by Terry Nation. Sadly known for the crummy reveal where Guy Crayford takes off his eye patch to discover...his other eye. What like he never noticed? Did he sleep in that thing? Not your strongest Terry.</p>
		</char>
		
		<p>Blake wants Avon to reprogram the Avalon-bot for something, then returns to the <em>Sparkletown</em> so they can rescue the meat-and-bones Avalon. He teleports down and Travis threatens to shoot him, with his weird old lady ring, but Blake's got that pink ball of McGuffin, and Travis doesn't want to break it.</p>

		<figure class="img-r">
			<img src="/Dear-Charlotte/img/series-1/episode-9-project-avalon/hot-pink-pursuit-ships.jpg" alt=""/>
			<figcaption>This season's hot pink Pursuit ships</figcaption>
		</figure>

		<h2><q cite="http://www.chakoteya.net/DoctorWho/12-4.htm">To hold in my hand a capsule which contains such power</q></h2>
		<p>Servalan tells Travis to hand over meat-Avalon. Blake gives her a teleport bracelet, then put the McGuffin in the grip of Avalon-bot. He warns Travis that certain phrases and actions will trigger the Avalon-bot to crush the ball, but doesn't elaborate on what those words or actions <em>are</em>. Then he and Avalon teleport out, leaving Travis holding the baby.</p>
		<p>As Travis creeps toward Avalon-bot, she drops the ball, and Travis just manages to catch it, before it smashes on the floor.</p>
		<p>Servalan tells Travis that he's suspended, pending an investigation, then sends out three bright pink pursuit ships after Blake.</p>

		<h2>Watch <em>Project Avalon</em> on YouTube</h2>
		<youtube id="sdhDp4rmN_s"/>
	</content>
</page>