<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="/Dear-Charlotte/xslt/page.xslt"?>
<page>
	<meta>
		<description>An introduction to Doctor Who, part 7: Women in the fourth Doctor era</description>
		<path>/charlotte-responds/women-in-the-fourth-doctor-era/</path>
	</meta>
	<content type="main">
		<h1>Women in the fourth Doctor era</h1>

		<p>And on to my specialist subject...</p>

		<figure class="img-r">
			<img SRC="/Dear-Charlotte/img/charlotte-responds/katy-manning.jpg" alt=""/>
			<figcaption>Katy Manning</figcaption>
		</figure>

		<p>The Third Doctor, Jon Pertwee, was like a James Bond character only with a cape. He had lots of gadgets and cars, did venusian aikido and was a teeny bit patronising. They did give him one female companion who was a scientist, but no-one could understand what she was talking about, so they replaced her with Katy Manning, who just sort of blinked her big sixties eyes at him.</p>

		<p>Tom Baker is a big man. Seriously. He’s door sized. I’ve met him twice. It’s hard to imagine a man of his size being in any sort of serious peril. So in this era there are a lot more baddies who are defeated by intellect. Mad scientists, mad millionaires, mad computers. And there are some awesome lady villains too. Eldrad, before she turns into STEPHEN THORNE, is played by a stunningly tall, very sexy lady who somehow manages not to be sexualised. She tricks the Doctor’s arse into taking her back to her dead planet. Then there’s lady Adrasta with her psycho-grandma side-kick. And the goodies too, like the Thal Bettan in <em>Genesis</em>. She’s well-ard. Yeah, go the girls.</p>

		<figure>
			<img SRC="/Dear-Charlotte/img/charlotte-responds/tom-baker-fans.jpg" alt=""/>
			<figcaption>Tom Baker in Northern Ireland</figcaption>
		</figure>

		<p>Before new Who, specifically Paul McGann, there was no Doctor-snog. There were often 50/50 female / male characters. In <em>Brain of Morbius</em>, it’s virtually all women. Somehow when the Doctor recovers consciousness lying on the floor with his shirt slightly undone<note>Yes, I notice these things</note> surrounded by a circle of young red-heads, Tom Baker manages not to act as though he’s woken up in the middle of a space orgy. This is <jargon type="RADA"/> training people.</p>
		<p>Then there are the companions. Again, this is pre-McGann so there’s no funny business going on. Often the opening scenes are of peaceful domesticity in the <jargon type="TARDIS"/>, playing chess or perhaps re-decorating. They are best friends, nothing more<note>Ok, so let’s skim over Romana version 2, but it’s trickier when the two actors in question are at it like rabbits.</note>.</p>

		<h2>Sarah-Jane</h2>

		<figure class="img-r">
			<img SRC="/Dear-Charlotte/img/charlotte-responds/sarah-jane.jpg" alt=""/>
			<figcaption>Sarah-Jane</figcaption>
		</figure>

		<p>Liz Sladen was apparently picked for this role because she managed to look both scared and brave in the audition. Sarah has a proper job as a journalist and is often the one to stir up a revolution, give someone the sharp edge of her tongue or even rescue the Doctor for a change. She gets on much better with him once Harry has left and you can see there’s a lovely relationship of trust between them.</p>
		<p>As an aside, the fourth Doctor doesn’t ‘pick’ any of his companions. He’s very much a loner and they either stow away or are foisted on him. However, by the time Sarah leaves you can tell he is fond. There’s a touching leaving scene in <em>Hand of Fear</em> which almost makes up for STEPHEN THORNE. Had it been written by Gareth Roberts or Stephen Moffat, there would be some agonised eye-contact and stirringly soppy background music. Instead the Doctor does a weird shoulder shrug that indicates he’s feeling something a bit sticky, then dumps Sarah in Croydon and takes off. Doors slam. <jargon type="TARDIS"/> disappears.</p>
		<p>She finally gets her hug in School Reunion and it’s from David Tennant, so it’s not all bad.</p>

		<h2>Leela</h2>

		<figure class="img-r">
			<img SRC="/Dear-Charlotte/img/charlotte-responds/leela.jpg" alt=""/>
			<figcaption>Leela</figcaption>
		</figure>

		<p>Credit has to go to Louise Jameson. How do you play a character that has been clearly ‘written for the Dads’ and who spends most stories wearing a leopard skin leotard and make that character somehow three dimensional and empathetic? Leela does all the violent stuff the Doctor isn’t allowed to. She knifes people and does the throwy/wrestling thing. She actually kills people. There are a couple of crackly moments in their strange relationship (one very odd scene in <em>Fendahl</em> where he sort of lands on her) but again, no Doctor-snog. Despite her being nearly naked all the time. Sadly other than Chris Boucher and Robert Holmes few writers could cope with her character and instead of dying saving the Doctor’s life she chooses to stay on Gallifrey and marry a really rubbish weedy Time Lord. The Doctor slams the <jargon type="TARDIS"/> door in her face and leaves.</p>

		<h2>Romanas 1 and 2</h2>

		<figure class="img-r">
			<img SRC="/Dear-Charlotte/img/charlotte-responds/romana1.jpg" alt=""/>
			<figcaption>Romana (played by Mary Tamm)</figcaption>
		</figure>

		<p>Like Leela and Sarah, Romana isn’t chosen by the Doctor, but foisted on him by the White Guardian. Like the Doctor she’s a Time Lord and unlike the Doctor she’s stayed to do her Time Lord academy studies so she is really pretty darn smart. Smarter than he is. Mary Tamm, who is beautiful and super elegant, has a wonderful introduction scene where she actually patronises the Doctor for a change. It’s nice. But then, for all her academia, the Doctor is more well-travelled and wordly wise. In the end she ends up being locked up, tied up and rescued far too often, but at least she has a fabulous wardrobe.</p>
		<p>So Mary Tamm regenerates into Lalla Ward. Tom Baker is very happy about this.</p>

		<figure class="img-r">
			<img SRC="/Dear-Charlotte/img/charlotte-responds/romana2.jpg" alt=""/>
			<figcaption>Romana (played by Lalla Ward)</figcaption>
		</figure>

		<p>By this point the series has evolved from gothic horror into shiny sci fi and camp humour. Lalla Ward is very much a love/hate figure<note>Sorry, it’s not just because she married Tom Baker honest</note>. She delivers some wonderful lines with a smug brilliance that can make you want to punch her in the face, except she looks like a fluffy blonde school girl so you can’t. Actually, she dressed as a school girl once. Coincidentally in the story where the two actors got together. I say nothing.</p>
		<p>Lalla Ward also claims to have spent the entire wardrobe budget, meaning the 80s companions coming after her basically had one outfit each for the rest of the decade. Eventually Romana is called back to Gallifrey. The Doctor shows he is struggling with this by having a socially awkward moment in her bedroom where he pretends to read a book but doesn’t really. Then she decides instead to stay in E-Space so he throws K-9 at her, slams the <jargon type="TARDIS"/> door and leaves.</p>

		<h2>The others</h2>
		<p>Nyssa. Tegan. Adric.</p>

		<figure>
			<img SRC="/Dear-Charlotte/img/charlotte-responds/nyssa-tegan-adric.jpg" alt=""/>
			<figcaption>From left to right: Nyssa, more hair than Baker, Tegan, hair restrained by pressure valve, Adric the combo-breaker / Poundland Micky Dolenz.</figcaption>
		</figure>

		<p><em>Whatever</em>.</p>

	</content>
</page>