<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="/Dear-Charlotte/xslt/page.xslt"?>
<page>
	<meta>
		<description>Episode 6: Seek-Locate-Destroy. Blake and crew break into the Federation base on Centero, in order to steal a Cypher machine, partially destroying the plant, in order to cover up this fact. Cally is accidentally left behind. We meet Servalan who appoints Travis, a man Blake thought he had killed, to hunt down Blake. Travis uses Cally to set a trap for Blake, but Blake turns the tables and knocks his silly robot hand off, for good measure.</description>
		<path>/Dear-Charlotte/series-1/episode-6-seek-locate-destroy/</path>
		<type>episode</type>
	</meta>
	<content type="main">
		<h1>Episode 6: Seek-Locate-Destroy</h1>
		<p>In the last episode, new crew member Cally went a bit nutzoid and started messing with <em>The Liberator</em>, so it would go to The Planet of The Lost David Bowies. It was a <em>bit</em> like the film <a href="https://youtu.be/gJzPSPkWTrM?t=7s" title="The trailer for 'I'm not There'">I'm Not There</a>, but with David Bowie instead of Bob Dylan. And with added lettuce men, telepathy and puppets. No, this comparison is terrible. Let's move on.</p>
		<p>So in the last episode, <em>The Liberator</em> got trapped, and Blake was asked to choose between the lives of his crew, and the lives of some hilarious lettuce men. Blake instead chose to kill off a corporate entity (it's complicated) from a group of exiles from Cally's planet called <q>The Lost</q>. Who were also hilarious / disgusting. My point is this: Cally turns up, makes a nuisance of herself and has nothing to give the team, except a slightly superior bubble perm to Blake.</p>
		
		<h2>Hello! My name's Rags!</h2>
		<p><em>Seek-Locate-Destroy</em><note>An unusual title for Terry Nation. Those hyphens are his, and not a requirement of <jargon type="HTTP"/>.</note> starts with a peek at this <em>adorable</em> robot:</p>

		<blockquote class="imgur-embed-pub" lang="en" data-id="Lji7EVo"><a href="/Dear-Charlotte//imgur.com/Lji7EVo">An adorably inept surveillance robot on the planet Centero.</a></blockquote><script async="" src="//s.imgur.com/min/embed.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
		
		<p>Look at how rubbish he is! But he's <em>really trying hard</em>.</p>
		
		<char>
			<p>Invented by writers Bob Baker and Dave Martin (or, fictionally, Prof Marius), Doctor Who's most memorable trundling robot is of course K-9. He's cute. He's smart. He's handy with a lazer. He's rubbish over loose rubble, which isn't that useful when most of your planets look like Quarries.</p>
		</char>
		
		<p>Blake beams down to Centero and runs away from CrapBot, who pops out a flame-thrower and tries to light him up. Then just sort of gives up and trundles away, the poor wee love<note>Terry Nation, who wrote this episode and devised <em>Blake's 7</em>, also invented The Daleks. That man loved him a trundling robot.</note>.</p>
		<p>As it's quite safe, Vila  beams down with a picnic box full of thieving tools which matches his jacket. They come to a gate with <q cite="http://blakes7.wikia.com/wiki/Seek-Locate-Destroy_(dialogue_transcript)">TOP SECURITY</q> written on it, under which an average, <jargon type="RADA"/> trained man could easily squeeze<note>To give the episode some credit, Vila explains that there's all manner of sensors around the fence which could mess them up.</note>. Vila comically picks the lock.</p>
		
		<h2>You know, for kids!</h2>
		<p>Blake and Vila get past two guards with some schtick which wouldn't be out-of-place in a <em>Three Stooges</em> film. <em>This is not a complement</em>.</p>
		
		<ross>
		
			<p>Vila distracts the guards by speaking in a posh accent and telling them the truth (he's come to sabotage the plant). Blake then creeps up behind them, and knocks them out. This is problematic for several reasons:</p>
			<ol>
				<li>It's well established that Vila is a coward first, and a comedian second</li>
				<li>Federation guards are quite happy to slaughter unarmed civilians at the drop of a hat</li>
				<li>Vila appears to knock out one of the guards out from the front, with his lunch box. He's more of a <a href="/Dear-Charlotte/series-1/episode-3-cygnus-alpha/">stab-a-monk-in-the-back</a> kind of guy.</li>
				<li>Both guards are wearing helmets</li>
			</ol>
			<p>But whatever. Some comedy happens.</p>
		
		</ross>
		
		<p>Blake and Vila burst into a room, and hold up the guard and two technicians inside. This room contains their primary objective and now that they have an exact fix, Avon, Cally and Gan can teleport down. They all have matching outfits in themed colours. Avon is wearing grey and black, of course<note>Quentin Tarantino is well known as a lover of obscure film and <jargon type="TV"/>. It's not at all beyond credibility to assume that this episode <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Es1vJCVWBCw" title="The scene from Reservoir Dogs, where they argue over names.">directly influenced Reservoir Dogs</a>.</note>.</p>

		<ross>
			<p>When the other three arrive, we see the teleporting process from the perspective of those being teleported, something which <em>Star Trek</em> has never done (to the best of my knowledge).</p>
		</ross>
		
		<blockquote class="imgur-embed-pub" lang="en" data-id="5SCc3Wl"><a href="/Dear-Charlotte//imgur.com/5SCc3Wl">This is what it looks like to teleport.</a></blockquote><script async="" src="//s.imgur.com/min/embed.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
		
		<figure class="img-r">
			<img src="/Dear-Charlotte/img/series-1/episode-6-seek-locate-destroy/future-iphone.jpg" alt=""/>
			<figcaption>Seriously, the iPhone 6 will just fall out your hand like a bar of soap.</figcaption>
		</figure>
		
		<p>Jenna's quite pleased with herself, with her precise teleporting skills, and starts playing with her iPhone 5<note>She's using a stylus because she thinks <a href="https://youtu.be/4YY3MSaUqMg?t=3s">Steve Jobs was wrong</a>.</note>.</p>
		
		<h2>The enigma variations</h2>
		<p>Gan, Cally and Vila take the prisoners away, while Avon pokes about with the console in the room. He finds what they're after: a Federation Cypher machine, and starts removing it.</p>
		<p>Cally and Gan take the prisoners to another room. Cally keeps them at gunpoint, while Gan sets explosive charges at a nice comfortable height, on an otherwise featureless wall<note>I suppose they do look a bit like fire alarms. Perhaps no-one will notice them.</note>. Blake's plan is that the Federation won't know the Cypher machine is missing, because so much of the area will be destroyed, and as a result, won't change their codes<note>This is a very Bletchley Park view of cryptography, which is fair enough, I suppose. The first book about Bletchley Park's role in the second world war was published in 1974, four years before this episode aired.</note>.</p>
		<p>One of the guards Vila and Blake knocked out outside wakes up and sets off the alarm.</p>
		
		<h2>Earn as you gurn</h2>
		<p>Avon can't get the Cypher machine out of the console, so Gan uses his superhuman strength and powerful gurning to remove the unit. It's nice that he has something to do.</p>
		
		<h2>Mini-boss</h2>

		<figure class="img-r">
			<img src="/Dear-Charlotte/img/series-1/episode-6-seek-locate-destroy/moustache.jpg" alt=""/>
			<figcaption>The balaclava. Truly, the most intimidating of garments.</figcaption>
		</figure>
		
		<p>The guards start to rush the console room, so Vila, Blake, Avon and Gan barricade themselves in. Meanwhile, Cally is overpowered by her prisoners and rendered unconscious<note>There's a lot of unconsciousness in this episode</note>. The technicians leave behind single guard to watch over her. He removes his gas mask to reveal a <em>luxurious, blond moustache</em><note>On the strength of the moustache alone, I assumed this character would recur. Alas, he doesn't. Perhaps I should write fan-fiction about him.</note>. Cally wakes up and has a punch-up with him, which she wins. Unfortunately, she's lost her bracelet in the fight, so she misses the teleport. All of Gan's explosives go off, and we see her lying next to her bracelet.</p>
		<p>Back on <em>The Liberator</em>, no-one notices that Cally is missing. Centero launches missiles at <em>The Liberator</em>, so Blake legs it away. Only then do they realise that Cally's missing, and of course, Avon and Vila suggest they should just leave her behind. Everyone tries to convince themselves that she's dead.</p>
		
		<ross>
			<p>The first half of this episode is a barn-storming heist, which also sets up the ending. But the <em>real</em> purpose of this episode is to set up two characters who are to recur for a long time: <a href="/Dear-Charlotte/about-blakes-7/servalan/">Servalan</a> and <a href="/Dear-Charlotte/about-blakes-7/travis/">Travis</a>.</p>
		</ross>
		
		<h2>TPS report</h2>
		<p>On Servalan's command centre, <a href="/Dear-Charlotte/about-blakes-7/servalan/">Supreme Commander Servalan</a> is being told about the impact Blake is having throughout the galaxy<note>Servalan has a <a href="http://www.longhi.it/sito/pag.php?pag=5&amp;idMenu=1&amp;l=2">white <q>Elda</q> armchair, designed by Joe Colombo</a>. This is not important to the plot, it's just that I'm massively jello.</note>. His acts have become a rallying cry and ordinary people seem to be massing behind him. The president wants to know how Servalan plans to capture Blake. Servalan plans to put Travis in charge of this task, with the instructions to <q cite="http://blakes7.wikia.com/wiki/Seek-Locate-Destroy_(dialogue_transcript)">seek, locate and destroy</q> Blake. Travis is supposed to be on trial for the massacre of civilians.</p>
		<p>Ray, one of Servalan's officers, brings her some <q cite="http://blakes7.wikia.com/wiki/Seek-Locate-Destroy_(dialogue_transcript)">micro tapes</q> and expresses concerns about Travis' appointment.</p>
		
		<ross>
			<p>The scene between Servalan and Ray is interesting. Servalan had been respectful during her meeting with the Presidential aides but her scene with Ray shows the lengths she goes to, in order to manipulate those around her.</p>
			<p>She wants Ray to agree with the appointment of Travis, but he is set against this plan, for moral reasons. In her attempt to persuade him, she moves from friendliness, then flirtatiousness, then moves behind her desk for her final play: simple authority. Throughout the encounter, Ray is unwavering and seemingly unaffected by her behaviour.</p>
		</ross>
		
		<p>Travis arrives, and receives his orders to destroy Blake.</p>
		<p>Avon gets the Cypher machine working, and hooks it into Zen. They intercept a signal saying Space Commander Travis is coming to Centero. Blake's surprised, because he thought he'd killed him.</p>
		<p>Back on Centero, Travis starts to investigate the explosion. He quickly sees that there was more to the assault than simple destruction, but he's not sure what he's missing yet.</p>

		<ross>
			<p>This isn't important, but Travis talks to this guy, Prell, who has the worst mobile phone <em>ever</em>:</p>
		</ross>
		
		<blockquote class="imgur-embed-pub" lang="en" data-id="FzgeYYb"><a href="/Dear-Charlotte//imgur.com/FzgeYYb">Prell refuses to update.</a></blockquote><script async="" src="//s.imgur.com/min/embed.js" charset="utf-8"></script>

		<ross>
			<p>Seriously, dude, change your contract.</p>
		</ross>

		<p>The guards find Cally in the wreckage. She's alive, but still unconscious. Travis takes her to the space station.</p>
		
		<figure class="img-r">
			<img src="/Dear-Charlotte/img/series-1/episode-6-seek-locate-destroy/travis.jpg" alt=""/>
			<figcaption>Travis proving that there's nothing as permanent as a temporary repair.</figcaption>
		</figure>
		
		<h2>To catch a thief</h2>
		<p>Travis is going over all of the information the Federation has on Blake<note>This seems to consist of a series of black and white photographs of Blake either being tortured, or in the throws of sexual ecstasy.</note>. He tells Servalan that he needs the fastest possible ships, if he's to have a chance to catch <em>The Liberator</em>. Servalan promises them to him, along with a crew of <q cite="http://blakes7.wikia.com/wiki/Seek-Locate-Destroy_(dialogue_transcript)">Mutoids</q>. We learn that Travis is a cyborg, with a robot hand with a <q cite="http://blakes7.wikia.com/wiki/Seek-Locate-Destroy_(dialogue_transcript)">laseron destroyer</q><note>One of the upgrades seem to consist of a ring with an enormous rock on it, of the sort one might see on the finger of an elderly dowager.</note>. He lost his original hand and about a quarter of his face to Blake, at their first meeting, and refused to get the original repair updated as it made him <q cite="http://blakes7.wikia.com/wiki/Seek-Locate-Destroy_(dialogue_transcript)">memorable</q>.</p>
		
		<h2>Old friends</h2>
		<p>Travis tells Servalan the story of how he first met Blake, and half way through, we cut to Blake telling the same story to his crew. Blake had planned to break out some prisoners who were to have their memories erased and Travis had lain in wait for him. Blake tried to surrender peacefully, but Travis was intent to slaughter Blake and his freedom fighters. Blake grabbed a gun and shot Travis, assuming he was mortally wounded. We learn that Blake's original memories started to come back after the second massacre (see <a href="http://127.0.0.1/series-1/episode-1-the-way-back/">The Way Back</a>).</p>
		<p>Cally is taken back down to Centero and perhaps tortured (it's difficult to tell). Then we get to meet Prell again<note>That guy who uses his mobile phone in a weird way.</note>. Look, he's not a major character, but let's give him one of these:</p>
		
		<biog>
			<src>/Dear-Charlotte/img/characters/prell.png</src>
			<info type="Name">Prell</info>
			<info type="Job">White-suited goon</info>
			<info type="Dramatic role">Cypher-machine-epiphany-haver</info>
			<info type="Android or iOS">Zune</info>
			<info type="Dislikes">When people are rude about <q>Trundles</q> the robot</info>
		</biog>
		
		<ross>
			<p>Peter Craze, who plays Prell, made <a href="https://youtu.be/aDG11TJO4kc?t=1m10s" title="Prell's the gonk in the hat on the right">a brief appearance in the Doctor Who story <em>Nightmare of Eden</em></a>, about which I know absolutely nothing. To the Charlottemobile!</p>
		</ross>
		
		<char>
			<p><em>Nightmare of Eden</em> is another classic from the later part of the Fourth Doctor's reign. At this point the show was very heavy on both humour and techno-babble <jargon type="sci-fi"/> concepts. Also big on shiny costumes. Interestingly <em>Nightmare</em> also has the underlying theme of drug smuggling. Yes that's right, DRUGS. Serious issues. Because Doctor Who is hard core adult entertainment and not, as some might suggest, a children's show. (The monsters are a bit too cuddly to be scary anyway.)</p>
		</char>

		<p>Prell discovers that the Cypher machine is missing. Travis realises that if Blake has access to the Cypher machine, he may be intercepting all Federation communications. So he sends out a message saying that Cally is alive and on Centero, in order to lure Blake into a trap. Travis wants Blake to be in the room with him and Cally before the guards surround them.</p>
		
		<ross>
			<p>The whole sub-plot with the Federation investigating the explosion is interesting. There's no moustache-twirling baddies, just professionals investigating a crime. You get a sense of these people as individuals, rather than mooks.</p>
		</ross>
		
		<p>Travis struts about for a bit then returns to the room where Cally is being held, but finds her chair empty - Blake had teleported down earlier having learnt this trick the last time he encountered Travis. Blake put him in the torture chair, but they don't know about his weaponised hand. Cally spots him fiddling with it, and warns Blake, who dives out of the way of the blast. Blake knocks Travis' silly robot hand off.</p>
		
		<h2>Cally come home</h2>
		<p><em>The Liberator</em> is out of teleport range, but coming in fast. The guards, alerted by the sound of Travis' shots, rush the room, but are too late.</p>
		<p>Gan plots a course to get them away from Centero and Cally thanks Blake. Travis does a daft wee speech, where he claims to be Blake's death.</p>
		
		<ross>
			<p>This episode is much less unitentionally funny than <em>The Web</em>. Nothing spoils drama more than a rubber suit, it would seem. Travis is established quite well: the coldness, intelligence and logic is in place from the start. But Servalan gets to be much more manupulative later on. She seems almost eager to please, in this episode.</p>
			<p>Terry Nation's original plan was for Servalan to make a single appearance. Perhaps as her role expanded, Nation made changes to her character. Or Jacqueline Pearce brought more to the role, in further episodes.</p>
		</ross>
		
		<h2>Watch <em>Seek-Locate-Destroy</em> on YouTube</h2>
		<youtube id="-6ZiOXPNjg4"/>
	</content>
</page>