<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="/xslt/page.xslt"?>
<page>
	<meta>
		<description>Episode 1: The Way Back. Roj Blake has had his mind rubbed out, so he's forgotten that he's a resistance leader. There's a bit of a massacre of his resistance buddies and he gets arrested on fake charges and sent to a prison planet.</description>
		<path>/series-1/episode-1-the-way-back/</path>
		<type>episode</type>
	</meta>
	<content type="main">
		<h1>Episode 1: The Way Back</h1>
		<p>The episode opens with a shot of a surveillance camera. This was after 1984, but before 1984, if you know what I mean. Then we get our first look at Blake. He does this:</p>

		<blockquote class="imgur-embed-pub" lang="en" data-id="dd2mXy0"><a href="//imgur.com/dd2mXy0">View post on imgur.com</a></blockquote><script async="" src="//s.imgur.com/min/embed.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
		
		<figure class="img-r">
			<img src="/img/series-1/episode-1-the-way-back/tom-baker.jpg" alt=""/>
			<figcaption>Tom Baker has crazy hair, is what I'm saying.</figcaption>
		</figure>
		<p>I mean, where do we start? The hand on hips? The beige? The <em>hair</em>? But of course Charlotte, you're used to much wilder hair than that.</p>
		<p>Given Baker's excesses in the late seventies, Gareth Thomas' barnet is modest. If Blake's hair is a sun, the fourth Doctor's hair is a supernova. But the quality of <em>Blake's 7</em> won't be decided upon by hair alone.</p>
		
		<char>
			<figure class="img-r">
				<img src="/img/charlotte-responds/driscoll.jpg" alt=""/>
				<figcaption>Driscoll from <em>Hand of Fear</em></figcaption>
			</figure>

			<p>Ok it’s a fair cop. Tom Baker’s hair is nuts. Even for the 70s. Other characters appear during his reign with decent enough man-bouffants (Driscoll in <em>Hand of Fear</em> for one) but no-one can quite compete.</p>
		</char>

		<p>So Blake is in a FutureCity<sup>&#8482;</sup><note>Which is quite nicely done, to be honest. Shades of Cloud City from <em>The Empire Strikes Back</em> and the unnamed city from <em>THX-1138</em>.</note> and he meets a friend (Ravella), who tricks him to attend an illegal meeting outside the city, by telling him he'll learn something about his family.</p>
		<p>To be fair to Ravella, he does learn something about his family. They're all <em>dead</em>.</p>
		
		<h2>Stitch and bitch</h2>
		<p>Once there, he learns that he used to be a resistance leader who was caught, and whose memory was erased. He's told all this by the pillock:</p>
		<biog>
			<src>/img/characters/bran-foster.png</src>
			<info type="Name">Bran Foster</info>
			<info type="Job">Resistance leader</info>
			<info type="Dramatic role">Ghost from the past</info>
			<info type="Hobbies">Quilting, amateur tailoring</info>
			<info type="Hair quality">Luxurious</info>
		</biog>
		<p>Him and Blake used to be <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=GjOEcoMy2fI" title="Matt Berry says 'buddies' in an amusing way, on 'Garth Marenghi's Darkplace'">buddies</a> before Blake got his brain Internet history wiped.</p>
		<p>Before he can fully take this in, The Terran Federation attacks, and every character we've been introduced to up until this point is killed. Apart from Dev Tarrant<note>He's the bad guy, but don't get too attached to him. He never turns up again.</note>.</p>
		
		<h2>The paedo libido</h2>
		<p>Blake gets arrested and is framed as a paedophile by the Federation. This is where the episode takes a bit of a left turn. Blake is assigned a defence lawyer, Tel Varon, and is quickly found guilty. He doesn't take this too well:<note>In Blake's defence, moments before this, a guard jabs a drugs needle into his shoulder</note></p>
		<blockquote class="imgur-embed-pub" lang="en" data-id="fueB67X"><a href="//imgur.com/fueB67X">Blake suffers from a tiny bit of drugs injected into his arm from a guard.</a></blockquote><script async="" src="//s.imgur.com/min/embed.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
		<p>Blake meets <em>proper recurring characters</em>: <a href="/about-blakes-7/vila-restal/">Vila</a> and <a href="/about-blakes-7/jenna-stannis/">Jenna</a>. They are all interned in a holding cell, before being taken to Cygnus Alpha, an off-world penal colony.</p>
		
		<p>The episode shifts focus to Tel, who investigates Blake's claims of the massacre. He finds the bodies and takes <q>picture tapes</q> of them, with this load of old nonsense:</p>
		<figure>
			<img src="/img/series-1/episode-1-the-way-back/picture-tapes.jpg" alt=""/>
			<figcaption>Much like the blasters, the future video camera needs to be attached to a power pack with a huge curly cable. Note also Tel's unconventional camera technique.</figcaption>
		</figure>
		<p>Unfortunately, the conspiracy against Blake moves against Tel and murders him and his wife, allowing Blake's transportation to Cygnus Alpha, the <em>London</em><note>Here's a fun fact. Ready? The short-lived comedy sci-fi show <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hyperdrive_(TV_series)">Hyperdrive</a> used place names of the <jargon type="UK"/> as spaceship names too, but it was done for comedy reasons. For example the  <em><jargon type="HMS"/> Camden Lock</em>.</note>, to take off.</p>
		<ross>
			<p>Oh, hello! What's going on here? Glad you asked. I'll be using these boxes to talk about the episode, rather than describing what goes on. Onward!</p>
			<h2>What the hell even <em>is</em> this show?</h2>
			<p><em>The Way Back</em> must have been very confusing for viewers when they first saw it. The pace of the episode is very slow by today's standards and keeps the audience guessing as to what kind of show <em>Blake's 7</em> is going to be. It moves from <em>THX-1138</em> through <em>1984</em> before ending up in a legal drama with a tragic consequence. Hardly any of the characters introduced in this episode will ever be seen again. Indeed, ordinary civilian life under the Terran Federation is barely shown in the series again, from this point onward.</p>
			<p>I <em>like</em> its weird, slow pace, though.</p>
		</ross>
		
		<h2>Watch <em>The Way Back</em> on YouTube</h2>
		<youtube id="DXDd1zO9F1I"/>
		
	</content>
</page>