<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="/xslt/page.xslt"?>
<page>
	<meta>
		<description>Episode 7: Mission to Destiny. The Liberator finds a striken ship circling in space and finds the crew unconscious. They recover and Avon and Cally investigate the murders of various crew members while Blake races to the Destiny, the ship's home planet, with a device which may save their people. Avon and Cally uncover the murderer and Blake discovers that the device isn't on The Liberator after all, so he returns just in time to save the crew from the murderous buyers of the device.</description>
		<path>/series-1/episode-7-mission-to-destiny/</path>
		<type>episode</type>
	</meta>
	<content type="main">
		<h1>Episode 7: Mission to Destiny</h1>
		<p>In the last episode, Blake and his gang stole a cypher machine, exploded a Federation base and we met Servalan and Travis. But that has no bearing on <em>this</em> episode whatsoever.</p>

		<figure class="img-r">
			<img src="/img/series-1/episode-7-mission-to-destiny/glaxy-class-cruiser-ortega.jpg" alt=""/>
			<figcaption><em>This</em> is what I signed up for: <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scratch_building">scratch-built</a> spaceship models.</figcaption>
		</figure>

		<p>The episode starts with a rostrum spaceship shot, but the model is <em>tight</em>. The pilot makes a log entry, complains about feeling a bit sleepy, then gets murdered by a hammer. <em>Bosh!</em></p>
		<p>On <em>The Liberator</em> Jenna's spots an old Galaxy class cruiser on the scanners, circling endlessly. She shows Blake and tells him she thinks the ship's in trouble, so he agrees to investigate.</p>

		<ross>
			<p>It's not much, but I like the fact that Jenna has both skills and a role to play on <em>The Liberator</em>. Despite having a hair colour in common with <a href="http://www.imdb.com/video/screenplay/vi2625634841" title="The bit in Galaxy Quest where Sigourney Weaver says 'Look, I have one job on this lousy ship. It's stupid, but I'm going to do it. OK?'">Sigourney Weaver's character in <em>Galaxy Quest</em></a>, Jenna is not the target of that pastiche.</p>
		</ross>

		<h2>Mostly ghostly</h2>
		<p>Blake, Avon and Cally teleport across to the ghost ship. Blake smells a sickly sweet smell which is NOT AT ALL OMINOUS. They split up to search the ship. Because you would, wouldn't you?</p>
		<p>Cally and Blake find two people - Sara and Mandrian who appear to be in a coma. Blake tries some shaking-based medical treatments, but they don't work. Then he starts feeling a bit woozy. He realises that the smell is sono vapour - a tranquilising gas. He shuts off the ventilators, and he and Cally start to feel better. Blake tells Cally to watch over the crew members, and wanders off.</p>

		<ross>
			<p>There's a <em>lot</em> of plot in this episode, I'm afraid. It's light on the sort of nonsense which went on in <a href="/series-1/episode-5-the-web/">The Web</a> and there's a <em>lot</em> of characters, so I'm going to do a lot of this sort of thing:</p>
		</ross>

		<biog>
			<src>/img/characters/sara.png</src>
			<info type="Name">Sara</info>
			<info type="Job">Hyperventilation</info>
			<info type="Dramatic role">Timid lady character</info>
			<info type="Partner">Nanjew Mandrian</info>
			<info type="Jumpsuit">Dark grey, with a bottle green polo neck</info>
			<info type="Celebrity look-a-like">Stevie Nicks</info>
		</biog>

		<biog>
			<src>/img/characters/mandrian.png</src>
			<info type="Name">Nanjew Mandrian</info>
			<info type="Job">Emergency Brillo pad</info>
			<info type="Dramatic role">Second most suspicious character</info>
			<info type="Partner">Sara</info>
			<info type="Jumpsuit">Artichoke green, with a bottle green polo neck</info>
			<info type="Celebrity look-a-like">A more polite version of Bob Ross (he has a smaller beard and afro), so <em>Robert</em> Ross then.</info>
		</biog>

		<h2>Weekend at Bernie's</h2>
		<p>Cally gets bored baby-sitting the unconscious, so goes wandering about on her own. A door opens all by itself, so Cally draws a weapon and approaches slowly, but it's just the dead pilot we saw in the opening sequence. He falls to the floor, because that's the sort of thing which happens in a drama like this: dead bodies get propped up in cupboards, and fall out for dramatic effect.</p>

		<ross>
			<p>It's worth mentioning the music score at this point. For sequences on the stricken ship, it's composed primarily of acoustic instruments - piano, cello etc. Early synthesisers are still used to underscore scenes on <em>The Liberator</em>. This is a deliberate choice.</p>
			<p><em>Mission to Destiny</em> is another episode with a serious tone, but with a playful undercurrent: initially, the episode is in the style of a ghost story, but gradually the genre changes to that of a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Whodunit">whodunit</a>, such as <em>An Inspector Calls</em>.</p>
		</ross>

		<h2>Handwriting recognition</h2>
		<p>Avon and Blake get to the filters and find a tank of sono vapour. Cally finds another one in the the smashed-up flight deck. She also finds the number <q>54124</q> WRITTEN IN BLOOD on the world's thickest tablet device. Then Sara walks past and starts screaming at the corpse. Blake starts questioning the crew.</p>

		<ross>
			<p>When Blake askes Sara where she was, she says <q>Nanjew and I were together</q>, but <a href="http://blakes7.wikia.com/wiki/Mission_To_Destiny">the Blake's 7 Wiki</a> lists this character's name as <q cite="http://blakes7.wikia.com/wiki/Mission_To_Destiny">Mandrian</q>. I think <q>Nanjew</q> is such a <jargon type="sci-fi"/> sounding name, I've decided it's his Christian name.</p>
		</ross>

		<p>We meet the Captain:</p>

		<biog>
			<src>/img/characters/kendall.png</src>
			<info type="Name">Dr Kendall</info>
			<info type="Job">Captain, moral compass</info>
			<info type="Dramatic role">Sympathetic character</info>
			<info type="Jumpsuit">Kobicha (brown), with a bottle green polo neck</info>
			<info type="Celebrity look-a-like">Ed Harris or Jean-Marc Barr</info>
		</biog>

		<p>The crew are all a bit edgy. One crew member, Dortman, is still unaccounted for. The rest of the crew reluctantly introduce themselves.</p>

		<h2>Circular logic</h2>
		<p>Avon starts investigating the damage to the flight deck. It was done in such a way so that the ship would be stuck in a circular flight pattern. Sara and Mandrian show Dr. Kendall that one of the <q>life rockets</q> has been launched.</p>

		<h2>Humongous fungus among us</h2>
		<p>Dr. Kendall checks on the energy refractor (also confusingly called the neutrotope), which he assumed had been stolen by Dortmunn, when he ejected in the life rocket. Turns out this McGuffin is needed to save all plant life on his home planet, <em>Destiny</em><note>Oh, <em>that's</em> what the episode title means.</note> from some fungus or other. And it's like <em>super</em> expensive and worth loads of credits.</p>

		<char>
			<p>Some of my favourite Mcguffins in DW of this era include the multi-quatiscope, the dimensional stabiliser, the etheric beam locator, the murgin nut, the gravitic anomaliser and of course the sonic screwdriver.</p>
		</char>

		<p>Avon says that because of the damage, the ship will take five months to get home, which is too late to destroy the fungus, before the next growing season. Blake offers to deliver the neutrotope himself and leave Avon and Cally to fix the ship. <em>The Liberator</em> could complete this journey in four days. The crew reckon this sounds well dodge, and have a vote, which Blake wins.</p>

		<ross>
			<p>Blake never suggests taking any other crew members with him to deliver the energy refractor. When the crew of <em>The Ortega</em> object, he simply restates his offer to deliver it himself.</p>
		</ross>

		<p>Blake takes the suitcase with the neutrotope in it and teleports back to <em>The Liberator</em>.</p>

		<ross>
			<h2>What's the difference between a teleporter and a replicator?</h2>
			<p>So, depending upon who you believe, a teleporter is similar to a replicator: both break down an object to a bunch of atoms, then reconstruct it. The detail of where the atoms come from is crucial, however. If the original object is broken down at one end, then different atoms are used at the other end to reassemble it, then you've basically got yourself a photocopier, which burns your original document for you. But if you somehow send a stream of atoms to the target location, then Blake transporting with the neutrotope means his atoms, and the extremely rare minerals which the neutrotope consists of, are sent from <em>The Ortega</em> to <em>The Liberator</em>.</p>
			<p>As you can no doubt imagine, cleverer people than me have given this matter <a href="http://scifi.stackexchange.com/questions/8718/what-is-the-difference-between-the-transporter-and-the-replicator">considerable thought</a>. But as a child, I always assumed <em>Blake's 7</em> took the <q>stream of atoms</q> approach. The existential horror of my original self being destroyed didn't occur to me until later.</p>
		</ross>

		<p>On the flight deck of <em>The Ortega</em>, Cally is still trying to work out what <q>54124</q> means. She notices that the air is stale and Levett:</p>

		<biog>
			<src>/img/characters/levett.png</src>
			<info type="Name">Levett</info>
			<info type="Job">Ship's cynic</info>
			<info type="Dramatic role">Belittling Sonheim, getting on with stuff</info>
			<info type="Jumpsuit">Wine red with a bottle green polo neck</info>
			<info type="Celebrity look-a-like">Cate Blanchett</info>
		</biog>

		<p>...  tells her the ventilator is closed. Cally goes down to the storage hold for some bits and bobs to fix the flight deck. On the way there, she sports Mandrian dicking about with something in Sara's bedroom, then hiding it under her mattress. Once he's left, Cally sneaks in and pockets the device because why not?</p>
		<p>She asks Sonheim:</p>

		<biog>
			<src>/img/characters/sonheim.png</src>
			<info type="Name">Sonheim</info>
			<info type="Job">Sex pest</info>
			<info type="Dramatic role">Main suspect</info>
			<info type="Jumpsuit">Wine red with a bottle green polo neck</info>
			<info type="Celebrity look-a-like">Gary Moore</info>
			<info type="Creep level">8</info>
			<info type="Rudeness">7</info>
		</biog>

		<p>... where the storage hold is, and he's kind of a dick about it. Pascal:</p>

		<biog>
			<src>/img/characters/pascal.png</src>
			<info type="Name">Pascal</info>
			<info type="Job">Meat in the room</info>
			<info type="Dramatic role">Man in background</info>
			<info type="Jumpsuit">Beige with a bottle green polo neck</info>
			<info type="Celebrity look-a-like">Jeremy Hardy</info>
			<info type="Trivia">Pascal is played by John Leeson, who was the voice of K9 from some show I forget the name of right now. No, wait: <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=rlFQmaLghsk" title="K9 and Company theme music">I just remembered</a>.</info>
		</biog>

		<p>... tells her and as soon as she's gone, Sonheim gets up to follow her. JUST LIKE A MURDERER WOULD. Cally arrives at the storage hold and finds the lights are bust. She pokes about a bit, then this goes down:</p>

		<blockquote class="imgur-embed-pub" lang="en" data-id="HwB0xME"><a href="//imgur.com/HwB0xME">Then Sonheim pretends to strangle her, but is like &quot;jk!&quot;</a></blockquote><script async="" src="//s.imgur.com/min/embed.js" charset="utf-8"></script>

		<ross>
			<h2>Sonheim's top tips on bereavement counselling:</h2>
			<ul>
				<li>If you're not the first person to discover the corpse, be mindful of the feelings of others. They might be a bit <q>on edge</q>, so try not to scare them with any sudden noises. To be on the safe side, try and walk up behind them as silently as possible.</li>
				<li>Be aware that someone who has just discovered a corpse will be upset, and will need reassurance. Try gently resting your hands on their neck, to make them feel relaxed.</li>
				<li>If they react badly to this, try glumly looking at the floor like a robot. It's certain to comfort them.</li>
			</ul>
		</ross>

		<h2><jargon type="FAQ"/>s</h2>
		<p>Avon gets everyone together in the drawing room. Cally suggests that the death of the pilot Raffett was an accident: because he had shut off his vent, he wasn't exposed to the sono vapour. When the murderer found him awake, they had no choice but to kill him upside the head.</p>
		<p>Avon suggests that the killer's original plan was to shove Dortmunn's corpse in the life rocket and send it out to space, framing him for the theft. But because Blake was capering about the ship, this proved impossible.</p>
		<p>Grovane:</p>

		<biog>
			<src>/img/characters/grovane.png</src>
			<info type="Name">Grovane</info>
			<info type="Job">Secret weekend wizard</info>
			<info type="Dramatic role">Nerd, wrong-hypothesis-haver</info>
			<info type="Jumpsuit">Wine red with a bottle green polo neck</info>
			<info type="Celebrity look-a-like"><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=WPa4BJ6Kuls" title="Ben Moor has played nerd characters before, but this isn't a video of that. I quite like it, though.">Ben Moor</a></info>
		</biog>


		<p>... suggests that there might be a stow-away who did the murder. Avon dismisses this as nonsense, but lets the crew search the ship anyway.</p>

		<h2>We're going on a bear hunt</h2>
		<p>On board <em>The Liberator</em>, Zen informs them about a meteorite storm in their path. It would take them four times as long to go around the storm, but Zen doesn't know if <em>The Liberator</em>'s force wall will be strong enough to survive going through the middle.</p>

		<ross>
			<p>From a hard-<jargon type="sci-fi"/> perspective, this is nonsense. For example a rock only <em>becomes</em> a meteorite once it's survived it's passage through the atmosphere. When it's in the atmosphere, it's a meteor and before that point, it's a meteoroid. However, this story isn't really trying to be hard <jargon type="sci-fi"/>. A balance needs to be struck between world building, science and telling a good story.</p>
			<p>But all this is the B-plot. Ignore it.</p>
		</ross>

		<p>Cally meets Sonheim and Sara in a corridor. She asks Sonheim why he followed her into the storage hold. He tells her some BS about how he wanted to apologise, but because she's an attractive lady, he wanted to do it ... <em>with his diiiiiick</em>. She suggests that it's because he didn't want her to find the corpse, and he vehemently denies it.</p>
		<p>Levett tells Avon and Cally that Mandrian is dead. Sonheim is being held as a suspect by the rest of the crew. Sonheim denies it.</p>

		<p>Meanwhile, on board <em>The Liberator</em> Gan watches his wicked new screensaver:</p>

		<blockquote class="imgur-embed-pub" lang="en" data-id="b2GD0pg"><a href="//imgur.com/b2GD0pg">Gan watches the main view screen of The Liberator for rubble.</a></blockquote><script async="" src="//s.imgur.com/min/embed.js" charset="utf-8"></script>

		<h2>You have 2% battery remaining</h2>
		<p>They have just over a minute of power left. Blake needs to decide if he shuts down the main drive or the force wall. He chooses to shut down the force wall and run his way out of the storm, rather than turn off the main drive and drift his way out<note>To be fair to Nation, he did think of this, and had Jenna say some line about the <q>field drag effect</q>.</note>. Jenna does some fancy flying and the neutrotope falls off the coffee table in all the excitement.</p>
		<p>Avon doesn't think Sonheim killed Mandrian because the sabotage to the filtration room would require tools which weren't found on him or in the room. He then explains that the number <q>54124</q> was just very messy handwriting for <q>Sara</q>. The lengthy explanation gives Sara enough time to arm herself and hold them all at gunpoint. She pegs it and barricades herself inside the flight deck.</p>

		<h2>You have been outbid</h2>
		<p>Cally works out that the object she filtched was a homing beam transmitter and the neutrotope buyer must be on their way. Avon assumes that they will destroy the ship and everyone on it, when they arrive.</p>
		<p>On <em>The Liberator</em>, Blake checks on the neutrotope and discovers it's missing. He realises it was never in the case and returns to <em>The Ortega</em>. As they approach, a third ship appears on their scan. Blake guesses it's the buyers.</p>
		<p>Sara smiles as she hears blaster fire outside the flight deck:</p>

		<blockquote class="imgur-embed-pub" lang="en" data-id="2YiYZGD"><a href="//imgur.com/2YiYZGD">The unique blasters from The Ortega.</a></blockquote><script async="" src="//s.imgur.com/min/embed.js" charset="utf-8"></script>

		<p>She assumes it's the buyers for the neutrotope, but it's Avon's crafty trap. She leaves the flight deck and has a punch up with Avon, which he wins.</p>

		<h2>Holmes sweet Holmes</h2>
		<p>Blake teleports onto <em>The Ortega</em> with bracelets for everyone, but needs to get out before the other ship arrives. At the last moment, Sara throws her bracelet across the room, and everyone else teleports back to <em>The Liberator</em>. <em>The Ortega</em> and the other ship explode because Blake rigged a charge on the entry hatch. There are no cool special effect shots, unfortunately.</p>

		<ross>
			<p>So while it's a great pleasure to see Paul Darrow (Avon) strutting about the place and doing his best Holmes, it's worth noting that Cally does at least as much investigating as Avon does. I know I keep harping on about this, but the depressing fact is that in this respect, <em>Blake's 7</em> is <em>still</em> progressive.</p>
		</ross>

		<h2>Watch <em>Mission to Destiny</em> on YouTube</h2>
		<youtube id="XkuFLugf85o"/>
	</content>
</page>
