<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="/Dear-Charlotte/xslt/page.xslt"?>
<page>
	<meta>
		<description>Quick character summary of Ensor Senior</description>
		<path>/about-blakes-7/ensor-senior/</path>
	</meta>
	<content type="main">
		<h1>Ensor Senior</h1>
		<biog>
			<src>/img/characters/ensor-sr.png</src>
			<info type="Name">Ensor Senior</info>
			<info type="Special skills">Computer expert</info>
		</biog>
		
		<ross>
			<p>Derek Farr who played Ensor Sr. was sixty-six when <a href="/series-1/episode-13-Orac/">Orac</a>, the episode in which he appears, underwent principle photography.</p>
			<p>At the time the episode <em>Orac</em> was shot, Terry Nation, the creator of <em>Blake's 7</em> and the writer of <em>Orac</em>, was forty-seven.</p>
		</ross>

		<h2>Early career</h2>
		<p>Not much is known of Ensor Sr.'s early career.</p>
		
		<ross>
			<figure class="img-r">
				<img SRC="/Dear-Charlotte/img/characters/terry-nation/terry-nation-early.jpg" alt=""/>
			</figure>
			<p>Terry Nation started work as a scriptwriter when he was twenty-five years old. Initially, he worked in comedy, producing scripts for Spike Milligan, Peter Sellers, Frankie Howerd and Tony Hancock.</p>
			<p>The scriptwriter David Whitaker contacted Nation, to offer him work on a <jargon type="sci-fi"/> show which was in development at the <jargon type="BBC"/>.</p>
		</ross>
		
		<h2>Big breakthrough</h2>
		<p>Ensor Sr. developed the Tarial Cell at the age of eighteen. The Tarial Cell became a key component in all Federation computers. Ensor was indispensable to the Federation.</p>
		
		<ross>
			<p>Nation's professional relationship with Tony Handcock broke down in 1963, following an argument. He contacted Whitaker and agreed to write for the show, eventually producing the second story for <em>Doctor Who</em>, <em>The Daleks</em>. The Daleks quickly became the series' most popular villains. Indeed, many credit Nation's scripts as saving the show from cancellation and winning over the hearts of the public.</p>
			<figure class="img-r">
				<img SRC="/Dear-Charlotte/img/characters/terry-nation/terry-nation-tom-baker.jpg" alt=""/>
			</figure>
			<p>Because Nation wasn't employed by the <jargon type="BBC"/> as a staff writer, he retained copyright of the Daleks. When they exploded in popularity, a deal was struck where the merchandising royalties for Dalek products were split evenly between the <jargon type="BBC"/> and Terry Nation. This meant he was comfortably off for the rest of his life, but also allowed him to control exactly how the Daleks were depicted<note>One of the few times he authorised <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=C0n88tZQc4Q" title="Spike Milligan was kind of a genius, but this sketch is rubbish.">the use of Daleks for comic effect was for Spike Milligan</a>, who gave him an early break in his writing career.</note>.</p>
			<p>Nation produced many more scripts for <em>Doctor Who</em>, creating other adversaries for The Doctor to defeat with his cunning and guile. But Nation also contributed scripts to shows such as <em>The Avengers</em>, <em>The Baron</em>, <em>The Champions</em>, <em>Department S</em>, <em>The Persuaders!</em> and <em>The Saint</em>.</p>
			<p>For better or worse, Nation's fate would always be tied to that of the Daleks.</p>
		</ross>
		
		<char>
			<p>It is interesting that a writer known largely for comedy should create one of the most successful and brutal monsters in Doctor Who. <note>There were some brave decisions taken with the early show, perhaps because no-one knew whether it would last. For example, casting Hartnell, who was known for heavy men and army generals, as a children’s hero.</note></p>

			<figure class="img-r">
				<img SRC="/Dear-Charlotte/img/characters/terry-nation/movellans.jpg" alt=""/>
				<figcaption>Movellans from <em>Destiny of the Daleks</em></figcaption>
			</figure>
			
			<p>There are flashes of comedy in Nation’s stories, especially in his later fourth Doctor contributions (<em>Android Invasion</em> and <em>Destiny of the Daleks</em>). Mainly, however, they are dark tales of repression, slavery and the battle to survive. Perhaps the Daleks were successful because they were so very opposite to humanity; cold and clinical, robotic in appearance; genetically engineered to become the dominant species in the universe and to rule without compassion or pity.</p>
			<p>Sydney Newman, who commissioned <em>Doctor Who</em> as family entertainment, designed to sit after the football results on a Saturday evening, had one rule: no <jargon type="BEM"/>s (bug-eyed monsters). To him, Nation’s creation were the epitome of <jargon type="BEM"/>s and they nearly didn’t appear at all. Fortunately for <em>Doctor Who</em>, the Dalek story, just the second full story in its history, immediately secured the show’s success.</p>
			<p>It could be argued that the design of the Daleks themselves was a key feature in their success. Certainly they gave rise to a handy stream of merchandise, from pepper pots to pants. But for many it was the strength of Nation’s writing that helped cement their legacy. <note>The same man was responsible for designing the original <jargon type="TARDIS"/> interior, now also iconic. For him it was simply another paid job. Nation’s contribution paid for a rather nice mansion house.</note></p>
		</char>

		<h2>Vital asset</h2>
		<p>The Federation realised that Ensor's knowledge could be dangerous in the wrong hands and that it was vital that he continued to work for them. He was essentially kept under house arrest.</p>
		<p>He developed other advances in computing which were incorporated into every level of society. He tutored Muller, who went on to create sophisticated androids.</p>
		
		<ross>
			<p>The success of <em>Doctor Who</em> allowed Nation to develop two original series from the middle of the nineteen-seventies onward: <em>The Survivors</em> and <em>Blake's 7</em>. Both were very dark in tone, with <em>The Survivors</em> taking place after most of the world's population has been killed by a plague and <em>Blake's 7</em> being set in a future ruled by an authoritarian and ruthless government.</p>
		</ross>

		<h2>Health problems</h2>
		<p>At the age of twenty-five, Ensor took his family on holiday to a frontier planet. While there, he suffered a heart attack. The only available transplant was a mechanical heart, powered by micro-power cells, with a life of forty Earth years.</p>

		<ross>
			<p>Nation wrote every episode of the first series of <em>Blake's 7</em> by himself, of which <em>Orac</em>, the thirteenth episode, was the series finale. It was broadcast on the 27th of March, 1978.</p>
		</ross>

		<h2>Escape</h2>
		<p>Ensor used the low security of the frontier planet to escape from the Federation, taking with him his four-year-old son. He constructed a laboratory under the seas of Aristo.</p>
		<p>Aristo used to have a great civilisation, but it collapsed and the remains were slowly being swallowed by the acid seas.</p>
		
		<char>
			<p>Interestingly Nation stopped writing for <em>Doctor Who</em> after the fourth Doctor era, although his creation continues to appear in the new stories, terrifying a whole new generation of Whovians.</p>
		</char>
		
		<ross>
			<p>Nation had less involvement with the final three series of <em>Blake's 7</em>, although he did still write episodes.</p>
			<p>In 1980, at the height of his popularity in the <jargon type="UK"/>, he moved with his wife and two children to Los Angeles, to look for work in America.</p>
		</ross>

		<h2>Wilderness years</h2>
		<p>Ensor toiled away in his laboratory for forty years, creating Orac, force walls, drones and other security devices. None of this technology, aside from Orac, would be appreciated by anyone.</p>
		
		<ross>
			<figure class="img-r">
				<img SRC="/Dear-Charlotte/img/characters/terry-nation/terry-nation-late.jpg" alt=""/>
			</figure>
			<p>Nation enjoyed the lifestyle in Los Angeles and within television circles was respected. He attended fan conventions and saw first-hand the impact his work had had on people.</p>
			<p>Unfortunately, there's little to show for Terry Nation's remaining seventeen years in Los Angeles. He wrote scripts for <em>MacGyver</em> and a <jargon type="TV"/> movie.</p>
			<p>Around the time of his death in 1997, he was working with Paul Darrow (Avon), in an attempt to revive <em>Blake's 7</em>.</p>
		</ross>

		<h2>Death</h2>
		<p>The micro-power cells in Ensor's artificial heart ran out of power before he could be taken to <em>The Liberator</em>'s surgical unit and Ensor died alone, in a tunnel, just metres away from the surface.</p>

		<ross>
			<p>Terry Nation died of emphysema, a condition of the lungs brought on by his heavy smoking, on the 9th of March, 1997, before <em>Blake's 7</em> could be recommissioned.</p>
			<p>He was sixty-six years old.</p>
		</ross>

		<h2>Legacy</h2>
		<p>Much of Ensor's irascible personality lived on in Orac, whose temperament changed to more resemble his creator, after Ensor's death. Orac's single-mindedness, determination and intelligence saved Blake and his crew many times.</p>
		
		<char>
			<p>Terry Nation's legacy is one of the strongest in the series’ 50 year history.</p>
			<p>Genesis is constantly voted as one of the best Doctor Who stories of all time and justifiably so.</p>
		</char>

		<ross>
			<p>Readers of <em>Doctor Who Magazine</em> voted Nation's <em>Genesis of the Daleks</em> as <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/tv-and-radio/tvandradioblog/2013/may/23/genesis-of-the-daleks-doctor-who">the greatest <em>Doctor Who</em> story of all time</a>, in 1998.</p>
			<p>In 2007, <a href="http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/entertainment/6574753.stm">the Daleks were voted the scariest villains</a>, in a survey of 21,000 <em>Doctor Who</em> fans.</p>
			<p>In 2010, <a href="http://www.dailyrecord.co.uk/entertainment/tv-radio/the-daleks-are-voted-sci-fis-top-monsters-1067481">the Daleks were voted the best <jargon type="sci-fi"/> monsters</a>, in a poll taken for SFX magazine.</p>
		</ross>

	</content>
</page>