<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="/Dear-Charlotte/xslt/page.xslt"?>
<page>
	<meta>
		<description>Quick character summary of Olag Gan</description>
		<path>/Dear-Charlotte/about-blakes-7/olag-gan/</path>
	</meta>
	<content type="main">
		<h1>Olag Gan</h1>
		<biog>
			<src>/Dear-Charlotte/img/characters/gan.png</src>
			<info type="Name">Olag Gan</info>
			<info type="Special skills">Brute force</info>
			<info type="Dramatic role">Crowd control</info>
			<info type="Character from Robin Hood he represents">Little John</info>
		</biog>
		
		<h2>First meeting</h2>
		<p>Gan just sort of lurks in the background of <a href="/Dear-Charlotte/series-1/episode-2-space-fall/">Space Fall</a>, like he's a supporting actor, until required to do some grunt work. It seems like Vila and he are friends, but Gan wasn't in the holding cell at the end of <a href="/Dear-Charlotte/series-1/episode-1-the-way-back/">The Way Back</a>. The journey from Earth to Cygnus Alpha took many months, so perhaps they became friends there, in the awkward atmosphere of a failed escape and several dead crew members and prisoners.</p>
		
		<h2>Background</h2>
		<p>All we know about Gan comes from Gan himself - he was imprisoned for the murder of a guard who had killed his <q>woman</q> and was fitted with a limiter<note>An electronic brain implant which makes it impossible for him to kill people</note> and deported to Cygnus Alpha with Blake, Jenna, Avon and Vila.</p>
		
		<h2>Character development</h2>
		<p>Rob Emery, over in the official <em>Blake's 7</em> fan club site, suggests that the episode <a href="/Dear-Charlotte/series-1/episode-10-breakdown/">Breakdown</a> was <a href="http://www.blakes7online.com/articles.php?article_id=7">originally intended to show a deeper side of Gan, but failed, due to him spending most of the episode unconscious</a>.</p>
		<p>He's right, but we do get <em>some</em> insight into Gan. Something goes wrong with his limiter at the start of the episode and he attacks <em>The Liberator</em> and its crew. There are two possible interpretations of this:</p>
		<ol>
			<li>The limiter goes wrong and compels Gan to kill</li>
			<li>The limiter goes wrong and <em>allows</em> Gan to express hitherto hidden desires</li>
		</ol>
		<p>Later in the episode, Gan is restrained and tricks Cally into letting him go, by pretending to be normal again. <em>Surely</em> such deception would require higher brain function? If the limiter was simply triggering his amygdala into a fight-or-flight reaction, he would be incapable of such a sophisticated ruse. Plus the limiter seems to be put in place to <em>control</em> certain impulses, not to implant different behaviour patterns.</p>
		<p><a href="/Dear-Charlotte/series-1/episode-10-breakdown/#professor-kayn">Professor Kayn</a> - a neurosurgeon - says that Gan must be <q cite="http://blakes7.wikia.com/wiki/Breakdown_(dialogue_transcript)">a dangerous psychopath</q>, due to the presence of his limiter. While we're not sure of the extent of his knowledge of Federation policy regarding the implantation of limiters, he does seem a more informed source than Gan himself.</p>
		<p>So what I'm suggesting here is that Gan <em>is</em> a psychopath, whose violent urges are only <em>just</em> being kept in check by his limiter. His secret plan is to persuade Blake and his crew of his loyalty, so they will remove his limiter and allow him to indulge his dark thoughts.</p>

		<h2>Screen time</h2>
		<p>In trying to find a suitable screen grab for the image at the top of this page, I realised that Gan is rarely in the middle of the frame, in focus and on his own. He's generally pushed to the back of shots, behind other actors. Basically, the camera <em>hates</em> him.</p>
		<p>It's perhaps little wonder that, as Rob Emery says of Gan: <q cite="http://www.blakes7online.com/articles.php?article_id=7">the first audience research reports were in and included in the results were the audiences’ rating of each character ... someone had to come last and that someone was Gan</q>.</p>

	</content>
</page>