<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="/Dear-Charlotte/xslt/page.xslt"?>
<page>
	<meta>
		<description>An introduction to Doctor Who, part 2: Use of quarries</description>
		<path>/charlotte-responds/use-of-quarries/</path>
	</meta>
	<content type="main">
		<h1>Use of quarries</h1>

		<figure class="img-r">
			<img SRC="/Dear-Charlotte/img/charlotte-responds/brain-of-morbius-castle.jpg" alt=""/>
			<figcaption>The castle from <em>Brain of Morbius</em></figcaption>
		</figure>

		<p>In the 70s, all alien invasions of Earth took place ‘somewhere in the south of England’. Even in <em>Terror of the Zygons</em>, where it is supposed to be Scotland, they film it in SE and just give the Doctor a tartan scarf<note>I’m so sorry Scotland.</note>. Times were hard and the BBC budget just couldn’t stretch to a few train tickets.</p>
		<p>Alien planets in Doctor Who come in two types: crazy studio sets and gravel pits. The former include <em>Brain of Morbius</em>, whose gothic castle looks strikingly similar to the one in <a href="/series-1/episode-3-cygnus-alpha/"><em>Cygnus Alpha</em></a>. The rocks make a clunky noise when Sarah (Elizabeth Sladen) walks up them in her platforms. Even the splendid forest-scape in Planet of Evil has a bit where Tom Baker steps through the polystyrene.</p>

		<figure class="img-r">
			<img SRC="/Dear-Charlotte/img/charlotte-responds/hand-of-fear.jpg" alt=""/>
			<figcaption>The quarry in <em>Hand of Fear</em></figcaption>
		</figure>

		<p>This does lead for a couple of lovely moments of self referencing humour when quarries appear in the story as, well, actual quarries. Cue the opening scene of <em>Hand of Fear</em>. Sarah basically says <q cite="http://www.chakoteya.net/DoctorWho/14-2.htm">what’s this planet Doctor? It’s a bit rubbish isn’t it?</q> and they stroll around throwing rocks and ignoring the sirens which they apparently think are ambient planet noise. The sirens turn out to be emergency warnings, the quarry is blown up and they get covered in a whole bunch of rocks. True story.</p>
	</content>
</page>