<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="/Dear-Charlotte/xslt/page.xslt"?>
<page>
	<meta>
		<description>Episode 1: Redemption. Avon figures out that Orac's prediction of The Liberator going boom happens against a unique star field, so all they need to do is avoid that bit of space. But then The Liberator gets attacked and taken over by the folk who originally built it. They take the crew to Space World, a space station which controls three planets. Blake is interrogated and the rest of the crew are imprisoned, pending execution. Blake escapes with the help of a handy slave and Vila gets the rest out. They peg it, but realise they're in exactly the location where Orac predicted their destruction. Luckily, Orac's been busy hacking into Space World's computers, and makes a ship which looks exactly like The Liberator explode instead.</description>
		<path>/Dear-Charlotte/series-2/episode-1-redemption/</path>
		<type>episode</type>
	</meta>
	<content type="main">
		<h1>Episode 1: Redemption</h1>
		<p>In the last episode, Blake and the gang went to Aristo, where Ensor Sr., the creator or Orac, lived (spoilers). Orac briefly takes over the ship, because Ensor Sr. is asleep and has left him in charge of security. Blake and Cally trot down to try and fix Ensor, but end up with a corpse and a free Orac. They pause long enough for Avon to blow off Travis' silly robot hand, then scamper away with Orac, the world's grumpiest fish tank.</p>
		<p>This time, Blake will have another use for Orac's <jargon type="L33T"/> hacking skills.</p>

		<h2>Death by paradox</h2>
		<p>Blake's going over Orac's prediction from the last episode, which shows <em>The Liberator</em> blowing up in sexy slow motion:</p>

		<blockquote class="imgur-embed-pub" lang="en" data-id="a/lwHx8"><a href="/Dear-Charlotte//imgur.com/lwHx8"></a></blockquote><script async="" src="//s.imgur.com/min/embed.js" charset="utf-8"></script>

		<p>He's looking for a loophole but Orac won't tell him any more details about the prediction because then Blake would be able to avoid it. So Orac would rather explode with <em>The Liberator</em> than give Blake any useful information which might avoid this fate. I'm sure we've all met people like this on the Internet before - <em>heyooo!</em></p>

		<char>
			<figure class="img-r">
				<img src="/Dear-Charlotte/img/series-2/episode-1-redemption/forth-doctor-regeneration.jpg" alt=""/>
				<figcaption>The Forth Doctor turns into some vet from <em>All Creatures Great and Small</em></figcaption>
			</figure>
			<p>I feel I should be able to reach into my vast knowledge of the Who-niverse to find a similar example of this prediction / limiter thing. The <jargon type="TARDIS"/> has a cloister bell which warns of danger, but gives little useful information other than making a mournful BONG noise. I could spend pages discussing the Doctor's thoughts on changing the past / future. (The old <a href="http://tardis.wikia.com/wiki/Blinovitch_Limitation_Effect" title="The page on TARDIS Data Core on Blinovitch Limitation Effect">Blinovitch Limitation Effect</a> and similar nonsense.) The fourth Doctor does predict a presidential assassination (before finding somewhere comfy for a wobbly lie down) and his own regeneration (via the medium of paper mâché).</p>
		</char>

		<h2>Cool Guys Don't Look At Explosions</h2>
		<p>Avon explains that Blake is looking in the wrong place: instead of staring at the explosion like a child at a fireworks display, he should look at the background. The star field is unique and all they need to do is avoid that bit of space.</p>

		<ross>
			<p>We all know that <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Sqz5dbs5zmo" title="Video for 'Cool Guys Don't Look At Explosions'">Cool Guys Don't Look At Explosions</a>, but what few have wondered is <q>I wonder how The Doctor reacts to explosions?</q></p>
			<p>Luckily, I know someone who has put extensive thought into the matter:</p>
		</ross>

		<char>
			<p>For all his alien intelligence and skill, the Doctor is mainly really good at causing chaos. Few stories end without the leadership having been overthrown, the system broken down, quite a lot of extras having met their untimely end and at least one building / space ship going ba-ba-da-BOOOM! in slow motion. Bits of model work everywhere. The Doctor has three reactions to explosions:</p>
			<ol>
				<li>run away slightly too slowly so the blast propels him into a muddy trench (Fenric)</li>
				<li>run away a bit faster so he can bury his face in a sandy pit (Zygons)</li>
				<li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=5Pm2LQIWipw">stroll away casually with Panama barely askance</a> (<em>Greatest Show</em>) using his brolly as a cane, like a chap on his way to the office of Farborough, Farborough and Pugh, galactic attorneys at law. Too cool for Time Lord school.</li>
			</ol>
		</char>

		<p>Avon has knows about this for <em>hours</em>, but didn't tell anyone because he wanted to make a weird passive-aggressive point.</p>

		<ross>
			<p>He does this a couple of times in the episode. I think Avon admires Blake for having skills he does not, such as inspiring devotion in people, rather than creeping them out or (even worse) inspiring them to draw endless pictures of him topless, riding a unicorn and then putting them on <em>Tumblr</em><note>Finding, or indeed <em>illustrating</em>, such a picture is an exercise left up to the reader</note>.</p>
		</ross>

		<p>The bit of space where Avon has identified the explosion takes place is very far away.</p>

		<h2>Environmental damage</h2>
		<p><em>The Liberator</em> is rocked by a weird green explosion and everyone does some <jargon type="RADA"/> tumbling. The ship is being shot at, but because the intermediary sensers are down, Zen can't tell them who's doing all the shooting.</p>
		<p>Avon gets on the communicator and says <q cite="http://blakes7.wikia.com/wiki/Redemption_(dialogue_transcript)">battle stations</q> with really dramatic intonation:</p>

		<figure>
			<p><iframe width="100%" height="166" scrolling="no" frameborder="no" src="https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/279426958&amp;color=ff5500&amp;auto_play=false&amp;hide_related=false&amp;show_comments=true&amp;show_user=true&amp;show_reposts=false"></iframe></p>
		</figure>

		<p>Blake sets the controls of <em>The Liberator</em> to <q>run away</q> and there's a chase which goes into the upper atmosphere of a gas giant:</p>

		<blockquote class="imgur-embed-pub" lang="en" data-id="a/h3KaO"><a href="/Dear-Charlotte//imgur.com/h3KaO"></a></blockquote><script async="" src="//s.imgur.com/min/embed.js" charset="utf-8"></script>

		<p>The ships look <em>suspiciously</em> like they're made out of bits of <em>The Liberator</em>. Zen is his usual evasive self, admitting that the ships aren't Federation, but when asked who they are, says <q cite="http://blakes7.wikia.com/wiki/Redemption_(dialogue_transcript)">That information is not available</q>.</p>

		<ross>
			<p>In the last episode, Orac is similarly evasive about the fate of <em>The Liberator</em>, and uses weasel words to avoid giving anything away, but also to avoid telling a lie.</p>
			<p>It's a strange trope of science fiction, the idea that we can create an <jargon type="AI"/>, but not one which is capable of telling a lie, or allowed to lie in the first place.</p>
		</ross>

		<h2>The Gasball Rally</h2>
		<p><em>The Liberator</em> starts orbiting the planet <em>really fast</em>, but the ships are catching up. Gan picks up their communications, but it's all in chirpy computer language.</p>
		<p>Vila tries to fire, but the <q cite="http://blakes7.wikia.com/wiki/Redemption_(dialogue_transcript)">failsafes</q> stop him from doing so. Then the force wall won't work. Blake is left with one option: leg it, only <em>more so</em>.</p>

		<h2>Cruise control</h2>

		<figure class="img-r">
			<img src="/Dear-Charlotte/img/series-2/episode-1-redemption/computer-probe.jpg" alt=""/>
			<figcaption>Cally and Avon begin repairs on <em>The Liberator</em></figcaption>
		</figure>

		<p>Both ships attack and shoot <em>The Liberator</em> so hard, everyone except Blake falls unconscious. <em>The Liberator</em> is flying somewhere at full power, the scanners are down and Blake and his crew have no control over it any more.</p>
		<p>Blake asks Zen for a status report, but he doesn't answer. Avon hypothesises that the translator unit has blown. Blake gives everyone jobs and Avon gets to use his computer probe thing again<note>Still the aerial from a transistor radio</note>.</p>
		<p>Avon suspects that the ships didn't <em>want</em> to destroy <em>The Liberator</em>, they wanted to disable some of it's systems, then take it <em>somewhere else</em>.</p>

		<h2>Suffragette city</h2>
		<p>Meanwhile, somewhere else, there is a bunch of David Bowies milling about in skin tight snow suits. Look, I'm sorry to go all mathematics on your arse, but the following equation should explain them:</p>

		<figure>
			<img src="/Dear-Charlotte/img/series-2/episode-1-redemption/bowie-equation.jpg" alt=""/>
			<figcaption>Starman plus bleach times Thin White Duke plus power button equals <jargon type="sci-fi"/> Bowies.</figcaption>
		</figure>

		<ross>
			<p>Like a lot of people, you're probably under the misconception that <a href="/Dear-Charlotte/charlotte-responds/loving-the-alien/">David Bowie</a> was a musician and occasional actor and painter. This is not true. David Bowie is a pan-dimensional life form which transcends our crude definition of reality. Observe:</p>
		</ross>

		<figure>
			<figcaption class="h2">History of The Bowie</figcaption>
			<div class="timeline">
				<ol start="1925" class="clearfix">
					<li><time datetime="1925" class="details">The Bowie assumes physical form and crawls out of a shallow pond on the planet Anthea</time></li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li><time datetime="1928" class="details">The Bowie gently floats up through the atmosphere of Anthea, born aloft on the solar wind.</time></li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li><time datetime="1931" class="details">The gravity of earth tugs The Bowie out of deep space, and it drifts down to Earth.</time></li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li><time datetime="1934" class="details">The Bowie meets Nikola Tesla and gives him the idea for <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Teleforce">Teleforce</a></time></li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li><time datetime="1941-06-02" class="details bubble-left">The Bowie lightly touches the virgin bellies of Toby Reed and Louella Osterberg</time></li>
					<li><time datetime="1942-03-02" class="details">Lou Reed is born in Brooklyn, New York</time></li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li><time datetime="1947-04-21" class="details bubble-left">Iggy Pop is born in Muskegon, Michigan</time></li>
					<li><time datetime="1948-05-15" class="details">The Bowie places one of its eyelashes in some agar jelly. Overnight, it takes the form of Brian Eno.</time></li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li><time datetime="1952" class="details">The Bowie is pleased with his butler Brian Eno and fits him with a head-computer.</time></li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li><time datetime="1958-10-28" class="details bubble-left">Lou Reed's first son, William Reid, is born in East Kilbride</time></li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li><time datetime="1961-12-29" class="details bubble-left">Lou Reed's second son, Jim Reid, is born in East Kilbride</time></li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li><time datetime="1964-12" class="details bubble-left">Lou Reed forms <em>The Velvet Underground</em>. He arranges that his children's mother will raise them in secret, in a music-free environment.</time></li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li><time datetime="1966" class="details">The Bowie divides itself into two parts. The smaller part is called Davy Jones and joins <em>The Monkees</em>.</time></li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li><time datetime="1969-07-11" class="details">The Bowie releases <em>Space Oddity</em>, a partially fictionalised account of his trip from Anthea to Earth.</time></li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li><time datetime="1975-07" class="details bubble-left">Lou Reed releases <em><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=XIMSbKU2oZM" title="'Metal Machine Music' by Lou Reed. It's ... challenging.">Metal Machine Music</a></em> and demands that it is the only music the Reid brothers are allowed to hear.</time></li>
					<li><time datetime="1976-03-18" class="details">The documentary <em>The Man Who Fell to Earth</em> is released.</time></li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li><time datetime="1980-02-08" class="details">The Bowie absorbs the zooid Angie Bowie. Her consciousness enriches his own, but she ceases to exist.</time></li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li><time datetime="1983" class="details">Jim and Willian Reid form <em>The Jesus &amp; Mary Chain</em>, whose first album, <em><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=iFp7W3PoNPI" title="'Psychocandy' by The Jesus &amp; Mary Chain">Psychocandy</a></em>, can only be understood by listening to <em>Metal Machine Music</em>.</time></li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li><time datetime="1986--11-28" class="details">The Bowie regenerates into Jareth, the Goblin King, in order to evoke weird boners in man and beast alike.</time></li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li><time datetime="1992-08-28" class="details bubble-left">The Bowie <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=3nSqDMqCJQw" title="The Bowie in 'Twin Peaks: Fire Walk with Me'">is accidentally captured on film, during the filming of <em>Twin Peaks: Fire Walk with Me</em></a></time></li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li><time datetime="1998-09" class="details bubble-left">The Bowie created <q cite="https://www.theguardian.com/technology/2016/jan/11/david-bowie-bowienet-isp-internet">BowieNet</q>, a network of computers designed to hold parts of his consciousness.</time></li>
					<li><time datetime="1999-06" class="details">The Bowie copies part of it's essence into the computer game <em>Omikron: The Nomad Soul</em>, so that future generations will be able to experience it.</time></li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li><time datetime="2006-10-10" class="details">The film <em>The Prestige</em> is released, featuring The Bowie playing his old friend Nikola Tesla</time></li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li><time datetime="2012-02-29" class="details bubble-left">Davy Jones is reabsorbed into The Bowie. His experiences with pop music will enrich their joint consciousness.</time></li>
					<li><time datetime="2013-10-27" class="details">Lou Reed is absorbed once more into The Bowie's consciousness</time></li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li><time datetime="2016-01-10" class="details">The Bowie moves beyond this mortal realm and becomes a creature of pure energy.</time></li>
				</ol>
			</div>
		</figure>

		<h2>Altered Images</h2>
		<p>The two figures are called <q cite="http://blakes7.wikia.com/wiki/Redemption_(dialogue_transcript)">Alters</q> and are sort of funny robot people, because they say things like <q cite="http://blakes7.wikia.com/wiki/Redemption_(dialogue_transcript)">acnowledged</q>, rather than <q>OK, pal</q>, in order to finish a sentence<note>It's strange that neither uses Zen's catch-phrase of <q cite="http://blakes7.wikia.com/wiki/Redemption_(dialogue_transcript)">confirmed</q>, even though <q cite="http://blakes7.wikia.com/wiki/Redemption_(dialogue_transcript)">acnowledged</q> serves the same purpose in the sentence. Zen always was rather wilful.</note>. They're wearing little see-through wipe-down tabards, so they can eat a lobster dinner if they want, and not worry about getting their uniforms all messy.</p>
		<p>The one with more hair tells the one with a Bowie cut that the pursuit ships have done their job.</p>

		<h2>Electricity python</h2>
		<p>On <em>The Liberator</em>, Blake is checking up on some sub-system or other, so he can bypass the auto-pilot. Once he starts mucking about, some electrical cables come loose and traps him in the room, because computers taking over a spaceship is <em>exactly</em> like being haunted by a ghost. Look:</p>

		<blockquote class="imgur-embed-pub" lang="en" data-id="a/hnSx4"><a href="/Dear-Charlotte//imgur.com/hnSx4"></a></blockquote><script async="" src="//s.imgur.com/min/embed.js" charset="utf-8"></script>

		<ross>
			<p>I love the look on Blake's face, when he goes for the communicator, and the cable pops in. <em>Anthropomorphism is always funny</em>.</p>
		</ross>

		<h2>The machine genie</h2>
		<p>There's other mischief going on, such as the teleporter controls waggling about and repairs the crew makes being rejected. Avon figures that Zen <em>is</em> working, but just not for Blake and the crew. He assumes that when <em>The Liberator</em> is boarded, it will all kick off in the teleporter lounge.</p>

		<p>Blake manages to reach the communicator and asks Avon to come down to help him with his possessed cable. Avon does this with all the good grace of a child being asked to eat some Brussels sprouts, when they want to play with Lego instead<note>This is <em>not</em> based on something from my childhood. No, <em>you're</em> autobiographical.</note>.</p>

		<char>
			<p>That's like that time I missed the resolution of a key cliff hanger in <em>Remembrance of the Daleks</em> coz mum made me have a bath. No-one who has known me for less than an hour will have heard that story before.</p>
		</char>

		<h2>Snake charming</h2>
		<p>Avon saves Blake by planting a very distracting bomb elsewhere in the room, which means the cable has a sniff about that, while they both leg it.</p>

		<p>Gan passes through the teleporter lounge, when he hears some weird teleport noises. He's in the process of warning Blake when three <a href="https://www.google.co.uk/search?q=morph+suits&amp;tbm=isch" title="You know - those body-condoms which make everyone look creepy">morph-suited</a> stormtroopers teleport in and start wrestling with him, then taser him unconscious. Crew members start disappearing left and right and Blake gets so desperate, he turns to Orac for help. Orac says he's busy with something, and can't receive any more instructions but will put Blake's instructions in a queue. Suddenly the Bowies turn up, under green lighting, for some reason. They take control of the ship.</p>

		<biog>
			<src>/Dear-Charlotte/img/characters/alter1.png</src>
			<info type="Name">Alter 1</info>
			<info type="Job">John Humphries on <em>Mastermind</em></info>
			<info type="Favourite perk of the job">Silver hair spray</info>
			<info type="Most embarrassing moment">That time I made a database query and the results came back null, so I just ended up repeating the last cached data, and sounded like a <em>right</em> berk</info>
			<info type="Secret fear">That I've missed a spot on the back of my head with my silver hair spray</info>
			<info type="Metal level"><em><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=63rYGgQ9UCA" title="'Join in the Chant' by Nitzer Ebb">Nitzer Ebb</a></em></info>
		</biog>

		<ross>
			<p>Bowie number one was played by <a href="http://www.imdb.com/name/nm0750835/">Sheila Ruskin</a>, who was also cast as Kassia in the forth Doctor era <em>The Keeper of Traken</em></p>
		</ross>

		<char>
			<figure class="img-r">
				<img src="/Dear-Charlotte/img/series-2/episode-1-redemption/kassia.jpg" alt=""/>
				<figcaption>Kassia from <em>The Keeper of Traken</em></figcaption>
			</figure>
			<p><em>Keeper of Traken</em>. Not my favourite although it had the benefit of:</p>
			<ol type="a">
				<li>The brilliant <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=bAKHb0JImNo" title="The scene from 'The Keeper of Traken' where The Master takes Tremas' body. This is less disturbing than it sounds.">Anthony Ainley</a> on real form and</li>
				<li>Being one of the few Doctor Who novels we could rent from my school library. (It was a grammar school. They generally frowned upon any literature that wasn't 'improving' in some way.)</li>
			</ol>
			<p>Kassia (Nyssa's mum) was a bit of a crazy lady who was in love with a statue. Turns out that's not super sensible as it transformed into the Master's <jargon type="TARDIS"/> and went all planetary domination on the Traken's arse.</p>
			<p>Never idolise kids. It'll end in...wait, did someone move something on my Tom Baker shrine?</p>
		</char>

		<biog>
			<src>/Dear-Charlotte/img/characters/alter2.png</src>
			<info type="Name">Alter 2</info>
			<info type="Job">Hemisphere-fondler</info>
			<info type="Favourite perk of the job">Access to the pain-wand</info>
			<info type="Most embarrassing moment">That time the server initiated a handshake protocol with me and I sent him a garbled synchronise-acknowledgement message, because my palms were all sweaty.</info>
			<info type="Secret fear">That my forehead button is <em>slightly</em> off-centre</info>
			<info type="Metal level"><em><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=9QMtDyvAzVw" title="'The Beautiful People' by Marilyn Manson, covered by robots">Marilyn Manson</a></em></info>
		</biog>

		<ross>
			<p>Bowie two was played by <a href="http://www.imdb.com/name/nm0680940/">Harriet Philpin</a>, who was also cast as Betan from <em>Genesis of the Daleks</em></p>
		</ross>

		<char>
			<figure class="img-r">
				<img src="/Dear-Charlotte/img/series-2/episode-1-redemption/betan.jpg" alt=""/>
				<figcaption>Betan from <em>Genesis of the Daleks</em></figcaption>
			</figure>
			<p>Betan is apparently one of only two women on the planet Skaro according to the amount of screen time ladies get in <em>Genesis of the Daleks</em>. The other one is Sarah and she's just passing through. I bet internet dating is a whole heap of fun. Anyway, Betan is super cool and leads up a resistance army against the Daleks despite apparently being about 12. Good to see she's kept the same pixie cut too.</p>
		</char>

		<p>Blake wants to know where Gan, Cally and Vila are. The Bowies are not interested in his questions:</p>

		<blockquote class="imgur-embed-pub" lang="en" data-id="a/OAOxh"><a href="/Dear-Charlotte//imgur.com/OAOxh"></a></blockquote><script async="" src="//s.imgur.com/min/embed.js" charset="utf-8"></script>


		<figure class="img-r">
			<img src="/Dear-Charlotte/img/series-2/episode-1-redemption/space-molecule.jpg" alt=""/>
			<figcaption><em>The Liberator</em> approaches <em>Space World</em><note>Ask about our family weekend ticket deals!</note></figcaption>
		</figure>

		<h2>Parking Space (World)</h2>
		<p>Zen's all better and the Bowies order him to dock with a sort of space-molecule.</p>
		<p>There's a landing sequence, cobbled together from shots of the actors looking bored and other shots of runways at night taken from aeroplanes. Blake, Jenna and Avon are ordered to walk to the main hatch.</p>
		<p>After Blake has left, the first Bowie hears Orac making a sound. She walks over and looks at him, utterly uninterested.</p>

		<ross>
			<h2>The part of <em>Space World</em><note>Not to be confused with <em><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=izQESt4D9N8" title="Sheeeeeeeeeeeeeeeit, McNulty!">Spice World</a></em></note> in tonight's performance...</h2>
			<p>This is the second appearance of the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oldbury_Nuclear_Power_Station">Oldbury-on-Severn Nuclear Power Station</a> in Bristol as a location. It was first used in <a href="/Dear-Charlotte/series-1/episode-4-time-squad/">Time Squad</a>. But I don't mind: it looks great.</p>
		</ross>

		<char>
			<figure class="img-r">
				<img src="/Dear-Charlotte/img/series-2/episode-1-redemption/oldbury-on-severn-doctor-who.jpg" alt=""/>
				<figcaption>The Oldbury-on-Severn Nuclear Power Station's appearance in <em>The Hand of Fear</em></figcaption>
			</figure>
			<p>Is it ok that I knew this fact before you mentioned it? Anyway. It's a great location and they make the most of it in <em>Hand of Fear</em>. Lots of lovely angles and running up and down ladders. In the same way as <a href="/Dear-Charlotte/charlotte-responds/use-of-quarries/">the quarry appears as a quarry in the same story</a>, the power station plays the part of a power station. That shouldn't be weird, but somehow is. I love <em>Hand</em> because it gives Sarah the chance to be a baddy. She also has a very sweet relationship with the Doctor in this, her last story. Low points include a rubbish attempt to bash the Doctor with a massive polystyrene spanner. Oh and <a href="/Dear-Charlotte/charlotte-responds/rada-acting/">STEPHEN THORNE</a>.</p>
		</char>

		<h2>Let's take this to the next level</h2>
		<p>Blake, Avon and Jenna are led through an industrial looking part of <em>Space World</em><note>Winner of <q>Most Improved Hygiene Award</q>, 2X58</note>. Blake is separated, so he can be interrogated by <q cite="http://blakes7.wikia.com/wiki/Redemption_(dialogue_transcript)">The System</q>. Avon and Jenna are to be executed. Blake argues that the Bowies have no right to do such a thing, and gets LEVEL FIVE to his neck:</p>

		<blockquote class="imgur-embed-pub" lang="en" data-id="a/POzWU"><a href="/Dear-Charlotte//imgur.com/POzWU"></a></blockquote><script async="" src="//s.imgur.com/min/embed.js" charset="utf-8"></script>

		<p>Avon and Jenna are taken to a cell. Things don't look good, but at least they've got a lovely view of the stars.</p>

		<h2>Pipe down</h2>
		<p>Blake is taken past some supporting actors, wearing comedy rags and carrying a large pipe on their shoulders. One of them drops the pipe, then gets the sparky rod treatment. Blake rushes to his aid and helps him up. They march on.</p>

		<ross>

			<figure class="img-r">
				<img src="/Dear-Charlotte/img/series-2/episode-1-redemption/miner.jpg" alt=""/>
				<figcaption>Roy Evans playing the un-named miner in <em>The Monster of Peladon</em>. 50% Leo Sayer, 50% badger.</figcaption>
			</figure>

			<p>The unnamed slave is played by Roy Evans, who has one of those faces which keeps popping up. You might remember him from <em>The Black Adder</em> or <em>The Elephant Man</em>, but I'm grateful for <a href="http://www.imdb.com/name/nm0263189/">his <jargon type="IMDB"/> page</a> introducing me to the film <em><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=hM1lsDhSjD8" title="Frankly, you had me at 'Space Hijab'">Moon Zero Two</a></em>.</p>
			<p>He also appeared in a couple of <em>Doctor Who</em> stories: <em>The Monster of Peladon</em> and <em>The Green Death</em>. He plays a miner in <em>both</em>, but looks much funnier in the first one.</p>
			<p>Unfortunately, both episodes were of the Jon Pertwee era, so they fall outside of Charlotte's jurisdiction. But let's nudge her, and see what she says anyway, eh, gang?</p>
		</ross>

		<char>

		<figure class="img-r">
				<img src="/Dear-Charlotte/img/series-2/episode-1-redemption/eyechild.jpg" alt=""/>
				<figcaption>Alpha Centauri (right) from <em>The Monster of Peladon</em>. An influence on the <em>Garth Marenghi's Darkplace</em> episode <em><a href="http://www.channel4.com/programmes/garth-marenghis-darkplace/on-demand/36434-003" title="Skipper the Eyechild on Channel4.com. Sorry folks outside the UK.">Skipper the Eyechild</a></em></figcaption>
			</figure>

			<p>Hmm, Jon Pertwee era. Stretching it. The Third Doctor goes to Peladon twice in his era, then never visits again in his remaining ten (depending when you're reading this) regenerations. This sort of thing, together with series 'arcs' makes Doctor Who tricky for me. If he can travel anywhere in time and space, why does he see particular species of monster in strict evolutionary order? Why doesn't he accidentally materialise, say, three tenths of the way through the Master's incredibly circuitous plan? Just saying.</p>
			<p>Yeah I know that wasn't anything to do with Jon Pertwee's era. It's not like I get paid for this.</p>
		</char>

		<h2>Get it out of your system</h2>
		<p>Blake is taken into a room where the Bowies interact with these <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=KAKWKfVcd04" title="The scene from 'Sleeper' where the orb is passed around at a party">orbs</a> set into the desks. Blake asks what <q cite="http://blakes7.wikia.com/wiki/Redemption_(dialogue_transcript)">The System</q> is. The Bowie explains that The System is a series of computers which runs every aspect of society, but also control the Bowies themselves. Blake demands that his crew remain unharmed and <em>nearly</em> gets LEVEL SEVEN to his neck:</p>

		<blockquote class="imgur-embed-pub" lang="en" data-id="a/Re920"><a href="/Dear-Charlotte//imgur.com/Re920"></a></blockquote><script async="" src="//s.imgur.com/min/embed.js" charset="utf-8"></script>

		<h2>Recap in hand</h2>
		<p>The System wants to know how Blake and his crew ended up on board <em>The Liberator</em>, which is handy, as it lets Blake do a bit of back story for those who missed the first series, because they were busy listening to <em>The Clash</em> or <em>Yes</em>. If <em>you</em> want a recap, just read my summary of <em><a href="/Dear-Charlotte/series-1/episode-2-space-fall/">Space Fall</a></em>, yeah?</p>
		<p>One of the Bowies (Alter 1) starts to go a bit wrong, and keeps repeating the question <q cite="http://blakes7.wikia.com/wiki/Redemption_(dialogue_transcript)">State any further information you have, regarding <abbr title="Deep Space Vehicle">DSV</abbr>2</q>, until smoke starts coming out of her orb. The other Bowie (Alter 2) notes that something is messing their computers <em>right</em> up. The first Bowie calls off the interrogation, until they can update their McAfee install. Blake realises that Orac is monkeying about in The System.</p>

		<figure class="img-r">
			<img src="/Dear-Charlotte/img/series-2/episode-1-redemption/avon-jenna-cell.jpg" alt=""/>
			<figcaption>Avon paces the cell while Jenna worries about the toilet facilities</figcaption>
		</figure>
		<h2>Written in the stars</h2>
		<p>Back in the cell, Avon and Jenna overhead that one of the slave gangs have attacked their guards and scarpered. Avon suddenly realises that the pattern of stars they can see out of the cell window matches those which was behind the video which Orac showed them, of <em>The Liberator</em> being blown up.</p>

		<char>
			<figure class="img-r">
				<img src="/Dear-Charlotte/img/series-2/episode-1-redemption/planet-of-evil.jpg" alt=""/>
				<figcaption>The Doctor and Sarah Jane are imprisoned during <em>Planet of Evil</em></figcaption>
			</figure>
			<p>Being incarcerated is a well known staple of 70s Who stories. It joins a tick list that includes corridors run down, regular cast knocked unconscious, on-screen deaths and people being moved pointlessly from one part of the set to another. The obvious reason for incarceration is to add a bit of sense of danger and to allow someone else to conduct a brave rescue. Sometimes it means the Dr and co. can have a nice chat about what's going on, so the more stupid or distracted viewers can keep up. In <em>Planet of Evil</em> the Doctor and Sarah have got so used to being locked up, they just sit on the bunk bed together. It's like they're sort of hanging out in a hostel, like bored gap year students.</p>
		</char>

		<h2>Always crashing in the same star</h2>
		<p>In the interrogation lounge, Bowie 2 tells Bowie 1 that they've got all kinds of errors up in their asses. The other Bowie suggests killing off the prisoners right away. Blake's not delighted by this. He gets marched to <em>Elimination Chamber 2</em>.</p>

		<ross>
			<p>To recap:</p>
			<ul>
				<li>The System is a computer whose control extends over three planets, plus <em>Space World</em><note>Book now, for summer next year. All transactions are final.</note></li>
				<li>The Bowies are essentially dumb terminals, doing the bidding of The System</li>
			</ul>
			<p>Doesn't this mean that when they speak to each other, it's The System talking to itself? Perhaps it's just show-boating, for Blake's benefit.</p>
		</ross>

		<h2>Debug the plug thug</h2>
		<p>On the way there, he <em>finally</em> breaks out some <jargon type="RADA"/> karate on the guards and unplugs something from Bowie 2's neck, which causes her to collapse. But it's OK: one of the guards plugs her in again and she's fine.</p>
		<p>Blake gets trapped in a dead end, but then the slave he helped lug that pipe pops out of a tiny hatch, and beckons him inside. A guard follows after Blake, but ends up looking like a right proper nana, because it appears that Blake has disappeared into thin air, and the man looks about the place, all confused.</p>

		<biog>
			<src>/Dear-Charlotte/img/characters/slave.png</src>
			<info type="Name">He doesn't seem to have one</info>
			<info type="Job">Slave / Pipe-carrier</info>
			<info type="Narrative role">Back-story dispenser</info>
			<info type="Look-a-like"><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=et0vpZvxnJY" title="Red Dwarf deleted scenes with Holly ">Norman Lovett</a></info>
		</biog>

		<h2>Hack the planets</h2>
		<p>The slave gives Blake some back-story: the three planets in this system were eternally at war until one of them developed a computer which hacked into the weaponry of the other two, but then sort of took over all three. The Bowies are called <q cite="http://blakes7.wikia.com/wiki/Redemption_(dialogue_transcript)">Alters</q> and aren't really people at all, apparently.</p>
		<p>In the cell, Avon and Jenna hear a noise from the door, so Avon adopts a karate pose next to it. Vila comes in, and gets a punch in his guts for his troubles. The three of them move off and meet Cally and Gan, before a guard spots them. They leg it, and the guards lob grenades and stuff at them<note>Remember, all of this was shot in an <em>operational nuclear power station</em>. The 1970s were a different time.</note>.</p>

		<blockquote class="imgur-embed-pub" lang="en" data-id="a/ZWFQT"><a href="/Dear-Charlotte//imgur.com/ZWFQT"></a></blockquote><script async="" src="//s.imgur.com/min/embed.js" charset="utf-8"></script>

		<h2>Boys keep swinging</h2>
		<p>Gan gets to do some wrestling, which the others just sort of watch. They clamber up a set of stairs, and the Bowie who got plugged in again holds them up. She gives the order to fire, but then the slave pal of Blake grabs her, and gives her DESTRUCTION LEVEL to the neck:</p>

		<blockquote class="imgur-embed-pub" lang="en" data-id="a/YSfeK"><a href="/Dear-Charlotte//imgur.com/YSfeK"></a></blockquote><script async="" src="//s.imgur.com/min/embed.js" charset="utf-8"></script>

		<h2>At death's door</h2>
		<p>Blake gives the guard a go of the pain wand too, in case he feels left out. The slave leads them back to the door where they came in<note>This is the same door which appears in <a href="/Dear-Charlotte/series-1/episode-4-time-squad/">Time Squad</a>, but it <em>is</em> a very cool door.</note>. For some reason, the slave wants to stay on <em>Space World</em><note>Twined with <a href="http://riddick.wikia.com/wiki/Crematoria" title="You know, the prison planet from the Riddick films">Crematoria</a></note>. As he's closing the door, he gets shot in the back by one of the morph-suited guards.</p>
		<p>Blake and the crew get onto the bridge, and start launch procedures. The guards who tried to follow them through the door stagger out coughing on <em>The Liberator</em>'s exhaust fumes, like they're in a Laurel and Hardy film<note>Except one of them dies. That probably didn't happen in Laurel and Hardy films</note>.</p>
		<p>The remaining Bowie sends a couple of guards through the teleporter onto <em>The Liberator</em>, where they immediately pull the pins out of a couple of grenades. But before they can lob them, Cally sends them right back again. <em>Ha!</em> In your <em>face</em> Bowie! Oh. Too soon. <small><a href="/Dear-Charlotte/charlotte-responds/loving-the-alien/">Sorry David</a></small>.</p>

		<blockquote class="imgur-embed-pub" lang="en" data-id="a/9Emou"><a href="/Dear-Charlotte//imgur.com/9Emou"></a></blockquote><script async="" src="//s.imgur.com/min/embed.js" charset="utf-8"></script>

		<p>The Bowie isn't dead, but she's chanting <q cite="http://blakes7.wikia.com/wiki/Redemption_(dialogue_transcript)">Destruct</q> over and over again, which is rarely a good sign.</p>

		<h2>Prophecy and loss</h2>
		<p><em>The Liberator</em> makes it out of <em>Space World</em><note>Might you, or anyone you know, be interested in working at Space World? Come along, for a no-strings trial, and see how you feel!</note> and Zen tells them there's another ship in pursuit. Jenna and Avon are convinced all is lost: Orac's prediction is coming true. <em>The Liberator</em> is in exactly the location where Orac showed them their destruction. Blake ordered the ship on the view-screen and they see it's <em>The Liberator</em>'s sister ship. It immediately explodes because Orac reprogrammed the missiles to detonate before they were launched. He did this so that his prediction would come true, rather than to save Blake, or even himself. Orac is an <em>arse</em>.</p>
		<p>Blake sets course for the Earth sector, which Avon isn't delighted with. He narrows his eyes at Blake, but does what he says.</p>

		<ross>
			<h2>Deus Ex Machina</h2>
			<p>So now we've seen the power of Orac, let's have a little inventory of Blake's assets:</p>
			<ul>
				<li><em>The Liberator</em>, the fastest ship in the galaxy, whose power recharges automatically</li>
				<li>Orac, a computer which can hack into any other computer in existence, even those which <em>don't</em> use Tarial cells</li>
				<li>The only teleport in existence capable of teleporting life forms</li>
				<li>Jenna, a highly skilled pilot, who can fly any ship</li>
				<li>Avon, a computer genius and star of fanfic</li>
				<li>Vila, who can pick almost any lock</li>
				<li>Cally, who can speak to others with the POWER OF HER MIND</li>
				<li>Gan is also there</li>
			</ul>
			<p>One of the things we found out way back in <a href="/Dear-Charlotte/series-1/episode-1-the-way-back/" title="The Way Back">the first episode</a> is that trials are not decided by jury. They're decided by computer, which automatically weighs the evidence. Even if Blake parked <em>The Liberator</em> in orbit, and allowed Orac to free those sympathetic to his cause, who were wrongly imprisoned, think of the impact he could have<note>For all we know, Orac could do this from half a galaxy away</note>.</p>
			<p>But Blake doesn't do any of this. He flies about the galaxy picking off targets seemingly at random. It's baffling.</p>
		</ross>

		<h2>Watch <em>Redemption</em> on YouTube</h2>
		<youtube id="QXzV0V8DSEg"/>

	</content>
</page>
