<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="/xslt/page.xslt"?>
<page>
	<meta>
		<description>An introduction to Doctor Who, part 6: Weird cults</description>
		<path>/charlotte-responds/weird-cults/</path>
	</meta>
	<content type="main">
		<h1>Weird cults</h1>

		<p>Quasi religions, sacrifices and dens of weirdos form an essential plot staple of this era of Doctor Who. There is potentially a whole philosophy essay to be written about the Doctor’s opinion of religion and morality. Anyway, at various points the companion or the Doctor get tied up in part of some dodgy ceremony. Sometimes they get tied up together, only not in a weird way. It’s a children’s show people.</p>
		<h2>A few examples...</h2>
		<figure class="img-r">
			<img src="/img/charlotte-responds/robot.jpg" alt=""/>
			<figcaption>A still from <em>Robot</em>, without the benefit of modern colour-correction.</figcaption>
		</figure>

		<ul>
			<li><em>Robot</em>: a gathering of scientists want to re-shape the world to fit in with what they think, so they make a big robot steal a massive gun. Mainly they don’t like women in trousers, which is odd as their leader is a lady.</li>
			<li><em>The Brain of Morbius</em>: The Sisterhood of Karn. Their main hobbies are drinking the elixir of life, destroying ships by telepathy, burning time-lords and wearing various shades of pink/orange/red despite all being brunettes.</li>
			<li><em>Image of the Fendahl</em>: in this really weird ceremony Wanda Ventham<note>Benedict Cumberbatch’s mum</note> is painted gold with big dodgy eyes painted on her eyelids. She gradually turns into a slug/tapeworm hybrid. One of the men watching shoots himself. DARK.</li>
			<li><em>Power of Kroll</em>: the Doctor and Romana are tied to boards with reeds, which will shrink as they dry, breaking their limbs. The Doctor escapes by singing. Seriously.</li>
			<li><em>Meglos</em>: this time the cult try to sacrifice the Doctor by dropping a big rock on him. This story was much better as a Target novelisation. The one main selling point of the <jargon type="TV"/> version is Tom Baker’s creepy performance as Meglos.</li>
		</ul>
	</content>
</page>