<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="/Dear-Charlotte/xslt/page.xslt"?>
<page>
	<meta>
		<description>Quick character summary of Vila Restal</description>
		<path>/about-blakes-7/zen/</path>
	</meta>
	<content type="main">
		<h1>Zen</h1>
		<biog>
			<src>/img/characters/zen.gif</src>
			<info type="Name">Zen</info>
			<info type="Special skills">Taking care of business on <em>The Liberator</em></info>
			<info type="Dramatic role">Basic spacial exposition</info>
		</biog>
		
		<h2>First meeting</h2>
		<p>Zen is introduced during <a href="/series-1/episode-3-cygnus-alpha/">Cygnus Alpha</a>, the episode <em>after</em> Blake and his crew first enter <em>The Liberator</em>. Jenna is fannying about with a console when she accidentally hits the <q>allow ship's computer to learn everything about you</q> button. This happens to her:</p>
		
		<blockquote class="imgur-embed-pub" lang="en" data-id="a/zYMe9"><a href="//imgur.com/zYMe9"></a></blockquote><script async="" src="//s.imgur.com/min/embed.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
		
		<p>Zen scans her brain and decides she's cool, so hands over control to her, and because she thinks Blake and Avon are cool too, they get their own access, even though Zen doesn't scan their brains. Perhaps access to Zen works like Gmail did when it first opened, on a referal system. Dunno.</p>

		
		<h2>Artificial intelligence</h2>
		<p>Zen is an unusual character - Avon is constantly dismissing him as <q>just a machine</q> but Blake is fond of attributing his behaviour to emotional states, sometimes in jest, sometimes seemingly seriously.</p>
		<p>Presumably Avon, as a computer expert, would be aware of the current status of artificial intelligence in Federation space, and he seems certain that machines cannot think. He maintains this opinion even after Orac joins the crew.</p>
		
		<h2>Limits of interaction</h2>
		<p>Zen seems to be restricted in how he can interact with Blake and his crew - in <a href="/series-1/episode-2-space-fall/">Space Fall</a> Blake asks about the previous crew, and Zen ignores the question. In <a href="/series-1/episode-4-time-squad/">Time Squad</a>, <a href="/series-1/episode-10-breakdown/">Breakdown</a> and <!--a href="/series-1/episode-13-orac/"-->Orac<!--/a-->, Zen appears to make an attempt to warn the crew they are in danger - albeit in a particularly circumspect way. When Zen needs to communicate to Blake and his crew that their current plan is dangerous, he pretends to go wrong or stops communicating altogether.</p>
		<p>Mostly, however, he is used for dramatic purposes: informing the crew where they are, what's happening to <em>The Liberator</em> and so on.</p>
	</content>
</page>