<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="/Dear-Charlotte/xslt/page.xslt"?>
<page>
	<meta>
		<description>Oh, no it isn’t</description>
		<path>/charlotte-responds/oh-no-it-isnt/</path>
	</meta>
	<content type="main">
		<h1>Oh, no it isn’t</h1>
		<p>So I thought to myself: what this blog needs is something to <q>hoof it up</q> in the intellectual sphere. Someone should delve deep into those reference books that sit gathering dust, unearth hitherto undiscovered insights and reveal them for the world (well, the 5 people reading this blog) to gasp at in awe.</p>
		<p>Perhaps: Terry Nation as <q>Nostradamus</q> making astute predictions via gravel pits and moonboots. Or, meaningful insights into the racial tensions of the 70s, expressed through <em>Blake's 7</em>’s attitude to robots.</p>
		<p>Instead: here are far too many words on why British <jargon type="sci-fi"/> from the 70s and 80s isn’t quite the same as pantomime. You’re welcome<note>It must be panto season somewhere in the infinite multi-verse. Perhaps on Tara, where it’s all silly hats and sword-fighting.</note>.</p>

		<h2>Why do some people hate retro <jargon type="sci-fi"/>?</h2>
		<p>I’m often asked why I like retro <jargon type="sci-fi"/> so much. The truth? I find it comforting. There’s a formula that can be pushed, but not broken. Within the confines of this unspoken contract, you can expand your mind, explore concepts and meet characters that make you see the world in a different way.</p>
		<p>In order to do that and get anything like the enjoyment I get from it, you have to get past some basic facts about British <jargon type="sci-fi"/> from this era<note>Actually not just British and not just <jargon type="sci-fi"/>: films like <em>Labyrinth</em> and <em>Silent Running</em> too.</note>.</p>
		<p>I’ve written a list (surprise!) of these elements. Many are similar to that other stalwart of British entertainment: the pantomime. Which is, coincidentally, also something people love or hate. Enjoyment is about accepting these elements and suspending your disbelief.</p>

		<h2>1) Wobbly sets</h2>
		<figure class="img-r">
			<img SRC="/Dear-Charlotte/img/charlotte-responds/oh-no-it-isnt/crunchy-sets-planet-of-evil.jpg" alt=""/>
			<figcaption>Sarah and The Doctor gingerly move around the set of <em>Planet of Evil</em></figcaption>
		</figure>
		<p>It’s one of the first things anyone mentions about <em>Doctor Who</em>, but for years I didn’t notice it. The rocky steps in <em>Brain of Morbius</em> echo when Liz Sladen stomps up them. Tom Baker puts his foot through a bit of polystyrene jungle in <em>Planet of Evil</em>. The point is; no-one bats an eyelid. The sets are the best they could do on 50p per episode. A friend compared watching <em>Doctor Who</em> to amateur dramatics; with such little money you beg, borrow, steal or make props and sets. The rest is up to your imagination. What makes it work, for me, is the actors. Ok, there are humdingers, but the regular cast take it so seriously that you believe those cardboard steps are the rocky landscape of Karn.</p>

		<h2>2) Camp costumes</h2>
		<p>The funny thing about retro <em>Who</em> is that the only person whose outfit hasn’t dated is the Doctor and that’s because he’s not meant to be fashionable. I admit it: I LOVE the camp costumes. The shiny space-suits in <em>Nightmare of Eden</em>. The white flares in <em>Ark in Space</em>. All that lovely velvet. Mmm.</p>

		<figure class="img-l">
			<img SRC="/Dear-Charlotte/img/charlotte-responds/oh-no-it-isnt/noah.jpg" alt=""/>
			<figcaption>Noah from <em>The Ark in Space</em></figcaption>
		</figure>

		<figure class="img-r">
			<img SRC="/Dear-Charlotte/img/charlotte-responds/oh-no-it-isnt/taran-capal.jpg" alt=""/>
			<figcaption>Taran Capal in <em>Robots of Death</em></figcaption>
		</figure>

		<p>Then there’s the make-up. Pity poor Noah: acting out mental torment by wrestling his own bubbled-wrapped arm. As with the sets, it takes something for an actor to approach believability wearing that much eye shadow. It’s not quite as confusing to, say, an American audience as why in pantos your principal boy is played by a girl and the Dame is played by a man in drag. But just look at Taran Capal in <em>Robots of Death</em>. LOOK AT HIM.</p>

		<h2>3) Fantasy and magic / good and evil</h2>
		<p>Basic fairy tales involve a quest / mystery, a villain being foiled, a long journey and/or a rescue. These plots wouldn’t look out of place in any <em>Doctor Who</em> or <em>Blake's 7</em> episode. It doesn’t take a huge leap of imagination to swap Snow White’s wicked stepmother for, say, Servalan. There are even <em>Doctor Who</em> episodes that steal directly from Greek Myths, like <em>Underworld</em> or <em>Horns of Nimon</em>. The regular cast are always getting stranded and/or locked up and having to be rescued. There are even monsters.</p>
		<p>And, as with panto, the villains are never quite destroyed forever. The Doctor and the Master are like the bad witch and good fairy; they exist in symbiosis with one another. The Master even has an evil beard to stroke whilst chuckling.</p>

		<h2>4) Double acts and comedy</h2>

		<figure class="img-r">
			<img SRC="/Dear-Charlotte/img/charlotte-responds/oh-no-it-isnt/the-gatherer-and-marn.jpg" alt=""/>
			<figcaption>Gatherer Hade and Marn from <em>The Sun Makers</em></figcaption>
		</figure>

		<p>I’ve put this one in as homage to the excellent Robert Holmes. He was, arguably, the best writer <em>Doctor Who</em> ever had. I’ll be interested to see how well his <em>Blake's 7</em> episodes stand up. He is the king of Victorian gothic; the creepy tale just dark and scary enough to hide behind the sofa, but not terrifying enough to smack of real world horrors. And, for every dark fairy tale, you need a comedy double act: the Gatherer and Marn; Engin and Spandrell; Jago and Litefoot. Genius.</p>

		<figure class="img-l">
			<img SRC="/Dear-Charlotte/img/charlotte-responds/oh-no-it-isnt/jago-and-litefoot.jpg" alt=""/>
			<figcaption>Jago and Litefoot have their own <a href="https://www.bigfinish.com/ranges/v/jago-litefoot">audio spin-off series</a>.</figcaption>
		</figure>

		<p>It’s fair to say there’s a large amount of irony and comedy in both pantomime and <em>Doctor Who</em>. But, in <em>Doctor Who</em>, while there’s often a nod and a wink to the audience, with the best of the stories, as with the sets, the actors don’t play for laughs.</p>
		<p>Just so it’s out of my head, here’s a list of bewildering moments when <em>Doctor Who</em> noticed the audience (from memory so apologies for misquotes):</p>
		<p><q>And a happy Christmas to all of you back home...</q></p>
		<p><q>We’ve got four minutes...’ (holds up five fingers)</q></p>
		<p><q>I think this is not Hyde Park...</q></p>
		<p><q>And now on <jargon type="BBC"/> 1, a brand new <jargon type="sci-fi"/> series...</q></p>
		<p>That’s enough of that.</p>

		<h2>5) But...no romance</h2>
		<p>The handsome prince is where the metaphor falls down. Sub-characters do seem to find happiness (normally off screen and after the credits roll) but it’s all wrapped in tissue paper and <abbr title="trichlorophenylmethyliodosalicyl">TCP</abbr>. At least until New <em>Who</em> and I can’t be bothered talking about the ins and outs of Doctor-Snog here.</p>

		<h2>So what have we learned?</h2>
		<p>There are many other elements for discussion around this topic, but most people would fall short of reading a 3,000 word essay. <note>Some of you have probably drifted off already.</note> The latter Tom Baker era is often cited as too comedy heavy; but for me, the panto elements in <em>Doctor Who</em> got a lot stronger in the 80s and later John Nathan-Turner era. Indeed, this piece is slightly inspired by my reading the book <q cite="https://www.theguardian.com/books/2013/mar/22/jnt-scandalous-doctor-who-review">JNT: the life and scandalous times of John Nathan-Turner</q>. <note>See? Textual references. It’s pure <jargon type="PhD"/>.</note></p>

		<figure class="img-r">
			<img SRC="/Dear-Charlotte/img/charlotte-responds/oh-no-it-isnt/peter-pan.jpg" alt=""/>
			<figcaption>Bonnie Langford dressed as Peter Pan with Colin Baker</figcaption>
		</figure>

		<p>John Nathan-Turner was a terrific fan of music hall and pantomime. For anyone who doubts that: here’s a photo of Colin Baker and Bonnie Langford dressed as Peter Pan (shudders).</p>
		<p>It seems from the book as though light entertainment really was John Nathan-Turner’s first love. He often, apparently, cast the <em>Who</em> actors in his own plays and took rehearsal time for these rather than <em>Doctor Who</em>.<note>That’s like, I dunno, writing a panto for your friends and making them star in it because it’s the only way you’ll see your work performed. Which is something I’ve never sunk to.</note></p>
		<p>Harsh critics might suggest this is reflected in the under-rehearsed feel to a lot of later stories. But let’s face it, whatever the era, <em>Doctor Who</em> never did suffer from ‘too much’ rehearsal time. Or too large an effects budget.</p>
		<p><em>Doctor Who</em> has more than 50 years of history and with any show that turns over its regular cast, producers and writers so often, there will be people who love or hate certain eras. Everyone has their own ‘<em>Who</em>’ that, for them, is the pinnacle. For me, it’s the Hinchcliffe era. For others, it might be the period just before it came off air.</p>
		<p>While John Nathan-Turner wasn’t my favourite, he was the reason many people (including me) came to discover the show. Again, the book suggests it wasn’t his first love and in fact ended up being something of an albatross. And for all his love of the innocence of music hall, some of his stories have a particularly dark element to them. Interestingly, while his persona was very much larger-than-life, complete with Hawaiian shirts and big grin, the book often shows a man who struggled with life and the goals he would never realise.</p>
		<p>Eric Saward, regular writer of the John Nathan-Turner period, mentions his colleague was fond of ‘a walk down ending’. Saward, like Robert Holmes, wanted to show the darkness side by side with the humour and glitter. To use a literary reference, Saward wanted <em>The Third Man</em>, rather than <em>Brighton Rock</em>.<note>Yes, ok strictly that’s a filmic reference as <em>Brighton Rock</em>, the book, had a much bleaker ending…oh look you try writing this stuff.</note></p>
		<p>Anyway, I think the point I was trying to make, is that where <em>Doctor Who</em> works well is when the balance of dark and light is just right. Pantomimes are, after all, based on fairy tales. Some of those can be really Grimm.<note>See what I did there?</note> The regular cast provide us the stability that we can be secure in being scared. We know that the ending will be ‘right’ even if it isn’t ‘good’ or ‘happy’.</p>
		<p>As all essays require a conclusion, here it is: real happiness exists side by side with sadness. This is, coincidentally, the moral behind the John Nathan-Turner era Thatcher-crit story <em>The Happiness Patrol</em>.<note>Also a story which put me off the flavour ‘strawberry’ for a long time.’</note></p>
		<p>My literary career? It’s behind me.</p>

	</content>
</page>
