<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="/Dear-Charlotte/xslt/page.xslt"?>
<page>
	<meta>
		<description>A subjective introduction to Blake's 7, from the perspective of someone who grew up with it.</description>
		<path>/Dear-Charlotte/about-blakes-7/</path>
	</meta>
	<content type="main">
		<h1>An introduction to <em>Blake's&#160;7</em></h1>
		<p><em>Blake's 7</em> feels like <em>my</em> show. More than <em>Star Trek</em>. More than <em>Lost in Space</em>. And yes, more than your husband, The Doctor. I would greedily devour any sci-fi as a child, regardless of quality. But for some reason, we would watch <em>Blake's 7</em> as a family. I suspect this made me believe that it was <em>serious</em> sci-fi. For <em>adults</em>.</p>
		<p>It didn't feel like it to me at the time, but the 1970s were pretty grim in the <jargon type="UK"/>. Unemployment. Strikes. Power cuts. Domestic terrorism. Art tends to reflect life and when Terry Nation<note>Who, as you'll know, Charlotte, inventor of the Daleks</note> wrote <em>Blake's 7</em>, he went for a darker tone than his scripts for <em>Doctor Who</em>.</p>
		<p>I suspect he was aiming at a more serious audience. But I don't think that was understood by all of the crew.</p>
		
		<figure>
			<img src="/Dear-Charlotte/img/cast-photo.jpg" alt=""/>
			<figcaption>Series two cast photo.</figcaption>
		</figure>

		<h2>Per ardua ad astra<note><q><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Per_ardua_ad_astra">Through adversity to the stars</a></q></note></h2>
		<p><em>Blake's 7</em>, like most film and television, is the product of many different disciplines. Terry Nation may have tried to establish its tone in his screenplays, but what's striking about it today is how the people who worked on the show pulled it in different directions.</p>
		<p>After <em>Blake's 7</em> went off the air in 1981, I didn't see an episode of it again until I found an early <jargon type="VHS"/> release in a charity shop around 1999. I excitedly carried it home and began to watch. It was a horrific experience, watching my childhood memories collide with what I saw with adult eyes for the first time.</p>
		<p>Watching that <jargon type="VHS"/>, I listened to actors reciting the scripts as if they were Shakespeare. No naturalism or method, just projecting to the back row of an imaginary theatre.</p>
		<p>Now, some of the performances feel more like pantomime. Broad, even camp acting styles, with tongue firmly in cheek, a sly wink at the camera never far away. This never happens in American sci-fi. No matter the quality of American <jargon type="TV"/>, they put on a good show of taking it seriously.</p>
		<p>This is why, Charlotte, I was asking you if Tom Baker talks about acting style in <a href="http://www.tombakerofficial.com/biography/excerpts-from-toms-autobiography/">his autobiography</a>. My working assumption is that British actors at that time went through stage school, then <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Repertory_theatre">repertory theatre</a> then finally they might get a shot at telly. I suspect most of them saw the script was science fiction, assumed it was aimed at children, and acted accordingly.</p>
		<p>But here's the thing: there <em>is</em> quality there, but it's well hidden. It's all too easy to make jokes about the production values or the delivery. Which is why that's exactly what I'll be doing (hello, and welcome to the Internet). But hopefully I'll remember to note what's actually <em>good</em> about the show too.<note>It's the scripts. It's <em>always</em> the scripts</note></p>

	</content>
</page>