<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="/Dear-Charlotte/xslt/page.xslt"?>
<page>
	<meta>
		<description>Episode 2: Space Fall. Blake, Vila, Avon, Jenna and Gan try to take over The London but are foiled by Vila's comic timing. Instead, they're put on board The Liberator by the crew of The London and are like "kthanxby".</description>
		<path>/series-1/episode-2-space-fall/</path>
		<type>episode</type>
	</meta>
	<content type="main">
		<h1>Episode 2: Space Fall</h1>
		<p>In the last episode, we learnt that Blake used to be a resistance fighter, before his brain got scrubbed. He gets framed for crimes and sentenced to live out his days on Cygnus Alpha, a prison planet. <em>Space Fall</em> starts with him on the <em>London</em>, a prison transport ship.</p>
		<p>So while <a href="/series-1/episode-1-the-way-back/">The Way Back</a> was (at least partially) a legal drama, <em>Space Fall</em> is more of a prison escape.</p>
		<p><em>Space Fall</em> starts with quite a nice bit of character building between the crew of the <em>London</em>. The captain, Laylan<note>Laylan is played by Glyn Owne, who also played Jack Rolf in the TV series <em>Howard's Way</em>, which my family obsessively watched, because it featured sailing. It was <em>nonsense</em>.</note> does some light &quot;bants&quot; with his bridge crew, Raiker<note>Who's a <em>diiiiiiiiiiiiiiiiiick</em></note> and Artix<note>Who seems quite sweet</note>.</p>
		
		<ross>
			<p>What I like about the opening scene is it establishes the characters and leaves the audience confused as to where the focus of the episode is. Coming after <em>The Way Back</em>, this seems to establish a theme of avoiding black and white moral judgements and showing the action from other perspectives.</p>
		</ross>

		<p>This twat:</p>
		
		<biog>
			<src>/img/characters/raiker.png</src>
			<info type="Name">Raiker</info>
			<info type="Job">First Commander</info>
			<info type="Dramatic role">Antagonist</info>
			<info type="Creep level">8</info>
			<info type="Most likely to die">Being sucked out of a tube</info>
		</biog>

		
		<p>...goes through to the back of the ship where the prisoners are, and does his welcome speech. Then makes a creepy pass at <a href="/about-blakes-7/jenna-stannis/">Jenna</a>.</p>
		
		<ross>
			<p>I like the way women are treated in Blake's 7, in general. Their gender seem to be utterly irrelevant in defining their personalties and tends to be ignored by in-world characters too. Raiker's creepiness isn't reflected by any other character and we later find out that Blake is primarily interested in Jenna for her piloting skills. Avon and Vila don't seem to consider her at all.</p>
			<h2>The good guys wear black</h2>
			<p>But I'm getting ahead of myself. The important thing is that we finally get to meet Avon. He scared me as a child, because he makes his motivations quite clear to everyone - he wants to save his own skin and, if possible, be rolling in credits while he does it. However, viewed from adult perspective, he's clearly the best character. <a href="/about-blakes-7/kerr-avon/">I've written more about Avon elsewhere</a>.</p>
		</ross>
		
		<char>
			<p>Doctor Who has been criticised as James Bond and the bikinied lovelies. For me <a href="/charlotte-responds/women-in-the-fourth-doctor-era/">the 4th Doctor era girls</a> were more progressive than modern Who. And had better clothes.</p>
		</char>
		
		<p>Blake immediately starts plotting to take over the <em>London</em>. While this is happening, the bridge crew notice an unscheduled space battle. Throughout the episode, stray shots and I dunno shock waves? pound the ship. Everyone shimmies about while the camera shakes, but to be honest, it's slightly better done than <em>Star Trek</em>.</p>
		<p>So while Blake is gestating his plan, <a href="/about-blakes-7/olag-gan/">Gan</a> is just sort of there. He never really gets introduced. One minute he's moping about in the background like an extra waiting for his tea break, the next he's Little Johning himself about the place, gurning and wrestling with supporting artists.</p>
		
		<h2>Super Nova</h2>
		<p>Blake hatches a plan which involves Avon turning off the cameras by taking over the computer, which he gains access to via a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jefferies_tube">Jefferies Tube</a>. Avon is delayed because there's a technician in the computer room, so Blake starts to worry. Nova, a rubbish character who sort of hangs about with Blake's gang like an oniony fart, offers to go after him because he's <q>not done anything yet</q>. He gets foamed to death:</p>

		<blockquote class="imgur-embed-pub" lang="en" data-id="g6kREJR"><a href="//imgur.com/g6kREJR">A Redshirt gets a private foam party in a Jefferies tube</a></blockquote><script async="" src="//s.imgur.com/min/embed.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
		
		<h2>Vagslaining</h2>
		<p>The foam is quite a nice, hard-<jargon type="sci-fi"/> idea: the <em>London</em> has a double hull and if the outer layer is pierced, the compartment is isolated and then filled with foam, which instantly hardens. This makes perfect sense in terms of world building, but is also narratively useful for killing off Nova the twit. Plus, the exposition which explains this comes from Jenna<note>Of <em>course</em> Jenna would know this: she's a pilot.</note>. Terry Nation gets a <em>woman</em> to do the mansplaining.</p>
		
		<p>Avon finally stops lurking in the Jefferies Tube and has a rubbish fight (which he wins) then does some hacking with the aerial of a transistor radio.</p>
		
		<ross>
			<p>The fight scenes in <em>Blake's 7</em> are weird. Most seems to be performed by the cast<note>Rather than stunt performers</note> and the choreography seems to be made up on the spot. Without the fast-cutting style of modern cinema (for which I'm personally thankful), you've got all the time in the world to admire the sight of two British character actors in their mid-thirties trying not to hit each other in the face. I can only assume they were put in there with such frequency due to the popularity of wrestling on television at the time.</p>
		</ross>
		
		<char>
			<p>Tom Baker and cast weren't allowed to do their own fighting after short sighted Louise Jameson threw a knife at a camera man and <a href="/charlotte-responds/stage-fighting/">Tom Baker broke his collarbone</a>.</p>
		</char>

		<p>Blake gets bored waiting for Avon to hack open the doors, so he gets Gan to force the guard to open the door. Gan does the world's most sensual high-five:</p>

		<blockquote class="imgur-embed-pub" lang="en" data-id="yqnnRGv"><a href="//imgur.com/yqnnRGv">Gan is introduced.</a></blockquote><script async="" src="//s.imgur.com/min/embed.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
		
		<p>So the prisoners escape and Blake, Jenna and Vila end up together, barricaded in the computer room.</p>
		
		<h2>Death by dad joke</h2>
		<p>The rest of the prisoners are recaptured, due to Vila's comic timing: Gan overpowers two guards while aggressively gurning, Vila and another prisoner grab their guns. Then two <em>more</em> guards turn up. Gan says <q>drop your guns</q>, and Vila immediately complies.</p>
		
		<p>Leylan is aware that something large is on a collision course with the <em>London</em> and that Blake's control of the computer leaves him helpless to avoid it. He negotiates with Blake through the door. Raiker asks for a <q>free hand</q> to resolve the crisis, to which Leylan agrees, out of desperation.</p>

		<h2>Loggerheads</h2>
		<p>Blake, Jenna and Avon discuss how they can get out of their predicament. This is a really interesting scene because it's both everything which is right and wrong with <em>Blake's 7</em>. Its purpose is to establish character: Blake is an idealist. Avon is cold and practical. Jenna is looking for someone or some<em>thing</em> to believe in. The problem is that while the characters are well defined and interesting, the dialogue isn't how any human discusses their political beliefs. But don't take my word for it: read this script I found in Sally Knyvette's dressing room:</p>

		<blockquote class="screenplay">
			<header>
				<p><b>B</b><b>B</b><b>C</b> <b>tv</b></p>
				<h2>Blake's 7</h2>
				<h3>&quot;Space Fall&quot;</h3>
			</header>

			<p>Cut to:</p>
			<p><abbr title="Interior">Int</abbr>. computer room</p>
			<dl>
				<dt>Jenna</dt>
				<dd><ins>(to Blake)</ins> What do you think they'll do?</dd>
				<dt>Blake</dt>
				<dd>Their time's running out.</dd>
				<dt>Jenna</dt>
				<dd>So's ours.</dd>
				<dt>Blake</dt>
				<dd>We ... have less to lose.</dd>
				<dt>Avon</dt>
				<dd>You may have, but I value my life.</dd>
				<dt>Jenna</dt>
				<dd><ins>(to Blake)</ins> Assuming they <em>do</em> land us somewhere, what then?</dd>
				<dt>Blake</dt>
				<dd>Find a way of getting back to Earth.</dd>
				<dt>Jenna</dt>
				<dd>Back to <em>Earth</em>?</dd>
			</dl>

			<footer class="clearfix">
				<p>Commercial and in confidence</p>
				<p>Page 30 of 52</p>
			</footer>
		</blockquote>

		<blockquote class="screenplay">
			<header>
				<p><b>B</b><b>B</b><b>C</b> <b>tv</b></p>
				<h2>Blake's 7</h2>
				<h3>&quot;Space Fall&quot;</h3>
			</header>
			
			<dl>
				<dt>Blake</dt>
				<dd>Yes: that's where the heart of the federation is. <em>I intend to see that heart torn out</em>.</dd>
				<dt>Avon</dt>
				<dd><ins>(to Blake)</ins>I thought you were probably insane!</dd>
				<dt>Blake</dt>
				<dd><ins>(with weird intensity)</ins> <em>That's possible</em>. They butchered my family, my friends. They murdered my past and gave me tranquilised dreams!</dd>
				<dt>Jenna</dt>
				<dd>At least you're still alive.</dd>
				<dt>Blake</dt>
				<dd><ins>(shouting, weirdly)</ins> No! Not until free men can think and speak!
				<ins>(Calmer)</ins>
				Not until ... <em>power</em> is back with the honest man.</dd>
				<dt>Avon</dt>
				<dd><ins>(to Blake)</ins> Have you even met an honest man?</dd>
				<dt>Jenna</dt>
				<dd><ins>(looking at Blake)</ins> Perhaps.</dd>
			</dl>

			<footer class="clearfix">
				<p>Commercial and in confidence</p>
				<p>Page 31 of 52</p>
			</footer>
		</blockquote>

		<blockquote class="screenplay">
			<header>
				<p><b>B</b><b>B</b><b>C</b> <b>tv</b></p>
				<h2>Blake's 7</h2>
				<h3>&quot;Space Fall&quot;</h3>
			</header>
			
			<dl>
				<dt>Avon</dt>
				<dd><ins>(with slightly crazy eyes)</ins> Listen to me: wealth is the only reality. And the only way to obtain wealth is to take it away from somebody else. <em>Wake up, Blake</em>. You may not be tranquilised any longer, but you're still dreaming.</dd>
				<dt>Jenna</dt>
				<dd>Maybe <em>some</em> dreams are worth having.</dd>
				<dt>Avon</dt>
				<dd><ins>(to Jenna)</ins> You don't <em>really</em> believe that?</dd>
				<dt>Jenna</dt>
				<dd><ins>(embarrassed)</ins> No, but I'd like to.</dd>
				<dt>Blake</dt>
				<dd>Yes. Well, you've asked me what I'm gonna do, and I've told you. What you do is up to yourselves.</dd>
				<dt>Avon</dt>
				<dd>Right. A new identity. A job in the Federation banking system. Three months with their computers I could lift a hundred million credits and nobody would know where they went. <em>Then</em> let anyone try and touch me.</dd>
				<dt>Blake</dt>
				<dd>And the rest?</dd>
				<dt>Avon</dt>
				<dd>Have the same chance that I have.</dd>
				<dt>Blake</dt>
				<dd>You don't really believe that?</dd>
			</dl>
			
			<footer class="clearfix">
				<p>Commercial and in confidence</p>
				<p>Page 32 of 52</p>
			</footer>
		</blockquote>
		
		<ross>
			<p>Let's take stock a bit. How do you think this episode's going? More importantly, <em>where</em> do you think this episode's going?</p>
			<p>If this <em>was</em> a prison drama, we've covered a lot of the basics:</p>
			<ul>
				<li>Introduction of cruel warden</li>
				<li>Escape attempt</li>
				<li>Attempted take over, leading to negotiation with the authorities<note>It's never explained what happened to the guard Gan held hands with, so we don't get a <em>hostage</em> negotiation.</note></li>
			</ul>
			<p>Sure, we've not had a new inmate meet Mr. Big or an unpleasant shower scene, but perhaps that's in the post for the next episode.</p>
			<p>However, this is <em>Blake's 7</em>, and Terry Nathan's a bit playful. He's not interested in the three act structure or genre conventions. He wants to have a bit of fun, within the confines of his dystopian future. Watch what happens next:</p>
		</ross>
		
		<h2>Neutron blaster diplomacy</h2>
		<p>Raiker's negotiation tactic is to kill off prisoners every thirty seconds until Blake surrenders. He kills two before Blake gives up, then gloats and punches Blake in the stomach. He somehow manages to look camp doing this. I think it's his hair.</p>
		
		<ross>
			<p>See? The whole escape attempt failed (much like Blake's defence at his trial). Terry's determined to keep us on our toes.</p>
		</ross>
		
		<h2>Technosexuality</h2>
		<p>The crew of the <em>London</em> get the computer working again and see the alien ship for the first time. They try and hail her, but she appearers to be drifting and abandoned. Raiker wants to board her and claim salvage.</p>
		<p>They extend a <q>transfer tube</q> into what for all the world looks like a face:</p>
		
		<figure class="img-r">
			<img SRC="/Dear-Charlotte/img/series-1/episode-2-space-fall/transfer-tube-face.jpg" alt="Not the face"/>
			<figcaption>Not the face!</figcaption>
		</figure>
		
		<p>Leylan sends over a bunch of guards to the ship, but they get killed while apparently being reunited with whispering loved ones. Raiker suggests sending prisoners, so Blake, Jenna and Avon board board the ship. It projects images into their minds of their loved ones suffering, using sort of trippy editing and ACTING. But because Blake is used to having his mind rubbed out or something, he manages to resist<note>Perhaps Blake resists because he's unable to love.</note>.</p>
		<p>Raiker comes over to the ship, to make sure Blake doesn't bugger off with it. Before he's out of the transfer tube, he spots Blake trying to shut the hatch. He shoots his baster so hard, it crosses the boundary between 16mm film stock and video tape. But luckily, Jenna managed to get the ship moving and Raiker gets sucked into space.</p>
		<p>Blake instructs Jenna to follow the <em>London</em> to Cygnus Alpha, so they can free the rest of the prisoners, and have a crew. END TITLES.</p>
		
		<h2>Watch <em>Space Fall</em> on YouTube</h2>
		<youtube id="vpqQPKjs27o"/>
	</content>
</page>