<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="/xslt/page.xslt"?>
<page>
	<meta>
		<description>Episode 8: Duel. The Liberator holeds up around an apparently dead planet, after fleeing the Federation. Travis attacks, but is stopped by magic space magic and Blake and Travis are forced to do battle in a woodland. Blake has the help of Jenna, Travis his Mutoid pilot. Blake wins but chooses not to kill Travis for solid, practical reasons.</description>
		<path>/series-1/episode-8-duel/</path>
		<type>episode</type>
	</meta>
	<content type="main">
		<h1>Episode 8: Duel</h1>
		<p>In the last episode, Avon and Cally got to play at Sherlock Holmes in a <del>haunted house</del> stricken spaceship. It had quite a complicated plot with red herrings and McGuffins. This time, Blake and Travis go to a wood and hit each other with sticks.</p>
		<figure class="img-r">
			<img src="/img/series-1/episode-8-duel/sinofar.jpg" alt=""/>
			<figcaption>Can anyone else hear <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=lcOxhH8N3Bo" title="Total Eclipse of the Heart official video">Bonnie Tyler</a>?</figcaption>
		</figure>
		<h2>Holding out for a hero</h2>
		<p>The episode starts with a <jargon type="TMS"/> of Sinofar, <jargon type="AKA"/> <q cite="http://blakes7.wikia.com/wiki/Duel_(dialogue_transcript)">The Guardian</q>, appearing among some polystyrene rocks as part of some strange ceremony on a semi-dead planet<note>The planet's also got some lovely foggy woodland.</note>. There are VIDEO EFFECTS. <em>So much video effects</em>. Sinofar's outfit has been designed with the Dad demographic in mind.</p>
		<p>Giroc, <jargon type="AKA"/> The Keeper, comes shuffling on set, dressed in hessian and carrying a staff. Jesus, what a mess. There's a lot of balls about <q cite="http://blakes7.wikia.com/wiki/Duel_(dialogue_transcript)">The Power</q> and <q cite="http://blakes7.wikia.com/wiki/Duel_(dialogue_transcript)">Balance</q>, but the upshot seems to be that both of them have some powers which they didn't choose and are obliged to remain on the planet for ... <em>reasons</em>.</p>

		<ross>
			<p>When I first saw this episode, I was in that brief, blissful period in a gynephilic's life when breasts had ceased to be nourishment, but had yet to become arousing. I was probably greatly relieved to be back in the cold embrace of space.</p>
		</ross>

		<figure class="img-r">
			<img src="/img/series-1/episode-8-duel/starburst-class.jpg" alt=""/>
			<figcaption>Travis' brand new Starburst Class ships (the previous generation of ships were called the <q>Opal Fruits Class</q>)</figcaption>
		</figure>

		<p>Finally, we're in ruddy space. We get to see Travis' new Starbust class ships, which he ordered from Servalan during <a href="/series-1/episode-6-seek-locate-destroy/">Seek-Locate-Destroy</a>. Travis is excited because he's finally tracked down Blake.</p>

		<h2>Charge not included</h2>
		<p><em>The Liberator</em> is looking for somewhere to recharge and take stock, as they've been fleeing Federation ships and their power banks are all run down. Avon calculates<note>Using a normal, 1978 calculator</note> that they need 48 hours to recharge.</p>
		<p>Blake, Jenna and Gan want to go down the planet to stretch their legs. Vila and Avon are staying behind and Cally is nowhere to be seen. She's probably doing some telepathy in her room. Vila has to squeeze past Avon, in order to operate the teleporter so Avon squares up to him, seemingly for his own entertainment.</p>

		<h2>Bodyformed for you</h2>
		<p>Back on Travis' ship, his Mutoid needs to change her blood serum vial. We learn that they're sort of vampires.</p>

		<blockquote class="imgur-embed-pub" lang="en" data-id="KxBWgyR"><a href="//imgur.com/KxBWgyR">View post on imgur.com</a></blockquote><script async="" src="//s.imgur.com/min/embed.js" charset="utf-8"></script>

		<ross>
			<p>I might be reading too much into this, but the scene where the Mutoid changes her blood serum seems to be disturbing on a number of levels. Travis uses the word <q cite="http://blakes7.wikia.com/wiki/Duel_(dialogue_transcript)">coyness</q>, when the Mutoid admits she wouldn't usually change the vial in front of an <q cite="http://blakes7.wikia.com/wiki/Duel_(dialogue_transcript)">unmodified</q>.</p>
			<p>The shape and size of the vessel, plus the use of the word <q cite="http://blakes7.wikia.com/wiki/Duel_(dialogue_transcript)">blood</q> suggest menstruation, which would have been almost as big a taboo as Vampirism in the <jargon type="UK"/> in 1978<note>Indeed advertising sanitary products on television was only made legal in the 1980s, but I can't seem to find the date when this actually happened. Perhaps I've finally found something which is too niche for the Internet: the history of sanitary products advertising in the <jargon type="UK"/>.</note>. I wonder if Terry Nation wasn't using <jargon type="sci-fi"/> to say something subversive about our<note>I have no idea who this <q>our</q> refers to.</note> discomfort with the menstrual cycle.</p>
		</ross>
		
		<char>
			<p>So I've just recalled that in <em>Destiny of the Daleks</em>, also written by Mr Nation, the Movellans had to recharge by changing their tubes. They were (spoiler) robots not vampires, but it does seem as though Terry had a thing for Tampax themed energy packs. Subtle feminist messaging? Or perhaps just shoddy plot recycling...</p>
		</char>

		<figure class="img-r">
			<img src="/img/series-1/episode-8-duel/relay-race.jpg" alt=""/>
			<figcaption>It's supposed to be a broken weapon.</figcaption>
		</figure>

		<p>Jenna, Blake and Gan turn up at the location used in the opening scene. Gan spots Sinofar and Giroc and tries to alert Blake, but the women have hidden behind a rock, or something. He thinks his <jargon type="EBE"/>'s on the blink. Gan finds a statue of some dude running a relay race.</p>
		<p>Gan spots Travis' fleet in the sky, using the Mark One Eyeball, so Blake raises the alarm and Vila teleports them back. Sinofar and Giroc get popcorn.</p>

		<h2>You need more RAM</h2>
		<p><em>The Liberator</em> doesn't have enough power to escape, and barely enough power to fight. Blake asks Zen what the battle computers think, and they suggest surrender<note>This is like using Google, and it telling you to get outside and go for a nice walk.</note>. The pursuit ships whittle away at Blake's power with plasma bolts but Blake works out that the one ship which <em>hasn't</em> fired must be Travis, so plans to ram it. Before the ships collide, some sort of space magic stops them from working and we get another <jargon type="TMS"/>. It goes on for ages and it <em>really</em> wants to be <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ou6JNQwPWE0" title="It's nine and a half minutes of Ligeti.">the stargate sequence from 2001</a> when it grows up.</p>

		<p>Giroc speaks to both crews and explains that they cannot use their ships then poofs Blake and Travis down to the planet. Sinofar and Giroc introduce themselves, so let's do that:</p>

		<biog>
			<src>/img/characters/sinofar.png</src>
			<info type="Name">Sinofar</info>
			<info type="Job">The Guardian</info>
			<info type="Dramatic role">Wise alien archetype, exciter of Dads</info>
			<info type="Structural model of the psyche component">Super-ego</info>
			<info type="Interests">Tumblr, scrap booking, Enya</info>
		</biog>

		<ross>
			<p>There's no polite way to say this but during the scene, Sinofar is crying out for bra. Come on, dear. You'll catch your death.</p>
		</ross>

		<biog>
			<src>/img/characters/giroc.png</src>
			<info type="Name">Giroc</info>
			<info type="Job">The Keeper</info>
			<info type="Dramatic role">Violence fan</info>
			<info type="Structural model of the psyche component">Id</info>
			<info type="Interests">Cackling, <jargon type="WWE"/>, Jethro Tull</info>
		</biog>

		<ross>
			<p>I like that Giroc is an old woman who doesn't conform to any stereotypes: she adores violence and insults Travis' stupidity loudly and often. I think people often assume that affirmative action or political correctness means we need to portray minorities in a positive light. I disagree: <em>any</em> non-stereotypical depiction is enough.</p>
		</ross>

		<h2>Let's settle this the old fashioned way</h2>
		<p>Their planet was in a state of constant war until it went nuclear and everyone died. Sinofar's plan is to get Travis and Blake to fight each other, in order to save the lives of their crew members who <em>would</em> have died, had they had their nice space battle. But she also wants them to understand what it's like to lose a loved one, so she takes one crew member from each ship to fight alongside them<note>Blake seems to recognise this as <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prisoner%27s_dilemma">the prisoner's dilemma</a>, and says to Travis <q cite="http://blakes7.wikia.com/wiki/Duel_(dialogue_transcript)">We could agree not to fight</q>. Travis ain't interested.</note>.</p>

		<p>Sinofar poofs Blake into a foggy wood with a sword. Giroc uses some magic to cause Blake pain, for some reason. It looks like this<note>There wasn't such a thing as strobe lighting warnings in 1978.</note>:</p>

		<blockquote class="imgur-embed-pub" lang="en" data-id="lP7ybxK"><a href="//imgur.com/lP7ybxK">It involves ACTING.</a></blockquote><script async="" src="//s.imgur.com/min/embed.js" charset="utf-8"></script>

		<p>Then she brings Travis in, who's very sporting, and gives Blake a chance to recover, when he could have just stabbed him up. Travis is just about to cut Blake's throat when Sinofar is all <q>nope!</q>, and restarts the contest. Giroc likes a bit of a rumble, see, where as Sinofar is all about TEACHING THESE PEOPLE LESSONS.</p>

		<figure>
			<figcaption class="h2">Characters in <jargon type="sci-fi"/> being forced to fight in an arena, for the edification of omnipotent beings</figcaption>
			<div class="timeline">
				<ol start="1918" class="clearfix"><!--  style="width: 5650px;" -->
					<li><time datetime="1918" class="details">The book <q>The Gods of Mars</q> is published. John Carter stabs white apes in an arena. On Mars, obv.</time></li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li><time datetime="1967-01-19" class="details bubble-left">The <em>Star Trek</em> episode <q>Arena</q> is broadcast in <jargon type="USA"/>. Captain Kirk repeatedly punches a lizard in the face, in the Hollywood hills.</time></li>
					<li><time datetime="1968-01-05" class="details">The <em>Star Trek</em> episode <q>The Gamesters of Triskelion</q> is broadcast in <jargon type="USA"/>. Captain Kirk punches <a href="http://www.startrek.com/watch_video/episode-preview-the-gamesters-of-triskelion" title="An original preview of the episode, from the time.">a wide selection of people in bikinis in the face</a>.</time></li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li><time datetime="1973" class="details">The book <q>Hunters of the Red Moon</q> by Marion Zimmer Bradley is published. Kidnapped humans fight aliens on a moon.</time></li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li><time datetime="1978-02-20" class="details">The <em>Blake's 7</em> episode <q>Duel</q> is broadcast. Blake, Jenna, Travis and a Mutoid go at each other, in a foggy wood just outside London.</time></li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li><time datetime="1985-10-18" class="details bubble-left">The film <q>Mad Max Beyond Thunderdome</q> is released. Mel Gibson punches members of the <jargon type="BDSM"/> community in a desert.</time></li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li><time datetime="1988-10-21" class="details bubble-left">The film <q>The Running Man</q> is released. Arnold Schwarzenegger punches people while wearing a leotard, in a sound stage.</time></li>
					<li><time datetime="1989-03-29" class="details">The film <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=5qwvUnFb-Yw" title="That's the whole movie on YouTube. Seriously."><q>Arena</q></a> is released in West Germany. No-one notices. It features Armin Shimerman, who later played <q>Quark</q> in <em>Star Trek: Deep Space Nine</em>.</time></li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li><time datetime="1993-07-23" class="details">The film <q>Coneheads</q> is released. <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ACPaWsdqCjA" title="I watched this scene, and now I regret it.">Dan Aykroyd fights a stop-motion creature while wearing a nappy</a>.</time></li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li><time datetime="1996" class="details">The book <q>Contest</q> by Matthew Reilly is published. A radiologist fights aliens in a library.</time></li>

					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li><time datetime="2000-12-16" class="details">The film <q>Battle Royale</q> is released. A bunch of Japanese teenagers murder each other on an island. Plus <em>Star Trek: Voyager</em> did <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=DYUyTcoe0qw" title="Dwayne Johnson fights Seven of Nine">this</a>.</time></li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li><time datetime="2006" class="details bubble-left">The comic series <q>Planet Hulk</q> begins. The Hulk punches aliens in an arena.</time></li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li><time datetime="2008-09-14" class="details">The book <q>The Hunger Games</q> is published. A bunch of <em>American</em> teenagers murder each other in a wood.</time></li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li><time datetime="2012-03-23" class="details">The film <q>The Hunger Games</q> is released in the <jargon type="USA"/>. <em>Jennifer Lawrence</em> murders a bunch of teenagers a wood.</time></li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li>&#160;</li>
					<li><time datetime="2016-01-24" class="details">The film <q>Lazer Team</q> is released in the <jargon type="USA"/>. Four losers battle a Champion in a stadium.</time></li>
				</ol>
			</div>
			<footer><small>Thanks to the <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/scifi">/r/scifi</a> readers for providing me with suggestions for this timeline.</small></footer>
		</figure>

		<h2>Explore the world through someone else's eyes.</h2>
		<p>The crew of <em>The Liberator</em> get to watch the whole thing on their view-screen. But before Blake goes boom-boom behind a tree with his crew all watching through their fingers, he bumps into Jenna, who tells him about the live feed. Blake starts sharpening some sticks, just like kids would do in the woods, when given half a chance.</p>
		<p>Travis gets his Mutoid pilot gal-pal:</p>

		<biog>
			<src>/img/characters/mutoid.png</src>
			<info type="Name">The Mutoid previously known as Keyeira</info>
			<info type="Job">Pilot / Travis' wingman</info>
			<info type="Dramatic role">Introduction to Mutoids</info>
			<info type="Favourite drink">O Negative</info>
			<info type="Favourite thing about being a mutoid">The rainproof headgear, plus the medical insurance perks.</info>
			<info type="Metal level">Slayer</info>
		</biog>

		<p>They do some talking in front of a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chroma_key">chroma key</a> screen. Just as Blake predicted, Travis plans to set a trap. Cally, watching from <em>The Liberator</em> thinks that Travis is making a mistake, by setting a trap: <q cite="http://blakes7.wikia.com/wiki/Duel_(dialogue_transcript)">That sort of war is best fought on the move</q><note>I like this, because it gives us insight into Cally's guerrilla warfare days.</note>.</p>
		<p>Night falls and the stock sound effects suggest (but don't show) that there are large, frightening creatures in the woods. Travis and his Mutoid have constructed a sort of spiky frame. Travis talks to his Mutoid about her previous life but she is beyond uninterested in the conversation. He tries to upset her, by talking about who she was, before she was surgically transformed into a Mutoid, but she is so indifferent, he gives up and falls asleep.</p>

		<h2>Transhuman transfusion</h2>
		<p>In the morning, Travis finds a number of bats at the foot of the tree. His Mutoid trapped them and drank their blood, because she's metal <jargon type="AF"/>.</p>
		<p>Blake climbs a tree to try and spot Travis. Jenna hears the Mutoid rustling about and goes after her. She is immediately captured and tied up then the Mutoid extends a needle toward Jenna's neck, so she can drink her blood. Travis stops her, for some reason. Perhaps he's squeamish.</p>

		<h2>Sticking together</h2>
		<p>Travis shouts to Blake, asking him to give himself up. Blake spots Jenna, tied up next to a tree. He approaches her and Travis bellows <q cite="http://blakes7.wikia.com/wiki/Duel_(dialogue_transcript)">Now!</q>. Suspended above him is Travis' rickety frame of spiky death. The Mutoid hacks away at the rope holding it aloft, but Jenna and Blake escape. While Jenna gets rid of her bonds, Travis and Blake have a stave fight. Then the Mutoid arrives, and Jenna and her have a fight too. Blake wins his fight, but refuses to kill Travis, despite Cally's telepathic goading. Avon shakes his head, while smiling to himself. Clearly, he predicted this outcome.</p>
		<p>Blake explains to Giroc why he didn't kill Travis:  if he <em>had</em> Travis would be replaced. And Blake knows he can beat Travis.</p>

		<ross>
			<p>This is a small twist. Usually, this kind of story goes one of a few ways:</p>
			<ul>
				<li>Omnipotent beings teach the protagonist something, which the antagonist refuses to learn</li>
				<li>The protagonist teaches the omnipotent being something, and raises their opinion of humanity in the process</li>
				<li>We (the audience) learn something about the protagonist and the antagonist, in the means by which they do battle</li>
				<li><q cite="http://tvtropes.org/pmwiki/pmwiki.php/Main/ItWasWithYouAllAlong">The power was inside you all along</q></li>
				<li>(Of the creature the protagonist is forced to fight) <q cite="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=GH0YPXb49q0">We are not so different, you and I</q></li>
			</ul>
			<p>While we <em>do</em> learn about Blake and Travis<note>For example, for all Travis' claims to Servalan that he wants to work with Mutoids for their cold efficiency, he's disappointed that his Mutoid doesn't get riled up, when he talks about her previous life.</note>, Blake doesn't refuse to kill Travis for moral reasons, or because that would make him what he hates. He refuses to kill Travis out of utility: because he thinks he's better at this than Travis is.</p>
			<p>I like this, because it avoids <em>Star Trek</em>'s smug sense of moral superiority.</p>
		</ross>

		<p><em>The Liberator</em> gets a full charge, and pulls away.</p>

		<h2>Spurn the respawn</h2>
		<p>The Mutoid is dead, having run out of blood. Sinofar offers to return her to life, but Travis is like <q>whatevs</q>, then demands to go back to his ship. Sinofar restores her life anyway. Travis plans to subject her to court martial, because she didn't cut the rope fast enough. The mutoid suggests that if she'd been allowed to drink Jenna's blood, she'd have been right as rain. <em>Silly Travis</em>.</p>
		<p>Travis sets a course to follow Blake.</p>

		<h2>Watch <em>Duel</em> on YouTube</h2>
		<youtube id="kUI6IEU6sA0"/>
	</content>
</page>